ANCHOR IN AMERICA.
>> THAT'S "NIGHTLY NEWS."
I'M LESTER HOLT.
♪♪
>>> GOOD EVENING.
THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR JOINING
US.
I'M MORGAN RADFORD.
WELCOME TO SPECIAL COVERAGE OF
THE SECOND NIGHT OF THE FIRST
DEMOCRATIC DEBATE OF THE 2020
ELECTION CYCLE RIGHT HERE ON NBC
NEWS NOW.
THIS IS A LIVE LOOK AT THE
DEBATE STAGE WHERE IN JUST ABOUT
AN HOUR, TEN MORE DEMOCRATIC
PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATES WILL
TAKE THEIR PLACE AT THOSE
PODIUMS.
WE HEARD FROM THE FIRST TEN LAST
NIGHT ON THAT SAME STAGE AND
AGAIN THEY ARE STANDING BASED ON
THEIR RESULTS IN PUBLIC POLLING
THROUGH JUNE 12th.
TAKING THE CENTER POSITION,
FORMER VICE PRESIDENT JOE BIDEN
AND BERNIE SANDERS.
THEY'LL BE FLANKED BY BUTTIGIEG
AND KAMALA HARRIS AND JUST A BIT
ABOUT HOW THE NIGHT IS GOING TO
WORK ON THE SECOND NIGHT.
SAME DEAL.
CANDIDATES HAVE 60 SECONDS TO
ANSWER QUESTIONS.
30 SECONDS TO RESPOND TO
FOLLOW-UP QUESTIONS AND THEN A
FINAL CHANCE TO MAKE THEIR
CLOSING STATEMENTS.
BUT BEFORE THE NIGHT BEGINS,
WE'RE HERE TO PREVIEW THE ISSUES
THAT ARE LIKELY GOING TO COME
UP.
WHAT WE'RE GOING TO HEAR AND
THEN BREAK DOWN WHY THOSE ISSUES
MATTER.
OF COURSE, TONIGHT, ALL EYES
WILL BE ON VICE PRESIDENT JOE
BIDEN.
HE'S LEADING THE REST OF THE
PACK IN THE POLLS.
THAT'S AT 32%.
SENATOR SANDERS IS POLLING
SECOND BASED ON THE REAL CLEAR
POLITICS AVERAGE.
WE SEE HIM AT 17%.
AS A POINT OF COMPARISON,
SANDERS HAS ALREADY BEEN TRYING
TO CONTRACT HIS RECORD WITH
BIDEN'S.
BUT IF LAST NIGHT WAS ANY
INDICATION, IT COULD BE THE
CANDIDATES THERE AT THE BOTTOM
OF YOUR SCREEN WHO ARE POLLING
IN THE LOWER SINGLE DIGITS WHO
COULD BE THE MOST WILLING TO
TAKE SHOTS AT THOSE STANDING IN
THE CENTER STAGE.
IN THE CENTER OF THE PODIUM AND
THOSE ARE THE CANDIDATES POLLING
MORE HIGH.
HERE TO HELP ME DIVE INTO THE
QUESTIONS, REPUBLICAN POLITICAL
CONSULTANT MICHAEL SINGLETON,
ALEX THOMPSON AND MSNBC
POLITICAL ANALYST SERLINA
MAXWELL.
>> HOW CAN WE EXPECT TO SEE
SOMETHING DIFFERENT TONIGHT?
>> IT'S GOING TO BE FAR MORE
COMBATANT.
HE CAN SAY, I AM THE GUY
>> THEY REPRESENT TWO DIFFERENT
WINGS OF THE DEMOCRATIC PARTY.
THE PROGRESSIVE WING AND MORE
MODERATE CENTRIST WING.
YOU'LL SEE THAT AND THEY'LL GO
AT EACH OTHER AND IT'S THE FIRST
TIME I'M SEEING IT.
>> ALEX, WHAT ABOUT THE BREAKOUT
STARS.
LAST NIGHT WE SAW A LOT OF
PEOPLE WERE TWEETING ABOUT
JULIAN CASTRO.
A LOT OF PEOPLE TALKING ABOUT
BOOKER.
DO WE EXPECT TO SEE A SIMILAR
BREAKOUT STAR TONIGHT.
>> YOU'RE ALREADY GOING TO HAVE
SOME, I GUESS, MORE EXOTIC
CANDIDATES WHEN YOU HAVE ANDREW
YANG, MARIANNE WILLIAMSON IN THE
RACE.
THEY'LL ATTRACT ATTENTION.
AND THEN EVEN PEOPLE LIKE
MICHAEL BENNET HAVE BENNETT, PE
CAMPAIGN SAY THEY EXPECT TO DRAW
A CONTRAST, THAT USUALLY MEANS
THEY WILL GO ON THE OFFENSIVE.
AND YOU HAVE MAYOR PETE AND
KAMALA RIGHT THERE.
KIRSTEN GILLIBRAND HAS BEEN
REALLY STRUGGLING TO GET THE
DONORS UP, AND SHE WILL TRY TO
MAKE HAD A MOMENT FOR HER LEVEL.
>> WITH SO MANY FRONT-RUNNERS ON
THE STAGE, HOW WILL THEY TRY TO
DISTINGUISH THEIR TACTICS
STRATEGICALLY IN TERMS OF
GETTING THEIR PLATFORM OUT
THERE?
>> I THINK BERNIE SANDERS HAS TO
HIT JOE BIDEN HARD AND SAY YOU
ARE NOT IN TOUCH WITH WHERE THE
CURRENT DEMOCRATIC PARTY, IS AND
WHAT'S INTERESTING IS TO SEE HOW
JOE BIDEN RESPONDS.
JOE BIDEN, WOULD I ARGUE, HAS A
BIT OF A TEMPERAMENT.
DOES HE SORT OF RISE ABOVE AND
SAY, OKAY, WHATEVER, I'M STILL
THE FRONT-RUNNER AND THE BEST
ONE AGAINST TRUMP OR DOES HE
SLING ARROW, IF YOU WILL, AT
BERNIE SANDERS WHICH WOULD GIVE
SOMEONE LIKE MAYOR PETE OR
KAMALA HARRIS AN OPPORTUNITY TO
ELEVATE THEMSELVES.
>> WHAT DO YOU MEAN WHEN YOU SAY
ABOUT THE TEMPER?
>> WHEN JOE BIDEN WAS
INTERVIEWING WITH AL SHARPTON
AND HE WAS PRESSING HIM HARD,
TRYING TO GIVE HIM EVERY
OPPORTUNITY TO APOLOGIZE, YOU
SAW A MOMENT WHERE HE GOT VERY
DEFENSIVE AND REFUSED TO
APOLOGIZE AND I WOULD VENTURE TO
SAY IF HE'S ATTACKED TOO MUCH,
IF HE LOSES SUCH TEMPER RATHER I
PREDICT THAT WE WILL SEE JOE
BIDEN SORT OF SAY I'M THE BEST
ONE TO DO THIS, I DON'T CARE
WHAT YOU HAVE TO SAY.
LOOK AT MY POLL NUMBERS AND THAT
MAY NOT RESONATE VERY WELL WITH
DEMOCRATIC VOTERS.
>> THE OTHER THING HE DOES IS HE
MAKES A JOKE WHEN IT'S NOT
APPROPRIATE TO MAKE A JOKE.
THE CONTROVERSY OVER HUGGING
PEOPLE WITHOUT ASKING FOR OR
TOUCHING PEOPLE WITHOUT THEIR
PERMISSION AND HE MADE A JOKE AT
AN EVENT SUBS KEPTLY, I'M
TALKING ABOUT LUCY FLORES, FOR
EXAMPLE, AND HE MADE A JOKE, AND
IT WAS VERY -- IT WAS VERY OUT
OF TOUCH.
IT WAS TONE DEAF GIVEN THE FACT
THAT THIS IS A SERIOUS
CONVERSATION SO I -- I HOPE THAT
HE DOESN'T GAFFE THAT WAY
SFWLEERT SPEAKING OF THE SERIOUS
CONVERSATION, WAS IT JUST ME OR
LAST NIGHT DID WE SEE THE
MOMENTS WHERE THE CANDIDATES
ALMOST LIKE TRIED TO OUTDEMOCRAT
EACH OTHER GO, AS FAR AS THEY
COULD TO THE LEFT, BUT IF THEY
DO THAT TONIGHT DO THEY RISK
THEN ALIENATING THE GENERAL
POPULATION?
>> I THINK THEY DO.
JOE BIDEN, KAMALA HEY, AND I
WOULD EVEN ARGUE MAYOR PETE IN
MANY WAYS ARE SORT I WOULD SAY
TRYING TO GET VOTERS FROM THE
SAME CENTRIST WING OF THE PARTY
THAT WE WERE JUST TALKING ABOUT.
I THINK BERNIE SANDERS, HOWEVER,
WILL TRY TO FOCUS ON SOME OF
WHAT ELIZABETH WARREN TALKED
ABOUT THE OTHER NIGHT.
HE HAVE'S GOING TO SHOWCASE TO
THOSE VOTERS THAT, YES,
ELIZABETH WARREN IS A GOOD
CANDIDATE BUT, REMEMBER, I'M THE
ORIGINAL GUY.
I'M THE ORIGINAL ONE WHO BROUGHT
US THESE IDEAS FOUR YEARS AGO IN
2016, AND NOW LOOK AT HOW I HAVE
SHAPED AND TRANSFORMED THE
DEMOCRATIC THAT'S RIGHT.
>> ALEX, WHAT DO YOU THINK?
>> ON THAT QUESTION I THINK YOU
HAVE GOT TO LOOK AT BIDEN AND
BENT AND LOOK AT KAMALA TO SEE
IF THEY TRY TO SAY I'M THE MOST
PROGRESSIVE.
BIDEN IS I'VE BEEN SO
PROGRESSIVE ALL THE TIME OR DOES
HE TRY TO STAKE OUT THE TIME AND
SAY I'M NOT LIKE BERNIE, NOT
GOING TO DO MEDICARE FOR ALL,
AND DOES HE START ARGUING FOR
THE CENTRIST WING THE PARTY OR
SAY I'M PROGRESSIVE ENOUGH AND
THAT DISTINCTION IS KEY.
YOU SAW EVERYONE SAYING I'M
PROGRESSIVE ENOUGH.
>> WHO DO YOU THINK POSES THE
BIGGEST THREAT TO BIDEN IN TERMS
OF POLICY?
WHO HAS THE MOST SIMILAR
POLICIES?
>> TODAY.
OH, TODAY.
I DON'T THINK THERE IS A DIRECT
CHALLENGE TODAY.
I THINK THE CHALLENGE IS
ELIZABETH WARREN, BUT THAT'S NOT
TODAY, RIGHT.
I THINK THE CONTRAST IS GOING TO
BE CAN BERNIE SANDERS ARTICULATE
THE SAME PROGRESSIVE VISION WITH
THE DETAILS, WITH THE MEAT.
>> BERNIE SANDERS.
>> AND IN ADDITION IS HE GOING
TO BE ABLE TO ADD ON TO THE
MOMENTUM HE CREATED IN 2016?
>> AND WHEN ABOUT THE OTHER
SIDE?
I MEAN, WHAT ABOUT THESE SWING
VOTERS AND PERHAPS SOME OF THOSE
TRUMP VOTERS, ARE THESE 2020
DEMOCRATIC CANDIDATES DOING
ENOUGH TO TRY TO SPEAK TO
CONSERVATIVES?
>> I DON'T THINK SO.
LOOK, I HAVE TO BE HONEST.
I THINK DEMOCRATS ARE MOVING TOO
FAR TO THE LEFSHTS AND I THINK
WHAT WE SAW LAST NIGHT, I THINK
WHAT WE WILL LIKELY HEAR FROM
BERNIE SANDERS IS NOT IN SYNC
WITH WHERE A VAST MAJORITY OF
THE COUNTRY IS AND I THINK HE
NEEDS TO BE CHALLENGED ON THE
FAR-FETCHING NOTION AND IDEAS,
HOW ARE YOU GOING TO GET THIS
STUFF PASSED, EVEN IF THE
DEMOCRATS WERE TO CONTROL THE
HOUSE AND SENATE MANY WITHIN THE
PARTY DON'T SUPPORT SOME OF
THOSE IDEAS AND I THINK BERNIE
SANDERS IS GOING TO HAVE A HARD
TIME TRYING TO CONTRAST, YES,
I'M THE GUY TO BRING THE COUNTRY
TOGETHER AND REACH OUT TO THE
DISAFFECTED VOTERS.
>> AND THE PARTY IS AT A POINT
WHERE THEY ARE TRYING TO
REDEFINE THEMSELVES, NOT ONLY
INTERNALLY BUT MORE TO WHAT
WE'LL SEE TONIGHT.
THANK YOU FOR STICKING AROUND
WITH US.
A LITTLE BIT LATER, WE'LL HAVE A
LONG NIGHT.
WE'LL TAKE A QUICK BREAK AND
STAY WITH US FOR SPECIAL
COVERAGE OF THE FIRST
PRESIDENTIAL DEMOCRATIC DEBATE
RIGHT HERE ON "NBC NEWS NOW."
>> LET'S HEAD OVER TO THE SPIN
ROOM NOW WHERE THE FINAL
PREPARATIONS ARE UNDER WAY
BEFORE THE CANDIDATES TAKE THE
STAPLING, AND AS YOU CAN SEE
THAT'S WHERE WE FIND NBC'S
GARRETT HAYES.
GARRETT, GOOD EVENING.
GIVE US A LITTLE BIT OF A TOUR.
SHOW US AROUND AND WHAT'S GOING
ON IN MIAMI NOW.
>> MORGAN, IN ABOUT TWO HOURS
THIS WILL BE THE CENTER OF THE
POLITICAL UNIVERSE IN WHICH ALL
THE CAMPAIGNS AND THEIR STAFF
WILL BE IN HERE TELLING US BRETT
LESLEY THAT EACH AND EVERY ONE
OF THEM WON THE DEBATE AND WHY
THEY WILL BE THE NEXT PRESIDENT
OF THE UNITED SATES, BUT FOR NOW
IT'S KIND OF THE CALM BEFORE THE
STORM.
THIS AREA WAS PACKED ALL NIGHT
LAST NIGHT.
IT WILL BE PACKED TO THE UNTIL
ABOUT 1:00 IN THE MORNING YOU
CAN SEE OUR SET IN THE
BACKGROUND.
ALL THE CANDIDATES DROPPING BY
HERE TO TALK ABOUT HOW THEY
PERFORMED, AND THEN THE
CANDIDATES, THEIR STAFF AND ALL
THESE REPORTERS, 700 OF US FROM
AROUND THE WORLD, COVERING THE
CAMPAIGN.
FOR NOW THOUGH THINGS ARE QUITE,
AND I HAVE TO TELL YOU THERE'S A
LITTLE BIT OF A DIFFERENT
ATMOSPHERE TONIGHT I THINK FOR
TWO REASONS.
NUMBER ONE, ALL THE CANDIDATES
INCLUDING THOSE WHO COMPETED
LAST NIGHT, PERFORMED LAST
NIGHT, HAVE NOW SEEN HOW THIS
PROCESS GOES, AND THE FOLKS WHO
ARE COMING UP TONIGHT KNOW A
LITTLE BIT ABOUT HOW THE
MODERATORS ARE TREATING THE
QUESTIONS AND HOW THE CANDIDATES
ARE LIKELY TO TREAT EACH OTHER
AND TONIGHT YOU HAVE MORE OF THE
EXPERIENCED DEBATERS ON THE
STAGE.
JOE BIDEN AND BERNIE SANDERS
HAVE BOTH DONE THE
MULTI-CANDIDATE PRESIDENTIAL
FORMULA BEFORE, AND EVEN THOUGH
THE OTHER CANDIDATES WHO HAVE
NOT KAMALA HARRIS, FOR EXAMPLE,
MICHAEL BENNETT, SOME OF THESE
SENATORS ARE A LITTLE MORE
PRACTICED IN THIS TYPE OF
DEBATING, SO I DO THINK IT'S A
LITTLE BIT LESS OF THAT NEAR
VOWS ENERGY THAN LAST NIGHT WHEN
SO MANY PEOPLE WERE LOOKING FOR
THE MOMENT TO BREAK OUT.
>> I WAS FOLLOWING YOU LAST
NIGHT ON TWITTER AND SEEING YOU
ON TELEVISION AND YOU HAD A
MOMENT IN THIS ROOM WITH BETO.
WHAT DID YOU LEARN AND WHAT WAS
THE SCOOP THAT YOU GOT LAST
NIGHT?
>> I THINK TWO THINGS.
NUMBER ONE, JULIAN CASTRO'S BIG
MOMENT WITH BETO O'ROUKE WAS NO
ACCIDENT.
THAT WAS VERY MUCH A PLANNED
MOMENT OF TRYING TO CONTRAST
WITH ANOTHER TEXAN ON A VERY
SPECIFIC ISSUE, TO PUT O'ROURKE
ON HIS BACK HEEL.
WHAT YOU SAW IN THAT EXCHANGE
WAS A DIFFERENCE IN STYLE AND
PREPARATION.
O'ROURKE SAID ALL ALONG HE'S NOT
MUCH OF A DEBATE-FOCUSED GUY.
HE'S A STORYTELLER AND WANTS TO
TELL THE STORY OF THE PEOPLE
HE'S MET AROUND THE COUNTRY AND
JULIAN CASTRO WANTED TO MAKE A
VERY SPECIFIC POINT ABOUT POLICY
AND WANTED TO MAKE IT AT BETO
O'ROUKE'S EXPENSE.
TEXAS IS A BIG STATE, BUT
THERE'S PROBABLY NOT ROOM ENOUGH
IN THIS RACE FOR TWO
UP-AND-COMERS FROM THE LONE STAR
STATE.
THEY COMPETE FOR DONORS AND
VOTERS AND ATTENTION.
AND THEY WILL COMPETE AGAIN
TOMORROW NIGHT.
CASTRO WILL BE IN AUSTIN AND
O'ROURKE'S CAMPAIGN ADDED AN
EVENT IN AUSTIN THIS AFTERNOON.
>> INTERESTING.
>> I ALSO SAW THAT FORMER
CHAIRMAN MICHAEL STEELE IS
SAYING JULIO IS TRYING TO PUNCH
SIDEWAYS AND YOU MENTIONED THE
STYLE AND THE PREPARATION.
BUT WHAT ABOUT THE STRATEGY?
HOW DO YOU THINK THE STRATEGY
WILL BE DIFFERENT TONIGHT?
>> INTERESTINGLY ENOUGH I THINK
THE TWO FRONT-RUNNERS IN THE
CENTER OF THE STAGE HAVE SIMILAR
STRATEGIES.
THEY WANT TO TALK ABOUT
THEMSELVES, THEIR RECORD AND
VISION FOR THE FUTURE AND A LOT
LESS THAN DONALD TRUMP.
EVERYONE ELSE ON THAT STAGE MAY
HAVE A DIFFERENT SET OF
OBJECTIVES.
I'M TALK ABOUT THE TWO
COLORADOANS HERE, JOHN
HICKENLOOPER AND MICHAEL
BENNETT.
I CAN SEE THEM HAVING THEIR EYES
ON BERNIE SANDERS.
THEY HAVE A VERY DIFFERENT
VISION FOR WHAT THE DEMOCRATIC
PARTY IS THE ALL ABOUT.
DO THEY WANT TO MIX IT UP ON
SOMEBODY THEY DESAGREE WITH ON
SOME OF THESE BIG QUESTIONS,
THIS ISSUE.
THIS DEBATE TONIGHT HAS TWO OF
THE MOST INTERESTING CANDIDATES.
TWO UNIQUE CANDIDATES ON THE
DEBATE STAGE AT THE SAME TIME,
ANDREW YANG AND MARIANNE
WILLIAMSON, BOTH OF WHOM HAVE
BIG FOLLOWS ONLINE AND PLATFORMS
THAT I THINK ARE SAY TO SAY
OUTSIDE THE DEMOCRATIC
MAINSTREAM AND THEY HAVE ELBOWED
THEIR WAY ON THE DEBATE STABLE
AND BOTH OF THEM ARE PRETTY WELL
PRIMED TO BRING THEIR MESSAGE TO
THE MASSES, PARTICULARLY YANG
WHO HAS SUCH A BIG ARM LINE
FOLLOWING.
ANY DROP COULD BE HAVE -- A LOT
OF THE WAYS THAT BERNIE SANDERS
DID BACK IN 2016.
>> I HAVE TO SAY I ALWAYS ENJOY
LEARNING FROM YOU.
I LEARN AS MUCH FROM YOUR
REPORTING AS I DO FROM YOUR
ANALYSIS AND THANKS FOR BEING ON
THE GROUND FOR US TONIGHT.
STAY WITH US.
WE'LL BE BACK IN A MOMENT WITH
MORE SPECIAL COVERAGE OF THE
FIRST DEMOCRATIC PRESIDENTIAL
DEBATE RIGHT HERE ON NBC.
>> LAST NIGHT U.S. IMMIGRATION
POLICY DOMINATED THE DEBATE
STAGE, BUT TONIGHT WE EXPECT TO
HEAR MUCH MORE ON FOREIGN
POLICY, ESPECIALLY AS THE SENATE
PREPARES TO TAKE UP A BILL ON
WHETHER CONGRESS SHOULD APPROVE
A STRIKE ON IRAN.
HERE TO DIVE INTO THE FOREIGN
POLICY PLATFORM TONIGHT WE HAVE
OUR GUESTS BACK WITH US ALONG
WITH THE FORMER SPOKESPERSON FOR
THE U.S. MISSION TO THE U.N.
THANK YOU ALL SO MUCH FOR
JOINING US.
SO LET'S JUMP IN.
SATURDAY WE EXPECT TO SEE THE
MEETING BETWEEN PRESIDENT TRUMP
AND PRESIDENT XI OF CHINA, CAN
THE DEMOCRATIC CANDIDATES PROVE
THAT THEY ARE STILL TOUGH ON
CHINA AND ALSO PROVE THAT THEY
ARE NOT DIRECTLY ALIGNED WITH
PRESIDENT TRUMP?
>> THEY HAVE BEEN PRETTY SILENT
ON FOREIGN POLICY IN GENERAL.
THEY HAVEN'T GONE TO PUT OUT A
LOT OF FOREIGN POLICY, AND I
THINK IT'S BECAUSE THEY CANNOT
DIFFERENTIATE THEMSELVES
STRONGLY FROM PRESIDENT TRUMP.
I MEAN, I THINK THEY WISH THEY
COULD, BUT CERTAINLY WHEN IT
COMES TO CHINA A LOT OF THEM
FEEL THAT THE UNITED STATES
SHOULD BE TOUGH ON CHINA.
I THINK THAT THEY WOULD PROBABLY
GO ABOUT IT A DIFFERENT WAY, BUT
THEY ARE NOT GIVING US DETAILS
ON HOW -- ON WHAT THEIR PLANS
WOULD BE, HOW THEY WOULD LIKE TO
GO WHEN IT COMES TO CHINA
SPECIFICALLY.
HOW THEY WOULD GO IN A TOUGHER
MANNER, AND I THINK THAT GOES
ACROSS THE BOARD WHETHER IT'S
IRAN AND RUSSIA IN GENERAL.
>> SO WE'RE MISSING THE TACTICS.
>> YOU'RE NODDING YOUR HEAD.
>> THAT'S TRUE.
>> THE DEMOCRATS HAVE NOT REALLY
FOCUSED ON FOREIGN POLICY.
>> THIS EARLY IN THE PRIMACY
VOTERS AREN'T FOCUSING IN.
YOU'RE TALKING ABOUT THE ECONOMY
AND THINGS LIKE THAT, KITCHEN
TABLE ISSUES AND WHEN YOU'RE
TALKING ABOUT ISSUES LIKE IRAN,
IF YOU'RE WAKING UP IN THE
MORNING AND YOU'RE SEEING THAT
PUSH NOTIFICATION THAT SAYS WE
WERE GOING TO BOMB THEM AND
CHANGED OUR MINDS AT THE LAST
MINUTE THAT CAN BE REAL
CONCERNING AND I DO WANT TO HEAR
DEMOCRATS BE SPECIFIC ABOUT WHAT
THEY ARE GOING TO DO THAT IS
DIFFERENT FROM PRESIDENT TRUMP
AND NOT JUST PRESIDENT TRUMP'S
RHETORIC BUT HIS ACTUAL
ADMINISTRATION'S POLICY BECAUSE
THOSE TWO THINGS ARE DIFFERENT.
>> WE'VE HEARD SOME SPECIFICS
THOUGH.
JOE BIDEN SAID THAT CHINA WAS
NOT DIRECT COMPETITION AND THEN
WE SAW BERNIE SANDERS SAY, WAIT
A MINUTE, UNTRUE.
IT'S ABSOLUTELY AN ECONOMIC
COMPETITION.
WHICH OF THOSE MESSAGES DO YOU
THINK IS GOING TO WIN OUT AND
PLAY BEST WITH VOTERS TONIGHT?
>> I THINK FOR THE DEMOCRATS IF
THEY FOCUS ON INTELLECTUAL
PROPERTY, THAT'S A BIG THING
THAT I THINK YOU CAN DISTINGUISH
YOURSELF FROM THE PRESIDENT.
YOU ALSO LOOK AT CHINA AND LOOK
AT WHAT THEY ARE DOING AND
ESSENTIALLY IN OUR OWN BACKYARD
IN SOUTH AMERICA, GIVING OUT
ZERO FREE INTEREST LOANS, LIKE
WHAT THEY ARE DOING IN SOUTH
AFRICA.
THERE ARE VERY NUANCED WAYS TO
SORT OF MAKE A CLEAR DISTINCTION
FROM WHAT WE'VE SEEN FROM THE
TRUMP ADMINISTRATION AND AS IT
RELATES TO IRAN STABILITY.
DON'T TRUMP FOR ME, VOTE FOR ME
BECAUSE I THINK I'LL BRING
STABILITY.
>> THAT'S WHAT THEY COULD SAY
BUT THEY ARE NOT.
>> RIGHT.
>> ON CHINA, THIS WOULD BE AN
EASY ONE TO SAY THAT CHINA,
BECAUSE OF THE TARIFFS THAT
WE'RE IMPOSING, THAT ARE HURTING
AMERICAN COMPANIES AND AMERICAN
CONSUMERS, THE CHINESE ARE GOING
AROUND AND DOING BUSINESS WITH
EVERYONE ELSE.
WE SHOULD HAVE ALLIES AROUND THE
WORLD SAYING LET'S WORK TOGETHER
TO CONFRONT CHINA SO THE
DEMOCRATIC CANDIDATES COULD SAY
THAT, BUT THEY ARE NOT SAYING,
THAT AND I JUST DON'T UNDERSTAND
WHY.
>> IT'S A LITTLE SURPRISING TO
SEE HOW LIGHT EVERYONE WAS ON
FOREIGN POLICY.
>> RIGHT.
>> BUT DO YOU THINK WHEN WE
BRING IT BACK HOME TO DOMESTIC
ISSUES THAT WILL CHANGE THINGS?
FOR EXAMPLE, WE KNOW ROBERT
MUELLER JUST DECIDED HE WAS IN
FACT GOING TO TESTIFY.
DO YOU THINK THAT WILL CHANGE
THE CONVERSATION AROUND THE
MUELLER REPORT OR EVEN RUSSIA'S
ROLE IN THE 2016 ELECTION?
>> AND IT SHOULD CHANGE THE
CONVERSATION, I'M SURPRISED THAT
RUSSIA DIDN'T COME UP.
BILL de BLASIO WAS THE ONLY ONE
WHO MENTIONED RUSSIA, AND WE
IMMEDIATE TO BE TALKING ABOUT
RUSSIA.
THEY ARE STILL BOT ARMIES TRYING
TO INFILTRATE OUR ELECTIONS AND
STILL DOING THE SAME THINGS THEY
ARE DOING IN 2016.
NEED TO BE VERY VIGILANT AND
PRESIDENT TRUMP DOESN'T BELIEVE
THEY REALLY DID IT SO HE HASN'T
PUT FORWARD ANY POLICY.
THAT'S AN OPENING THAT WOULD TIE
TOGETHER DOMESTIC AND FOREIGN
POLICY BY SAYING THIS IS WHAT
I'M GOING TO DO TO ENSURE THAT
OUR ELECTION SYSTEMS ARE
PROTECTED.
>> I THINK DEMOCRATS NEED TO BE
CAREFUL WITH THE IMPEACHMENT
NOTION AND I'M TELL YOU WHY, OF
THE 61 SEATS THAT THEY WON IN
2018, 42, 43 WERE FROM
REPUBLICAN PREVIOUSLY HELD
DISTRICTS, DISTRICTS THAT DONALD
TRUMP WON.
"THE WASHINGTON POST" A MONTH
AGO DID A GREAT PROFILE PIECE ON
SOME OF THOSE MEMBERS AND WHAT
THEY SAID IS MOST CONSTITUENTS
IN THEIR DISTRICTS ARE NOT
TALKING ABOUT IMPEACHING TRUMP.
THEY DON'T EVEN WANT TO HEAR
THAT WHICH IS WHY I THINK NANCY
PELOSI HAS BEEN VERY, VERY
CAREFUL BECAUSE SHE DOESN'T WANT
TO RISK LOSING HER MAJORITY SO I
THINK IT'S GREAT TO SAY THAT FOR
THE BASE OF THE PARTY, BUT THEY
NEED TO BE VERY, VERY CAREFUL
ABOUT SOME OF THOSE OTHER AREAS
THAT THEY WON IN 2018 THAT I
WOULD ARGUE THAT THEY NEED IN
2020 IF THEY PLAN TO BEAT DONALD
TRUMP.
>> I DON'T THINK THAT'S A PUSH
RIGHT NOW FOR THE MAJORITY OF
THEM, THE DEMOCRATIC PARTY EVEN
THE ONES IN CONGRESS IS FOR
IMPEACHMENT.
THERE ARE 80 OR SO DEMOCRATS ON
THE RECORD SAYING THEY ARE
CALLING FOR IMPEACHMENT.
THE NUMBER IS GOING UP, BUT
THAT'S LESS THAN HALF THE
CAUCUS.
THAT'S NOT THE MAIN FOCUS OF THE
CONVERSATION, THE LOUDEST VOICES
ARE TALKING ABOUT IT, BUT I
DON'T THINK THAT THAT'S THE
ULTIMATE GOAL.
WHAT I DO THINK IN THE SHORT
TERM IS THEY ARE GOING TO TRY TO
DO IS BRING THE MUELLER REPORT
TO LIFE AND BRING IN THE
WITNESSES.
NOW THAT WE HAVE ROBERT MUELLER
COMING IN.
WHO ELSE CAN WE BRING IN TO
ACTUALLY PULL THE INFORMATION
THAT'S ON THE PAGES THAT
AMERICANS HAVE NOT READ AND
INTERNALIZE AND HOW CAN WE BRING
THAT TO LIGHT AND ALMOST ACT IT
OUT FOR PEOPLE SO THAT THEY
UNDERSTAND WHAT OBSTRUCTION OF
JUSTICE WAS TAKING PLACE IN THE
WHITE HOUSE.
>> WHERE IS THIS GOING?
WHERE DOES THIS GO?
>> WHERE DOES THIS GO?
>> IT'S GOING TO FAIL IN THE
SENATE WE KNOW THAT
AUTOMATICALLY.
MITCH McCONNELL IS NOT GOING TO
AGREE TO THIS.
>> I DON'T CARE ABOUT THAT.
>> SO WHY ARE YOU DOING IT?
>> BECAUSE THE AMERICAN PEOPLE
NEED TO BE EDUCATED ABOUT WHAT
THEIR PRESIDENT IS DOING WHILE
HE'S IN THE WHITE HOUSE.
A FOREIGN GOVERNMENT --
>> IS THIS THE WAY TO EDUCATED
THEM?
THAT'S CONGRESS' ROLE.
OVERSIGHT OVER THE EXECUTIVE
BRANCH AND INFORM THE AMERICAN
PEOPLE WHO NEED TO KNOW ALL OF
THE INFORMATION THAT IS
CONTAINED IN THE MUELLER REPORT
SO THEY CAN MAKE EDUCATED VOTES.
>> AND GUESS WHAT I WOULD DO.
>> IT'S NOT UP TO YOU.
>> IT WOULD WOULD GOT BE UP TO
MITCH McCONNELL BUT UP TO THE
AMERICAN PEOPLE.
>> REPUBLICANS ONLY NEED 21 OF
THOSE SEATS TO TAKE BACK THE
MAJORITY IN THE HOUSE.
IF THIS IS THE DIRECTION
DEMOCRATS WANT TO GO, I WOULD
TARGET EVERY SINGLE ONE OF THOSE
DEMOCRATS WHO FLIPPED THOSE
REPUBLICAN SEATS.
>> WHAT DIRECTION ARE YOU
SPECIFYING?
I'M NOT TALKING ABOUT --
>> AND NANCY PELOSI WILL LOSE
HER MAJORITY.
>> I'M NOT SAYING DEMOCRATS ARE
RUNNING ON IMPEACHMENT.
>> THAT'S WHAT YOU ARE SAYING.
>> YOU ARE SAYING IT'S
IMPORTANT.
>> WHAT I'M SAYING IS
UNDERSTANDING THE CONTENT OF THE
MUELLER REPORT IS IMPORTANT.
I'M NOT TALKING ABOUT, YOU KNOW,
IMPEACHING THE PRESIDENT IS AN
AUTOMATIC TWO-STEP DO IT AND IT
HAPPENS OVERNIGHT.
THAT'S NOT HOW THIS COUNTRY
WORKS.
NO PRESIDENT HAS EVER BEEN
REMOVED IN THAT MANNER SO WHAT
WE'RE TALKING ABOUT NOW IS USING
THE CONGRESSIONAL OVERSIGHT
RESPONSIBILITY TO EDUCATE THE
AMERICAN PUBLIC ABOUT THE
CONTENTS OF THE MUELLER REPORT
BECAUSE --
>> GET OVER IT.
THERE WERE NOT CRIMES ENUMERATED
IN THAT REPORT.
>> CRIMES, TEN OF THEM.
>> I AGREE WITH YOU AS FAR AS
ETHICS AND AS FAR AS THE
PRESIDENT DOING THINGS BUT WHAT
I'M SAYING --
>> IF A DEMOCRAT HAD DONE THE
SAME THING.
>> I'M NOT DISAGREEING WITH YOU,
BUT AS A STRATEGIST I'M TELLING
YOU IF DEMOCRATS WANT TO GO IN
THAT DIRECTION, THERE'S EVERY
SINGLE REPUBLICAN AT THE RNC AND
THE HOUSE REPUBLICAN RESEARCH
COMMITTEE THAT'S GOING TO FOCUS
ON THOSE MEMBERS AND THEY ARE
GOING TO DO EVERYTHING THEY CAN
TO MAKE SURE PELOSI LOSES THAT
MAJORITY.
THAT'S -- THAT'S --
>> REPUBLICANS DO THAT EVERY
DAY.
>> MY VIEW IS MORE FROM THE
FOREIGN POLICY ANGLE.
YOU STARTED ASKING ROBERT
MUELLER, HOW DOES THIS AFFECT
OUR CONVERSATION.
I THINK THAT'S CRITICAL BECAUSE,
I MEAN, TO NO ONE'S SURPRISE I'M
GOING TO SAY I THINK FOREIGN
POLICY IS MUCH MORE IMPORTANT
BUT FOR THE VOTER IT'S REALLY
ABOUT THE ECONOMY AND
HEALTHCARE, AND THAT BEING SAID,
FOREIGN POLICY CERTAINLY NOW IS
REALLY CRITICAL BECAUSE IT
ENTERED OUR ELECTIONS IN 2016
AND HAD A DIRECT IMPACT ON THE
VOTER.
VOTERS SHOULD CARE.
THEY MAY NOT KNOW THEY SHOULD
CARE AT THE MOMENT AND THAT'S
WHY EDUCATING THEN IS SO
CRITICAL.
ON IMPEACHMENT, THIS IS A
SEPARATE STORY.
MY VIEW IS THAT IT'S A
DISTRACTION AND THAT'S MY OWN
OPINION.
>> WHAT I'M SAYING IS I WANT
THERE TO BE SERIOUS AND FORMAL
HEARINGS BUT THAT DOESN'T MEAN.
>> BUT PEOPLE SHOULD BE TALKING
ABOUT IT.
>> ARE YOU KILLING TWO BIRDS
WITH ONE STONE?
IS THAT HOW YOU EDUCATE THEM
THROUGH THIS PROCESS OF THE
MUELLER REPORT?
>> YOU KNOW, THERE'S NO
LOUDER -- THE LOUDSPEAKER THAT
THE CANDIDATES HAVE RIGHT NOW IS
MUCH LARGER THAN ANY HEARING,
THAN ANY NEWSPAPER ARTICLE.
THEY HAVE AN OPPORTUNITY RIGHT
NOW WITH ALL THEIR FOLLOWS ON
SOCIAL MEDIA AND ALL THEIR
RALLIES TODAY, YOU KNOW, THIS IS
WHY THIS IS IMPORTANT.
THIS IS WHAT RUSSIA IS DOING.
CHINA COULD BE DOING THIS, AND
THIS IS WHAT I'M GOING TO DO
ABOUT IT.
I'M GOING TO PUT, FOR EXAMPLE,
MORE MONEY AND RESEARCH INTO THE
U.S. GOVERNMENT WHEN I BECOME
PRESIDENT TO COMBAT THAT AND
BEEF UP CYBER SECURITY AND
ENSURE THAT FACEBOOK AND GOOGLE
WORK WITH US TO MAKE SURE THAT
DISINFORMATION ISN'T RAMPANT.
>> THERE'S A LOT OF PEOPLE WHO
ARE JUST UNCLEAR.
>> RIGHT.
>> WHO DON'T UNDERSTAND.
>> DEMOCRATS HAD AN OPPORTUNITY
TO EDUCATE THE AMERICAN PEOPLE
OVER AND OVER AND OVER AGAIN.
>> HOW LONG DID WATERGATE TAKE
FROM THE BREAK-IN UNTIL RICHARD
NIXON RESIGNING?
>> IT TAKES A LONG TIME.
>> A YEAR AND A HALF FROM NOW
THAT'S HOW LONG IT WOULD TAKE IF
YOU OPEN UP IMPEACHMENT
HEARINGS.
DONALD TRUMP WILL ALREADY BE
RE-ELECTED.
>> HERE'S THE THING.
>> WE DON'T KNOW WHAT'S GOING TO
HAPPEN BEFORE MIDNIGHT.
SO I -- I'M NOT SITTING HERE AND
SAYING THAT I KNOW EXACTLY
WHAT'S GOING TO HAPPEN IN 2020
BASED ON THE STRATEGY.
WHAT I'M SAYING AS AN AMERICAN
CITIZEN WE LIVE IN A COUNTRY
THAT HAD ELECTIONS ATTACKED AND
EVEN MY OWN PERSONAL EMAIL
HACKED BECAUSE I WAS ON THE
CLINTON CAMPAIGN BY A FOREIGN
GOVERNMENT, I THINK THERE NEEDS
TO BE SOME SORT OF
ACCOUNTABILITY FOR THAT.
>> I AGREE.
>> AND IN THE REPORT ROBERT
MUELLER FOUND CRIME.
>> TONIGHT IT'S ALL ABOUT
ACCOUNTABILITY, AND WE COULD DO
THIS ALL NIGHT AND HOPEFULLY
WE'LL CARE AS MUCH ABOUT FOREIGN
POLICY ON THE DEBATE FLOOR.
STAY WITH US.
>> OUR VERY OWN DR. SEBASTIAN
BURNS WITH US TONIGHT.
WATCHING THE DEBATE LIVE FROM
DOWNTOWN NEW YORK WITH A FEW
COLLEGE STUDENTS FROM ALL ACROSS
THE COUNTRY.
WHAT IS ON EVERYONE'S MIND
HEADING NOW INTO NIGHT TWO?
>> HEY, MORGAN, I'VE GOT
BRILLIANT STUDENTS HERE FROM
ACROSS THE COUNTRY.
THEY ARE FROM ACROSS THE COUNTRY
AND THE POLITICAL SPECTRUM.
DEMOCRATS, REPUBLICANS,
INDEPENDENTS AND FOR A COUPLE OF
FOLKS HERE THIS IS ACTUALLY
GOING TO BE THEIR FIRST TIME
VOTING IN A PRESIDENTIAL
ELECTION, SO THEY ARE WATCHING
REALLY CLOSELY.
GUYS, LET'S START WITH THE
FRONT-RUNNER, JOE BIDEN.
OKAY.
SHOW OF HANDS.
WHO IS SUPER EXCITED ABOUT
BIDEN?
WOW, NOBODY.
OKAY.
WANT TO TALK TO ME ABOUT WHY,
WHY IS HE NOT LIGHTING A FIRE IN
THIS ROOM?
>> PERSONALLY I FEEL LIKE AS IT
RELATES TO JOE BIDEN HIM RUNNING
FOR PRESIDENT IS REALLY JUST
SOMETHING TO CHECK OFF A LIST.
LIKE MONDAY I HAD SOMETHINGITY,
TUESDAY I WAS VICE PRESIDENT AND
NOW WEDNESDAY I WANT TO BE
PRESIDENT.
HE'S REALLY IN MY OPINION A
PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE LIKE IT'S
RIGHT FOR HIM AND IT WILL BE
INTERESTING TO SEE OTHER
CANDIDATES HOLD HIS FEET TO THE
FIRE ESPECIALLY HIS
CONTROVERSIAL PAST REFORMING THE
PRISON SYSTEM THAT WE HAVE NOW.
>> WE'RE ALL GOING TO BE
WATCHING TO SEE BIDEN KIND OF
DEFINE HIS POLICIES BECAUSE HE'S
FLIP-FLOPPED SO LONG IN HIS LONG
POLITICAL CAREER.
I THINK WE'RE ALL LOOKING TO
DELIVER A SOLID MESSAGE AND SAY
SOMETHING THAT HE BELIEVES IN IT
GENUINELY AND NOT JUST DOING IT
FOR THE POLITICAL ASPECT OF IT.
>> WE'VE HEARD THAT VICE
PRESIDENT BIDEN DOESN'T VIEW
CHINA AS AN ECONOMIC THREAT AND
WHEN YOU GO TO A PLACE LIKE
PITTSBURGH, THE U.S. STEEL PLANT
HAS A 1.5 BILLION INVESTMENT AND
HOW IS BIDEN GOING TO GO TO THAT
PART OF AMERICA AND SAY I'M THE
BETTER CANDIDATE FOR THE WORKING
CLASS AND DISTINGUISH HIMSELF
FROM THE PRESIDENT.
>> SOUNDS LIKE HE'S NOT REALLY
RESONATING BOTH WITH POLICY AND
WITH MESSAGING.
I MEAN, ONE OF THE REASONS SOME
PEOPLE ARE MORE EXCITED ABOUT
HIM, ARE MORE EXCITED ABOUT HIM
IS BECAUSE OF THE LONG TRACK
RECORD HE HAS AND THE KIND OF
EXPERIENCE THAT HE HAS.
SOMEONE WHO IS ALSO A
FRONT-RUNNER ON THE STABLE WHO
HAS THE LEAST GOVERNMENT
EXPERIENCE IS PUT BUTTIGIEG.
THINKING ABOUT THOSE TWO,
THERE'S ABOUT A 40-YEAR AGE GAP
BETWEEN THE TWO OF THEM AND THAT
SAYS A LOT ABOUT EXPERIENCE AND
PERSPECTIVE.
THERE'S A LOT OF DIFFERENCES
THERE.
WHAT'S RESONATING MORE WITH YOU
GUYS?
A LOT OF YOU MORE WERE EXCITED
ABOUT BUTTIGIEG.
WHY IS THAT SOMETHING THAT GETS
YOU GOING?
>> WELL, I MEAN, YEAH.
NOT ONLY BECAUSE HE'S YOUNG BUT
BECAUSE HE'S BRING IDEAS.
THE REASON WHY I THINK BIDEN HAS
A BIG TEST, HE'S NOT BRING NEW
AND EXCITING INNOVATIVE IDEAS.
YES, HE'S YOUNG BUT HE'S GOING
TO BRING NEW IDEAS AND THAT'S
WHAT WE WANT TO SEE.
WE WANT TO SEE TAX REFORM AND
REFORM OF THE PRISON SYSTEM AND
WITH BIDEN THE CONVERSATION HAS
NEVER BEEN ABOUT REFORM, KEEPING
THINGS HOW THEY ARE AND JUST
TWEAKING THEM A LITTLE BIT AND
WE DON'T WANT TO SEE A LITTLE
BIT OF TWEAK.
THIS IS GOING TO BE OUR FUTURE
SO FOR US IT'S REALLY KEY TO
FIND CANDIDATES WHO ARE ACTUALLY
GOING TO TALK ABOUT INNOVATION
AND HOW THEY WILL HAVE AN EFFECT
IN THREE YEARS AND TWO YEARS
WHEN THEY ARE ALREADY EFFECTED
AND WE'LL SEAT RIPPLE EFFECT.
>> AND THERE'S THE PERSPECTIVE
GAP BETWEEN BUTTIGIEG AND BIDEN
AND BERNIE SANDERS AND JOE BIDEN
ARE NOT THAT DIFFERENT IN AGE
AND YOU SEEM TO VIEW HIM PRETTY
DIFFERENTLY.
CAN YOU TALK ABOUT BERNIE
SANDERS AND WHY HE'S RESONATING
IN A WAY THAT MAYBE BIDEN ISN'T.
>> BERNIE SANDERS IS HIGH ENERGY
AND USES SOCIAL MEDIA WELL AND
REACHES OUT TO YOUNGER VOTER
BASES REALLY WELL.
JUST SOMEONE I THINK NO MATTER
WHAT AGE YOU ARE YOU CAN KIND OF
CONNECT WITH HIM AND SEE ALL THE
WORK HE'S DONE HIS WHOLE LIFE.
HE'S SOMEONE WHO HAS PUSHED AND
PUSHED AND PUSHED AND HE'S KIND
OF AT THIS POINT NOW WHERE,
YEAH, HE'S OLD BUT HE CERTAINLY
DOESN'T ACT OLD EVEN THOUGH HE'S
BEEN THROUGH SO MUCH.
>> I FEEL LIKE WITH BERNIE WE
SEE A CONSISTENT PASSION AND A
REALLY CONSISTENT MESSAGE AND A
CONSISTENT POINT OF VIEW FROM
WHERE HE'S COMING AND HIS IDOL.
>>> EVEN IF YOU DISAGREE WITH
IT, YOU CAN RESPECT THE WAY HE'S
BEEN EXPRESSING IT FOR A LONG
TIME WHEREAS WITH BIDEN WE SEE
LESS OF A GENUINE PASSION COMING
FROM HIM.
>> CAN WE TALK ABOUT THIS TERM
DEMOCRATIC SOCIALISM AND HOW IS
THAT PLAYING AMONGST YOU AND
YOUR PEERS?
>> WELL, I THINK THE TERM ITSELF
DEMOCRATIC SOCIALISM, IT HAS A
VERY CONTROVERSIAL TERM ALREADY
IN IT, SOCIALISM, AND I BELIEVE
THAT'S WHY A LOT OF PEOPLE ARE
EVEN HAVING A LOT OF PROBLEMS AS
IT RELATES TO CANDIDATES LIKE
BERNIE SANDERS.
IT'S GOING TO BE INTERESTING TO
SEE HOW HE TRIES TOSS PUSH THAT
MORE INTO A POSITION WHERE BOTH
REPUBLICANS AND DEMOCRATS CAN
KIND OF COME TOGETHER AND AGREE
ON THE ISSUES THAT THEY WANT TO
REFORM AS WELL AS OTHER
CANDIDATES SUCH AS AN ELIZABETH
WARREN THAT'S ALREADY KIND OF
STRAIGHT DOWN THE MIDDLE.
THAT'S GOING TO BE A LOT EASIER
FOR THOSE THAT ARE MODERATES OR
INDEPENDENTS TO KIND OF JOIN ON
TO HER OWN BANDWAGON.
>> IT'S ALSO IMPORTANT TO
RECOGNIZE JUST BECAUSE THEY ARE
LABELING THEMSELVES AS
DEMOCRATIC SOCIALISTS IT DOESN'T
NECESSARILY MEAN THAT THEY ARE
AGAINST WHAT CAPITALISM IS.
THEY ARE TAKING THE MOST
EGREGIOUS ASPECTS OF CAPITALISM,
THE MASSIVE INEQUALITY AND A
SHRINKING MIDDLE CLASS AND THEY
ARE TAKING THAT AND SAYING WE
CAN FIX THIS AND WE CAN FIX THIS
UNDER CAPITALISM WITH WHAT COULD
BE SOCIALIST POLICIES.
>> THAT'S NOT NECESSARILY A
TURNOFF, BUT YOU WANT TO SEE HOW
THEY ACTUALLY DEFINE THAT AND
HOW IT PLAYS TONIGHT.
WELL, WE'LL BE SEEING HOW THAT
TERM IS THROWN AROUND AND WHAT
THESE CANDIDATES ARE PUTTING ON
THE TABLE.
MORGAN.
>> THANK YOU SO MUCH, AND THANK
YOU TO ALL OF YOUR STUDENT
PANELISTS.
WE HOPE THAT YOU STICK AROUND
WITH US HERE.
FOR ALL OF THOSE WATCHING OUT
THERE, STAY TUNED BECAUSE WE
HAVE A LOT MORE TO DIVE INTO
RIGHT BEFORE NIGHT TWO OF THE
DEMOCRATIC DEBATES BEGIN.
>>> HEALTHCARE WAS ONE OF THE
TOP ISSUES IN LAST NIGHT'S
DEBATE SPARKING SOME HEATED
MOMENTS FROM NEARLY EVERY SINGLE
CANDIDATE ON STAGE, BUT PERHAPS
MOST NOTABLY THEY FOUGHT OVER
THE ROLE THAT PRIVATE INSURANCE
SHOULD PLAY IN INDIVIDUAL
HEALTHCARE PLANS.
ELIZABETH WARREN DECLARED THAT
SHE WAS WITH BERNIE SANDERS IN
SUPPORTING MEDICARE FOR ALL AND
THEN TONIGHT THE SENATOR FROM
VERMONT IS GOING TO BE TAKING
CENTER STAGE WITH HIS POLICY
PLATFORM.
OUR GUESTS ARE BACK WITH ME NOW,
AND I WANT TO TALK A LITTLE BIT
ABOUT THE SENSE OF HEALTHCARE
AND WHERE WE ARE.
WE SAW THAT WARREN AND DeBLASIO
WERE AGAINST KEEPING THE PRIVATE
OPTION AND O'ROURKE AND
KLOBUCHAR WANT TO KEEP IT.
WHERE DO YOU THINK THE
CANDIDATES ON NIGHT TWO WILL
FALL?
>> I REALLY DO THINK THIS WILL
BE -- I THINK IT WILL ILLUSTRATE
HOW DESPERATE JOE BIDEN AND
BERNIE SANDERS ARE.
YOU HAVE BERNIE ON ONE SIDE OF
THE SPEC TRURNLGS RIGHT, WHO IS
ANTI-INCREMENTALISM AND WANTS TO
IMPLEMENT MEDICARE FOR ALL AND
WANTS TO ELIMINATE PRIVATE
INSURANCE, AND THEN YOU HAVE JOE
BIDEN, ON THE OTHER HAND, WHO
WANTS, YOU KNOW, OBAMACARE IS
ONE OF HIS BIGGEST LEGACIES.
HE WANTS TO BUILD ON OBAMACARE.
HE WANTS TO GIVE PEOPLE THE
PUBLIC OPTION AND I THINK THAT
REALLY CAPTURES HIS
INCREMENTALIST APPROACH AND THAT
HERE I THINK IS WHAT YOU'RE
SEEING THESE KIDS THAT WERE
AGAINST THIS SORT OF SLOW BOIL
AND ARE IN FAVOR OF MORE
DRAMATIC POLICIES THAT CAN
EFFECT CHANGE TOMORROW.
>> YOU'RE CHUCKLING, WHY?
>> BECAUSE IT'S NOT REALISTIC.
I RESPECT THE KIDS AND I GET IT,
BUT I'VE WORKED IN POLITICS FOR
A WHILE NOW.
I'VE BEEN IN D.C. FOR A WHILE
NOW.
THAT'S JUST NOT HOW THINGS WORK,
AND I THINK ONE OF THE ISSUES
FOR SOMEONE LIKE AN AOC SHE'S
FOUND OUT FAST THAT THE GREEN
NEW DEAL, JUST HOW D.C. WORKS.
HAVE YOU TO WORK IN REALITY AND
YOU HAVE TO GET OTHER MEMBERS
AND SOMETIMES PEOPLE IN YOUR OWN
PARTY TO WORK WITH YOU TO PASS
SOME OF THESE PIECES OF
LEGISLATION.
IT'S NOT ABOUT INCREMENTALISM.
>> JOHN DELANEY HAD A GREAT
CONVERSATION TODAY AND WENT BACK
AND FORTH ON THIS TOPIC AND SOME
OF THE BIGGEST, RICH ET
COUNTRIES, MOST DEVELOPED
COUNTRIES IN THE WORLD HAVE
TRANSITIONED VERY EASILY
OVERNIGHT TO -- ELIMINATED
PRIVATE HEALTH INSURANCE AND
HAVE CONSISTENT RATES.
>> CANADA, THE NHS IN ENGLAND.
>> BUT THEY DON'T HAVE THE SAME
POLITICAL SYSTEM OR SETUP THAT
WE DO, PARTICULARLY WHEN YOU
THINK ABOUT THE PARTISANSHIP
THAT CURRENTLY EXISTS.
>> WHY DO YOU THINK IT'S NOT A
REALISTIC OPTION?
>> I REALLY CANNOT WRAP MY HEAD
AROUND HOW IT'S FUNDED AND WHEN
YOU ASK, WHEN CANDIDATES HAVE
BEEN ASKED, KAMALA HARRIS HAVE
BEEN ASKED, THEY FUMBLE OVER
THEIR WORDS, WELL, WE'LL
INCREASE TAXES AND INCREASE ON
THE 1% AND WE'LL INCREASE THE
ESTATE TAXES.
NONE OF THAT ACTUALLY MAKES
SENSE AND NONE OF IT TO ME SEEMS
VERY FEASIBLE FOR THE REASONS
MENTIONED BECAUSE WASHINGTON
DOESN'T WORK LIKE THAT AND IT
DOESN'T HAPPEN OVERNIGHT AND I
THINK IT SOUNDS ATTRACTIVE TO A
YOUNG VOTE.
>> BUT WHERE THE RUBBER MEETS
THE ROAD, AND I DON'T SEE HOW IT
COULD WORK.
>> IN THE SPAN OF FOUR YEARS
THAT WE'VE SEEN THIS
CONVERSATION DRAMATICALLY
CHANGE, THIS REALLY WASN'T A
TOPIC OF CONVERSATION IN THE
DEMOCRATIC PARTY UNTIL BERNIE
SANDERS HIT THE BIG STAGE AND
NOW YOU SEE AOC DOING THE EXACT
SAME THING.
IN LESS THAN A YEAR SHE'S
REVOLUTIONIZED THE CONVERSATION
AROUND CLIMATE CHANGE.
>> AND EVERYTHING SHE'S
ATTEMPTED TO DO HAS FAILED.
EVERY SINGLE THING SHE HAS
PROPOSED.
WHAT I'M SAYING THE REALITY IS
YOU LOOK AT THE PROCESS OF HOW
YOU GET THESE THINGS DONE.
HOW DO YOU ACPLASH THIS?
IT'S VERY, VERY DIFFICULT AND TO
HAVE SHE IS SWEEPING NOTIONS
THAT I'M GOING TO GET IN AN
ELECTION ON DAY ONE AND
EVERYTHING IS GOING TO CHANGE.
IT'S NOT REAL.
>> BUT I THINK THAT'S WHY THIS
PRIMARY IS SO FASCINATING,
RIGHT, BECAUSE THERE IS THIS
SCHISM THIS YEAR, AND I THINK
IT'S A BIG GENERATIONAL GAP, YOU
KNOW, BETWEEN PEOPLE WHO WANT
STRUCTURE AND IDEOLOGICAL CHANGE
THAT PEOPLE THINK TRUMP IS AN
ABERRATION AND THE OUTGROWTH OF
A LOT OF SYSTEMIC INEQUALITIES
YEAHTATING TOWARDS CANDIDATES
LIKE ELIZABETH WARREN AND BERNIE
SANDERS RATHER THAN JOE BIDEN
THINKING THAT TRUMP IS A ONE-OFF
AND ONCE HE GETS INTO OFFICE
IT'S BUSINESS AS SGLUSHL WHAT
ABOUT THE COMPETITION BETWEEN
THE CANDIDATES?
EARLIER ON WE HEARD SENATOR
WARREN SAY I SUPPORT BERNIE
SANDERS' PLAN.
I BELIEVE IN EVERYONE HAVING
THIS.
DO YOU THINK SHE'S TRYING TO TRY
TO CREEP INTO HIS BASE AND PULL
SOME OF THOSE VOTERS FOR
HERSELF?
>> LOOKING AT THE NUMBERS SHE'S
ALREADY DOING, IT RIGHT.
I SAW NINA TURNER ON EARLIER
TODAY AND SHE'S MAKE THE CASE
FOR BERNIE SANDERS, AND SHE WAS
ESSENTIALLY SAYING HE'S THE
ORIGINAL.
WE'RE NOT REALLY WORRIED ABOUT
ELIZABETH WARREN BECAUSE BERNIE
IS THE ORIGINAL.
WELL, THE REALITY IS ELIZABETH
WARREN HAS BEEN ADDED TO ADD A
LOT OF SUBSTANCE WHO WHAT BERNIE
SANDERS ORIGINALLY BROUGHT TO
THE CONVERSATION BACK IN 2016.
>> THE CANDIDATES NEED TO BE
VERY CAREFUL IN NOT
OVERPROMISING AND SAYING THINGS
THAT -- THAT THEY ASSUME THE
VOTER WANTS TO HEAR.
MAYBE THEY KNOW THE VOTER WANTS
TO HEAR IT BUT YOU CAN'T GO
AROUND MAKING FALSE PROMISES AND
THAT'S WHERE YOU END UP BEING
THE TRUMPET LEFT.
>> ALL OF ELIZABETH WARREN'S
PROGRAMS AND POLICIES PUT
TOGETHER ARE PRETTY BALANCED.
"THE WASHINGTON POST" HAS A
GREAT PIECE BY JEFF STEIN THAT
SHOWED THAT IT ALL EVENED OUT TO
ZERO THE WAY THAT ALL OF HER
POLICIES AND TAXES OFFSET EACH
OTHER AND THAT'S SOMETHING
BERNIE HASN'T BEEN ABLE TO
ARTICULATE.
>> STAYING ON THE TOPIC OF
HEALTHCARE, WHAT ABOUT WOMEN'S
RIGHTS BECAUSE WE HEARD THIS
ROUND OF APPLAUSE YESTERDAY WHEN
JULIAN CASTRO WAS TALKING ABOUT
REPRODUCTIVE JUSTICE.
WHEN IT COMES TO THE TOPIC OF
ABORTION WHICH, OF COURSE, HAS
BEEN DEBATED HEAVILY OF LATE, IS
THERE A MIDDLE GROUND ON THIS
ISSUE?
IS THERE SOMETHING THAT THESE
CANDIDATES CAN SAY TO PERHAPS
GET THE SWING STATE MIDDLE OF
THE ROAD VOTERS
?
>> THE MIDDLE INVOLVEMENT I
THOUGHT ELIZABETH WARREN -- THIS
IS NOT MIDDLE OF THE ROAD.
I'M JUST SAYING I THOUGHT SHE
DID A GREAT JOB IN SETTING
HERSELF APART BY SAYING THAT THE
COURTS HAD AJEWETT KATED ON IT,
AND THAT IT WAS LEGISLATION TO
PREVENT STATES GOING RIGHT UP OR
EVEN PUSHING THAT LIMIT, RIGHT,
SO I THOUGHT THAT THAT WAS SMART
AND PUTTING SOMETHING NEW
FORWARD BUT WHERE TO GET THE
MIDDLE OF THE GROUND?
THAT'S PRACTICAL I THINK HAVING
SOMETHING LEGAL WHERE THERE'S
LESS INTERPRETATION.
>> IS THERE A MIDDLE GROUND IN
THIS?
>> I DON'T THINK THERE IS.
I THINK YOU'RE EITHER ON THE
LEFT OF THIS OR YOU'RE ON THE
RIGHT.
I DON'T THINK YOU'LL FIND EVEN
AMONGST VOTERS CENTRISTS ON THE
IDEA OF ABORTION, PRO WOMEN
RIGHTS OR AGAINST IT.
>> RIGHT.
LET'S SEE WHAT THE STUDENTS HAVE
TO SAY BECAUSE I'M CURIOUS WHAT
THE COLLEGE STUDENTS HAVE TO SAY
ABOUT THEIR OWN HEALTHCARE PLAN.
>> I KNOW YOU HAVE YOUR PANEL OF
STUDENTS THERE TONIGHT.
I WANTED TO ASK SOMETHING THAT I
HEARD THEM SAY IN THE LAST
SEGMENT.
IT SEEMS LIKE EVERYTHING THAT
THE STUDENTS TALKED ABOUT CAME
DOWN TO AUTHENTICITY.
THIS IS A QUICK LIGHTNING ROUND.
WHICH CANDIDATE DOES EACH
STUDENT BLEACH IS MOTOR
AUTHENTIC?
>> YEAH, WHAT DO YOU THINK,
GUYS?
WHO HAS MADE THE MOST AUTHENTIC
PITCH TO YOU?
>> PETE BUTTIGIEG.
>> BERNIE SANDERS.
>> I THINK BERNIE SANDERS IS THE
MOST AUTHENTIC.
>> BERNIE SANDERS.
>> INTERESTING.
>> SO THINKING ABOUT LAST NIGHT,
I MEAN, LAST NIGHT BASICALLY ALL
OF YOU SAID CASTRO SORT OF STOLE
THE SPOTLIGHT.
WHAT -- WHAT DO YOU WANT TO SEE
TONIGHT THAT YOU DIDN'T SEE LAST
NIGHT?
WHO DO YOU WANT TO SEE SHINE?
WHAT TOPIC DO YOU THINK DIDN'T
GET ENOUGH COVER?
>> DEFINITELY I FEEL LIKE THE
CANDIDATES BARELY TOUCHED ON THE
ISSUE OF REPRODUCTIVE RIGHTS AND
HEARD A LOT ABOUT HEALTHCARE
WHICH IS VERY IMPORTANT BUT AS
WOMEN WE WANT TO HEAR ABOUT,
ESPECIALLY WITH THE LAWS PASSED
RECENTLY, VERY HARSHLY LIMITING
WOMEN'S RIGHT TO CHOOSE, I THINK
THAT WE'RE ALL VERY INTERESTED
IN JUST PROTECTING OR GOING
AGAINST THE RIGHT TO CHOOSE AND
WHAT DOES IT REALLY MEAN TO
MAYBE BE ANTI-ABORTION BUT PRO
CHOICE.
>> THAT'S AN INTERESTING POINT
BECAUSE THIS IS AN HISTORIC
NUMBER OF WOMEN THAT WE HAVE IN
THIS ELECTION AND ON THAT DEBATE
STAGE, HOW DO YOU THINK THAT
MIGHT CHANGE THE CONVERSATION
AROUND REPRODUCTIVE RIGHTS
TONIGHT?
>> I THINK IT'S OPENING UP AGAIN
A UNIQUE CONVERSATION AS TO THE
RIGHTS THAT WOMEN MIGHT BE ABLE
TO HAVE OVER THEIR BODIES VERSUS
HOW ONE IDENTIFIES WITH THEIR
RELIGIOUS BELIEFS AND HOW ONE
MIGHT BE ABLE TO COME TO A
MIDDLE GROUND AS IT RELATES TO
THAT.
IT'S ALSO OPENING UP ANOTHER
CONVERSATION AS TO THE ROLE THAT
MEN PLAY WITHIN THIS
CONVERSATION.
EVEN THOUGH THIS IS AN ISSUE
THAT DIRECTLY AFFECTS WOMEN, WE
ALL KNOW THAT WOMEN ARE NOT THE
ONLY PEOPLE THAT ARE VOTING ON
THESE LAWS, SO IT THEN ALSO
BRINGS INTO THE CONVERSATION AS
TO THE POWERS THAT MEN ARE GOING
TO PLAY WHEN IT COMES TO THE
CONVERSATION OF REPRODUCTIVE
RIGHTS.
>> ONE THING THAT I ALSO LOVE TO
TALK ABOUT AND I DON'T THINK
WE'VE TALKED ABOUT IT ENOUGH,
WE'VE DISCUSSED SORT OF THE
APPEAL OF BEAUTE YEG, YOUNG AND
INNOVATIVE AND BLOW IT ALL UP
AND THINK OF SOMETHING NEW
APPROACH.
WHAT ABOUT BIPARTISANSHIP?
DO YOU WANT TO MAKE ANY APPEAL
TO THAT TONIGHT AND TRY TO REACH
ACROSS THE AISLE A LITTLE BIT,
OR IS THAT NOT THE TIME FOR IT
RIGHT NOW?
>> I THINK IT'S ABSOLUTELY TIME.
WEST VIRGINIA WHERE I COME FROM
USED TO BE A RELIABLY DEMOCRATIC
STATE AND POLICIES NOW, WE WENT
68% FOR TRUMP IN 2016.
I THINK IT'S GOING TO BE
IMPORTANT FOR CANDIDATES TO
ARTICULATE.
HOW ARE THEY GOING TO GO IN AND
REACH OUT.
I THINK IT'S GOING TO BE
INTERESTING IN HOW THEY TALK
ABOUT BRIDGING THAT GAP AND
MAYOR BUTTIGIEG COMES FROM SOUTH
BEND, ENINDIANA, A DYING CITY
WHEN HE CAME TO IT AND NOW WILL
HE BE ABLE TO BRING THAT TO THE
ENTIRE MIDWEST.
>> HARD TO DEAL WITH WHEN YOU'RE
DEALING WITH -- THAT'S WHY I
THINK BIPARTISANSHIP IS GOING TO
BE SO BARN BECAUSE WE WANT TO
MAKE SURE THAT THEY ARE ACTUALLY
ABLE TO PASS LEGISLATION.
LIKE YOU CAN BE VERY RETRO -- I
THINK.
>> DO YOU THINK THEY HAVE TALKED
ABOUT THAT ENOUGH ON THE
CAMPAIGN TRAIL SO FAR?
>> IT'S ACTUALLY INTERESTING
ESPECIALLY CONSIDERING WHAT YOU
JUST SAID BECAUSE I KNOW THAT A
LOT OF LIBERALS HAVE A
PERSPECTIVE THAT AS WELL AS
CONSERVATIVES THAT THERE ARE
ISSUES.
LET'S TAKE ABORTION, FOR
EXAMPLE, WHERE, YOU KNOW, IT'S
JUST IMPOSSIBLE TO REACH A
MIDDLE GROUND.
SOME ISSUE THAT PEOPLE FEEL THAT
THERE'S NOTHING TO COME TOGETHER
ON.
YOU EITHER ARE OR YOU AREN'T.
AS WE TALKED ABOUT, AGAIN, FOR
EXAMPLE, BERNIE SANDERS AND THE
TOPIC, FOR EXAMPLE, ABOUT A
DEMOCRATIC GLOBALISM.
HOW WAS HE GOING TO BE ABLE TO
REACH OUT TO THOSE WHO ARE A BIT
MORE CONSERVATIVE OR
INDEPENDENT.
THERE'S ALSO CONVERSATIONS ON
HOW THE DEMOCRATIC PARTY IS
BECOMING MORE QUOTE, UNQUOTE
RADICAL AS WELL SO WITH THAT
CONVERSATION THERE ARE A LOT OF
TOPICS THAT PEOPLE FEEL THAT,
NO, THERE IS NO REASON TO WIN
THE MIDDLE.
I WANT MY WAY OR, YOU KNOW, I
DON'T WANT TO THE HEAR IT AT
ALL.
>> IN THAT REGARD I'M ACTUALLY
REALLY EXCITED ABOUT PEOPLE LIKE
PETE BUTTIGIEG BECAUSE THEY KIND
OF SERVE AS A BRIDGE BETWEEN THE
DEMOCRATIC SOCIALISTS AND THESE
KIND OF MORE DEMOCRATIC PARTY
AND YOU HEAR ABOUT THE PEOPLE IN
HIS CONSTITUENCY THAT DISAGREE
WITH HIM AND HE'S ABLE TO
NEGOTIATE AND SERVE IN THEIR
INTEREST.
>> THAT IS AN IMPORTANT THING,
TOO, GUYS.
YOU DON'T WANT JUST THE APPEAL
TO THE LEFT AND FAR LEFT.
YOU WANT TO SEE PEOPLE KIND OF
CHANGE THE DISCOURSE AND OPEN UP
A LITTLE BIT.
>> AND I FEEL LIKE MANY PEOPLE
OUT THERE ARE LOOKING FOR AN
ALTERNATIVE TO DONALD TRUMP AND
SOME THINK THAT THE LEFT HAS
GONE TOO LEFT, THAT THEY DON'T
WANT TO GET INTO SOCIALISM AND
THEY AREN'T IN SUPPORT OF THE
RHETORIC THAT THE PRESIDENT IS
GOING TO TALK ABOUT SO PEOPLE
ARE LOOKING FOR A HAPPY MEDIUM
BETWEEN THE TWO.
>> I KEEP HEARING FROM YOUNGER
DEMOGRAPHICS THAT THEY ARE TIRED
OF THE FIST FIGHTS AND THEY JUST
WANT SOME PEOPLE WHO CAN GET
THINGS DONE, ESPECIALLY IN A
BIPARTISAN WAY, SO WE'LL SEE
WHAT THE CANDIDATES HAVE TO SAY
NOT.
>> ALL RIGHT.
THANK YOU.
THANK YOU SO MUCH TO YOUR
PANELISTS.
IT'S A GREAT PLEASURE LISTENING
TO THEM.
LET'S BRING BACK IN OUR GUESTS
HERE IN THE STUDIO.
JACKIE, WHO DO YOU THINK STANDS
THE MOST TO LOSE TONIGHT?
>> JOE BIDEN.
HE'S -- HE'S NOT DOING SPIN ROOM
TONIGHT AND VISIT THE CHILD CARE
FACILITY 20 MILES AWAY.
I KNOW HIS TEAM HAS BEEN WORKING
FOR WEEKS, BUT HE ALSO HAS A LOT
THAT I THINK -- THAT HE NEEDS TO
EXPLAIN AND MAYBE EXPRESS SOME
REGRET FOR AND THOSE CONTRASTS
WILL STAND OUT.
YOU HAD HOT WATER, TOO, THIS
WEEKEND.
>> THANK YOU.
>> THERE ARE CONTESTS.
I'M NOT SURE.
>> I THINK THERE'S A CONTRAST
WITH PETE AND JOE BIDEN ON
ISSUES OF RACE.
I THINK THAT'S SOMETHING YOU'LL
SEE KAMALA CONTRAST BETWEEN HIM
AND EVERYONE SEEMS TO BE
ATTACKING BIDEN.
HE IS THE FRONT-RUNNER HERE AND
HE'S THE PERSON THAT EVERYONE
WILL BE GUNNINGOR.
>> IF I WAS VICE PRESIDENT BIDEN
I WOULD WRITE A SPEECH AND I
WOULD GO OVER HIS RECORD AND
HISTORY AND I WOULD ADDRESS
EVERY SINGLE THING THAT'S
PROBLEMATIC TODAY.
I'VE MADE MISTAKES.
I'M A DIFFERENT PERSON AND
THINGS WERE DIFFERENT THEN
BUTTER WHO'S WHO I AM TODAY.
I'M WILLING TO CHANGE AND TO GET
IT OUT OF THE WAY SO THAT HE CAN
MOVE ON.
>> SPEAKING OF THOSE VOTING
RECORDS, THE ONE PERSON WE'VE
NOT TALKED ABOUT IS KAMALA
HARRIS.
>> YEAH.
>> WHAT DO YOU THINK?
I MEAN, WE SAW WHEN SHE GRILLED
KAVANAUGH, WHEN SHE GRILLED A.G.
BARR, HOW WILL SHE HANDLE BEING
IN THE HOT SEAT?
>> I THINK SHE HAS THE CHALLENGE
OF HIGH EXPECTATIONS.
SHE'S, ACCORDING TO A NEW ABC
POLL, THE NUMBER ONE CANDIDATE
PEOPLE WANT TO LEARN MORE
B.PEOPLE WANT TO KNOW ABOUT WHO
SHE IS, HER BACKGROUND.
KNOW THAT SHE WAS A PROSECUTOR.
THEY LIKELY THINK THAT SHE HAD A
STRONG HOPING ROLLOUT TO HER
CAPE, VERY SMOOTH.
20,000 PEOPLE AND IT'S NOT EASY
TO BUILD AN EVENT TO OPENING
YOUR CAMPAIGN, SO I THINK THAT
SHE HAS THE CHALLENGE OF
INTRODUCING HERSELF TO THE
AMERICAN PUBLIC FOR FOLKS WHO
HAVEN'T SEEN HER AND PUTTING
THAT SUBSTANCE OUT THERE TO GO
TOE TO TOE WITH AN ELIZABETH
WARREN.
SHE'S SOMEBODY THAT YOU HAVE TO
SEE FOR YOURSELF IN ORDER TO
REALLY JUDGE.
YOU CAN'T BASED ON WHAT OTHER
PEOPLE HAVE SAID, AND IT'S
REALLY DIFFERENT THAN WHEN
YOU'RE IN THE ROOM.
>> EVERYONE IS SMALLER WHEN YOU
MEET.
EVERYONE IS SMALLER, AND
NORMALLY YOU'RE SEEING THE
TISSUES ON TELEVISION AND WHEN
YOU SEE THEM THEY ARE ALWAYS THE
SMALLER, ESPECIALLY THE WOMEN.
>> WHILE SHE'S SMALL IN STATURE
SHE HAS PRESENCE AND IS VERY
CONFIDENCE AND I WAIT FOR HER TO
SAY I FULLY INTEND TO WIN THIS
ELECTION AND GETS A SPARKLER IN
HER EYE.
NOT IN THE RACE TO RAISE HER
PROFILE.
>> BECAUSE I THINK SHE'S
ACTUALLY SOMEONE WHO COULD STAND
TO GAIN TOMORROW.
>> I MEAN, TO THE POINT THAT
EVERY TIME WE'VE SEEN HER IN A
SETTING WHERE SHE'S DEBATING
SOMEONE OR SHE'S QUESTIONING
SOMEONE, SHE STANDS OUT THE
MOST, AND I THINK WHAT'S
INTERESTING ABOUT KAMALA IS YOU
THINK ABOUT BLACK WOMEN, BLACK
WOMEN SEEING KAMALA HARRIS AS
SOMEONE WHOLE POWERS THEM,
THAT'S VERY, VERY IMPORTANT.
>> TWO VERY IMPORTANT ASPECTS.
>> I WOULDN'T UNDERESTIMATE IT.
>> AND JUST FINALLY, ONE THING
THAT WE'VE HEARD A LOT FROM
VOTERS AND THAT WE DIDN'T TOUCH
ON TONIGHT WAS THE ECONOMY.
I MEAN, SOMETHING WE HEARD FROM
THE OTHER CANDIDATES LAUGH NIGHT
WAS INTENTIONED TO SHOW YOU HOW
AN ECONOMIC PLAN UNDER A
DEMOCRATIC PRESIDENT COULD BEAT
THAT OF TRUMP.
HOW COULD THE CANDIDATES TONIGHT
DO THAT.
>> THAT'S WHERE BIDEN HAS SOME
EXPLAINING TO DO.
BECAUSE HE DID MAKE THE REMARKS
THAT WERE WIDELY CRITICIZED
ABOUT WORKING WITH
SEGREGATIONIST DEMOCRATS AND
DURING THE SAME REMARKS HE ALSO
SAID THAT NOTHING WOULD CHANGE
FOR THIS GROUP OF WEALTHY
DONORS, THAT THINGS WOULD BE
EXACTLY THE SAME AND A LOT OF
PEOPLE TOOK THAT TO INTERPRET
THEY WOULDN'T BE PAYING MORE
MONEY OR BE SUBJECT TO A WEALTH
TAX LIKE A LOT OF OTHER
CANDIDATES ARE PUSHING FOR AND
THAT'S WHERE SOMEONE LIKE BERNIE
SANDERS HAS THE OPPORTUNITY TO
SHINE, AT LEAST IN A CERTAIN AGE
GROUP POTENTIALLY BECAUSE,
AGAIN, HE DOES HAVE A
MULTI-FACETTED APPROACH TO
BUILDING THE ECONOMY WITH HIS
STUDENT DEBT PLAN, WITH HIS
WEALTH TAX, AND I THINK THAT
HE'S UNPARALED ON THE STAGE IN
TERMS OF OFFERING THAT SPECTRUM
OF POLICIES.
>> WITH LESS THAN ONE MINUTE TO
GO UNTIL THESE CANDIDATES --
THEY ARE ALREADY ON THE STAGE
AND WHEN THEY BEGIN.
DO YOU THINK IT'S GOING TO BE
MORE IMPORTANT FOR THE
CANDIDATES TO ADDRESS SOME OF
THE SHORTCOMINGS WITH THE
EVOLUTION OF THEIR IDEAS, OR DO
YOU THINK IT'S GOING TO BE MORE
IDEA FOR THEM TO BEGIN WITH A
BRAND-NEW PLAN FOR AMERICA?
>> I THINK THEY NEED TO SHOW HOW
THEY ARE BETTER THAN DONALD
TRUMP AND DEFEAT HIM.
>> SO TONIGHT ABOUT TRUMP.
>> THANK YOU SO MUCH, AND THIS
IS THE MOMENT WE'VE BEEN WAITING
FOR.
WE'RE ABOUT TO SEE THE
CANDIDATES TAKE THE STAGE.
STAY RIGHT HERE BECAUSE WE ARE
HEADED STRAIGHT TO MIAMI.
.
>>> GOOD EVENING, I'M LESTER
HOLT.
WELCOME TO NIGHT TWO OF THE
DEMOCRATIC DEBATE IN THE 2020
RACE FOR PRESIDENT.
>> LAST NIGHT WE HEARD FROM TEN
CANDIDATES.
TEN MORE TAKE THE STAGE.
>> AGAIN TONIGHTLA WE'LL BE JOID
IN THE QUESTIONING BY OUR
COLLEAGUE JOSE DIAZ BALART,
CHUCK TODD AND RACHEL MADDOW.
>> TONIGHT, ROUND TWO, MICHAEL
BENNET, FORMER VICE PRESIDENT
JOE BIDEN, SOUTH BEND INDIANA
MAYOR PETE BUTTIGIEG, KIRSTEN
GILLIBRAND, KAMALA HARRIS,
FORMER COLORADO GOVERNOR JOHN
HICKENLOOPER, BERNIE SANDERS,
CALIFORNIA CONGRESSMAN ERIC
SWALWELL, AUTHOR MARY ANNEMA
WILLIAM SON.
DECISION 2020, THE DEMOCRATIC
CANDIDATE DEBATE.
LIVE FROM MIAMI, FLORIDA.
[ CHEERS AND APPLAUSE ]
>> GOOD EVENING ONCE AGAIN.
WELCOME TO THE CANDIDATES AND
OURR SPIRITED AUDIENCE TONIGHT
HERE AND ACROSS AMERICA.
WE CONTINUE THE SPIRITED DEBATE
ABOUT THE FUTURE OF THE COUNTRY,
HOW TO ATTACK OUR MOST PRESSING
PROBLEMS AND GETTING TO THE
HEART OF THE BIGGESTF  ISSUES I
THIS DEMOCRATIC PRIMARY.
>> TONIGHT WE ARE TALKING ABOUT
HEALTH CARE, ARIMMIGRATION.
WE'RE GOING TO DIVE INTO THE
ECONOMY, CLIMATE CHANGE AS WELL.
>> THE I RULES OF THE ROAD BEFO
WE BEGIN MAY SOUND FAMILIAR.
20 CANDIDATES QUALIFIED FOR THE
FIRST DEBATE.
WE HEARD FROM TEN LAST NIGHT.
WE'LL HEAR FROM TEN MORE
TONIGHT.
THE BREAKDOWN WAS SELECTED AT
RANDOM.
THEY HAVE 60AT SECONDS TO ANSWE
AND 30 SECONDS FOR A FOLLOW UP.
>> BECAUSE OF THE LARGE FIELD
NOT EVERY PERSON CAN WEIGH IN AN
EVERY TOPIC.
OVER THE COURSE OF THE NEXT TWO
HOURS WE WILL HEAR FROM
EVERYONE.
>> WE LOVE OUR AUDIENCE BUT WE'D
LIKE TO ASK THEM TO KEEP THEIR
REACTIONS TO A MINIMUM.
WE ARE NOT GOING TO HOLD BACK IN
MAKING SURE THE CANDIDATES STICK
TO TIME.
WITH THAT BUSINESS TAKEN CARE OF
LET'S GET TO IT.
WE'LL START TODAY WITH SENATOR
SANDERS.
GOOD EVENING.
YOU HAVEND CALLED FOR BIG NEW
GOVERNMENT BENEFITS LIKE
UNIVERSAL HEALTH CARE AND FREE
COLLEGE.
IN A RECENT INTERVIEW YOU SAID
YOU SUSPECTED AMERICANS WOULD
BE,  AQUOTE, DELIGHTED TO PAY ME
TAXES FOR THINGS LIKE THAT.
MY QUESTION IS WILL TAXES GO UP
FOR THE MIDDLE CLASS IN A
SANDERS ADMINISTRATION AND IF
SO, HOW DO YOU SELL IT TO
VOTERS?
>> YOU'RE QUITE RIGHT.
WE HAVE A NEW VISION FOR
AMERICA.
AT A TIME WHEN WE HAVE THREE
PEOPLE IN THIS COUNTRY OWNING
MORE WEALTH THAN THE BOTTOM HALF
OF AMERICA WHILE 500,000 PEOPLE
ARE SLEEPING OUT ON THE STREETS
TODAY, WE THINK IT IS TIME FOR
CHANGE, REAL CHANGE.
BY THAT I MEAN THAT HEALTH CARE,
IN MY VIEW, IS A HUMAN RIGHT.
WE HAVE GOT TO PASS A MEDICARE
FOR ALL, SINGLE PAYER SYSTEM.
UNDER THAT YESYSTEM, BY THE WAY
THE VAST MAJORITY OF THE PEOPLE
IN THIS COUNTRY WILL BE PAYING
SIGNIFICANTLY LESS FOR HEALTH
CARE THAN THEY ARE RIGHT NOW.
I BELIEVE THAT EDUCATION IS THE
FUTURE FOR THIS COUNTRY.
THAT IS WHY I BELIEVE WE MUST
MAKE PUBLIC COLLEGES AND
UNIVERSITIES TUITION-FREE AND
ELIMINATE STUDENT DEBT.
WE DO THAT BY PLACING A TAX ON
WALL STREET.
EVERY PROPOSAL THAT I HAVE
BROUGHT FORTH IS FULLY PAID FOR.
>> SENATOR SANDERS, I WILL GIVE
YOU TEN SECONDS TO ANSWER THIS
VERY DIRECT QUESTION.
WILL YOU RAISE TAXES FOR THE
MIDDLE CLASS IN A SANDERS
ADMINISTRATION?
>> PEOPLE WHO HAVE HEALTH CARE
UNDER MEDICARE>> FOR ALL WILL HE
NO PREMIUMS, NO DEDUCTIBLES, NO
COPAYMENTS, NO OUT OF POCKET
EXPENSES.
YES.
THEY WILL PAY MORE IN TAXES BUT
LESS IN HEALTH CARE FOR WHAT
THEY GET.
>> THANK YOU, SENATOR.
>> SENATOR SANDERS --
>> SENATOR BENNETT, WE'LL GET TO
EVERYBODY, I PROMISE.
I PROMISE EVERYBODY WILL GET IN
HERE, I PROMISE.
VICE PRESIDENT BIDEN, SENATOR
SANDERS HAS BEEN CALLING FOR A
REVOLUTION.
RECENTLY IN REMARKS TO A GROUP
OF G WEALTHY DONORS AS YOU WERE
SPEAKING ABOUT THE PROBLEMS OF
INCOME INEQUALITY YOU SAID WE
SHOULDN'T DEMONIZERO THE RICH.
YOU SAID NOBODY HAS TO BE
PUNISHED.
NO ONE'S STANDARD OF LIVING
WOULD CHANGE.
NOTHING WOULD FUNDAMENTALLY
CHANGE.
THAT?O YOU MEAN BY
>> LOOK, DONALD TRUMP THINKS
WALL STREET BUILT AMERICA.
MY DAD HAD AN EXPRESSION.
A JOB IS ABOUT MORE THAN A
PAYCHECK.ER
IT'S ABOUT DIGNITY, RESPECT,
LOOKING YOUR KID IN THE EYEMY A
SAYING EVERYTHING WILL BE OKAY.
TOO MANY PEOPLE IN THE MIDDLE
CLASINS HAVE HAD THE BOTTOM FAL
OUT UNDER THIS A PROPOSAL.
I'M SAYING WE HAVE TO BE
STRAIGHTFORWARD.
WE HAVE TO MAKE SURE WE
UNDERSTAND THAT TO RETURN
DIGNITY TO THE MIDDLE CLASS THEY
HAVE TO HAVE INSURANCE THAT'S
COVERED AND THEY CAN AFFORD IT.
THEY HAVE TO. MAKE SURE WE ARE N
A SITUATION WHERE THERE IS
CONTINUINGN  EDUCATION AND THEY
CAN PAY FOR IT.
WE HAVE TO MAKE SURE THEY CAN
BREATHE AIR THAT'S CLEAN AND
THEY HAVE WATERCL THEY CAN DRIN.
DONALD TRUMP PUT US IN A
HORRIBLE SITUATION.
WE HAVE ENORMOUS INCOME
INEQUALITY.
WE CAN MAKE CUTS IN THE $1.6
TRILLION IN TAXHE LOOPHOLES AND
WOULD BE GOING ABOUT ELIMINATING
DONALD TRUMP'S TAX CUTS TO THE
WEALTHY.
>> VICE PRESIDENT BIDEN, THANK
YOU.
SENATOR HARRIS, THERE IS A LOT
OF TALK ABOUT NEW BENEFITS LIKE
STUDENT LOAN CANCELLATION, FREE
COLLEGE, HEALTH CARE AND MORE.
DO YOU THINK DEMOCRATS HAVE A
RESPONSIBILITY TO EXPLAIN HOW
THEY WILL PAY FOR EVERY PROPOSAL
THEY MAKE ALONG THOSE LINES?
>> LET
ME TELL YOU SOMETHING.
I HEAR THAT QUESTION, BUT WHERE
WAS THAT QUESTION WHEN THE
REPUBLICANSMP AND DONALD TRUMP
PASSED A BILL THAT BENEFITTED
THE BIGGEST CORPORATIONS IN THIS
COUNTRY AND THE TOP 1%
CONTRIBUTING AT LEAST $1
TRILLION TO THE DEBT OF AMERICA
WHICH MIDDLE CLASSBT FAMILIES WL
PAY FOR ONE WAY OR ANOTHER.
WORKING A FAMILIES NEED SUPPORT
AND NEED
TO BE LIFTED UP.
FRANKLY, THIS ECONOMY IS NOT
WORKINGAN FOR WORKING PEOPLE.
FOR TOO LONG THE RULES HAVE BEEN
WORKING IN FAVOR OF THE PEOPLE
WHO HAVE THE MOST AND NOT IN
FAVOR OF THE PEOPLE WHO WORK THE
MOST.
I AM PROPOSING WE CHANGE THE TAX
CODE.
FOR EVERY FAMILY THAT'S MAKING
LESS THAN $100,000 A YEAR THEY
RECEIVE A TAX CREDIT THEY CAN
COLLECT OF $500 A MONTH WHICH
MAKES ALL THE DIFFERENCE BETWEEN
THOSE FAMILIES GETTING THROUGH
THETH END OF THE MONTH WITH
DIGNITY AND SUPPORTT OR NOT.
ON DAY ONE, I WILL REPEAL THE
TAX BILL THAT BENEFITS THE TOP
1% AND THE BIGGEST CORPORATIONS
OF AMERICA.
>> SENATOR HARRIS, THANK YOU.
GOVERNOR HICKENLOOPER YOU WARNED
DEMOCRATS WILL LOSE IN 2020 IF
THEY EMBRACE SOCIALISM, AS YOU
PUT IT.
YOU WERE BOOED AT THE CALIFORNIA
DEMOCRATIC CONVENTION WHEN YOU
SAID THAT.
ONLY ONE CANDIDATE ON THIS
STAGE, SENATOR SANDERS
IDENTIFIES HIMSELF AS A
DEMOCRATIC SOCIALIST.
WHAT ARE THE POLICIES OR T
POSITIONS OF YOUR OPPONENTS YOU
THINK ARE VEERING TOWARD
SOCIALISM?
>> I THINK THE BOTTOM LINE IS IF
WE DON'T CLEARLY DEFINE THAT WE
ARE NOT SOCIALISTS THE
REPUBLICANS WILL COME AT US
EVERY WAY THEY CAN AND CALL US
SOCIALISTS.
IF YOU LOOK AT THE GREEN NEW
DEAL WHICH I ADMIRE THE SENSE OF
URGENCY ANDD HOW IMPORTANT IT I
TO DO CLIMATE CHANGE, I'M A
SCIENTIST.
WE CAN'T PROMISE EVERY AMERICAN
A GOVERNMENT JOB.
IF YOU WANT UNIVERSAL HEALTH
CARE COVERAGE, HEALTH CARE IS A
RIGHT NOT A PRIVILEGE.
YOU CAN'T EXPECT TO ELIMINATE
PRIVATE INSURANCE FOR 180
MILLION PEOPLE, MANY OF WHOM
DON'T WANT TO GIVE IT UP.
IN COLORADO WE BROUGHT
BUSINESSES AND NONPROFITS
TOGETHER.
WE GOT NEAR UNIVERSAL HEALTH
CARE COVERAGE.
WE WERE THE FIRST STATE IN
AMERICA TOGE HAVE THE OIL AND G
INDUSTRY AND ENVIRONMENTAL
COMMUNITY TO ADDRESS METHANE
EMISSIONS.
WE WERE THE FIRST PLACE TO
EXPAND REPRODUCTIVE RIGHTS ON A
SCALE BASIS WE REDUCED TEEN
PREGNANCY BY 54%.
WE HAVE DONE THE BIG PROGRESSIVE
THINGS PEOPLE SAID COULDN'T BE
DONE.
I HAVE DONE WHAT PRETTY MUCH
EVERYONE ELSE UP HERE IS STILL
TALKING ABOUT DOING.
>> GOVERNOR SANDERS, I WILL GIVE
YOU A CHANCE TO WEIGH IN.
WHAT'S YOUR RESPONSE TO THOSE
WHO SAY NOMINATING A SOCIALIST
WOULDIA RE-ELECT DONALD TRUMP?
>> I THINK THE RESPONSE AT THE
LAST POLL I SAW HAD US TEN
POINTS AHEAD OF DONALD TRUMP.
THE AMERICAN PEOPLE UNDERSTAND
THAT TRUMP IS A PHONY.
TRUMP IS A PATHOLOGICAL LIAR AND
A RACIST AND THAT HE LIED TO THE
AMERICAN PEOPLE DURING HIS
CAMPAIGN.
HE SAID HE WAS GOING TO STAND UP
FOR WORKING FAMILIES.
WELL, PRESIDENT TRUMP, YOU'RE
NOT STANDING UP FOR WORKING
FAMILIES WHEN YOU'RET  TRYING T
THROWNG 32 MILLION PEOPLE OFF T
HEALTH CARE THAT THEY HAVE AND
83% OF YOUR TAX BENEFITS GO
TO THE TOP 1%.
THAT'S HOW WE BEAT TRUMP.
WE EXPOSE HIM FOR THE FRAUD THAT
HE IS.
>> SENATOR --
>> THE DEBATE WE ARE HAVING IN
OUR PARTY RIGHT NOW IS
CONFUSING.
THE TRUTH IS THERE IS A BIG
DIFFERENCE BETWEEN CAPITALISM ON
THE ONE HAND AND GREED ON THE
OTHER.
SO ALL THE THINGS THAT WE ARE
TRYING TO CHANGE IS WHEN
MORE ABOUT RE
PROFITS THAN THEY DO ABOUT
PEOPLE.
SO THEY'RE TALKING ABOUT ENDING
GUN VIOLENCE.
IT'S THE GREED OF THE NRA AND
THE GUN MANUFACTURERS THAT MAKE
ANY PROGRESS IMPOSSIBLE.
IT'SHE THE GREED OF INSURANCE
COMPANIES.
>> THANK  AYOU.
>> THERE MAY NOT BE DISAGREEMENT
IN THE PARTY BECAUSE IN TRUTH WE
WANT --
>> SENATOR, THANK YOU.
>> WE DON'T WANT CORRUPTED
CAPITALISM.
>> THANK YOU.
I WANT TO BE
LI FAIR TO ALL THE
CANDIDATES.
SENATOR BENNET YOU SAID IT IS
POSSIBLE TO WRITELE POLICY
PROPOSALS WITH NO BASIS IN
REALITY.
YOU MIGHT AS WELL CALL THEM
CANDY.
WERE YOU REFERRING TO ANY
PROPOSAL INAR PARTICULAR?
>> WAS THAT FOR ME?
IT SOUNDED LIKE ME, THANK YOU.
>> IT WAS YOU.
>> I APPRECIATE IT.
I AGREE WITH BERNIE.
40 YEARS OF NOW ECONOMIC GROWTH
FOR 90% OF THE AMERICAN PEOPLE.
FAMILIES IN THE TOP 1% HAVE THE
SAME WEALTH AS THE BOTTOM 1%.
WE HAVE THE WORST INCOME
INEQUALITY WE HAVE HAD IN A
HUNDRED YEARS.
IN  DISAGREE ON HIS SOLUTION OF
MEDICARE FOR ALL.
I HAVE PROPOSED GETTING TO
UNIVERSAL HEALTH CARE WHICH WE
NEED TOGE DO.
IT IS A RIGHT.
HEALTH CARE IS A RIGHT.
WE NEED TO GET TO UNIVERSAL
HEALTH CARE.
I BELIEVE THE WAY TO DO IT IS BY
FINISHING THE WORK WE STARTED
WITH OBAMACARE AND CREATING A
PUBLIC OPTION THAT EVERY FAMILY
AND EVERY PERSON IN AMERICA CAN
MAKE A CHOICE FOR THEIR FAMILY
ABOUT WHETHER THEY WANT A PUBLIC
OPTION WHICH FOR THEM WOULD BE
LIKE HAVING MEDICARE FOR ALL OR
IF THEY WANT TO KEEP PRIVATE
INSURANCE.
I BELIEVE WE'LL GET THERE MORE
QUICKLY IF WE DO THAT.
IF I COULD FINISH, BERNIE
MENTIONED THE TAXES WE WOULD
HAVE TOIM PAY.
BECAUSE OF THE TAXES VERMONT
REJECTED MEDICARE FOR ALL.
>> WHOA, WHOA, SENATOR.
WE ARE GOING TO TALK ABOUT
HEALTH CARE AT HELENGTH.
FOR THE MOMENT --
>> I WROTE THE PART IN SENATOR
SANDERS' BILL THAT IS THE
TRANSITION WHICH MERGES WHAT THE
TWO SENATORS SAID.
>> SENATOR.
>> THE TRUTH IS YOU HAVE A
BUY-IN OVERUT A FOUR OR FIVE-YE
PERIOD.
YOU MOVE US TOBUR  SINGLE PAYERE
QUICKLY.
>> WE WILL GET TO THIS, SENATOR.
WE WILL.
BEFORE WE DO, I WANT TO SAY
HELLO, GOOD EVENING, BUENOS
NOCHES TO MAYOR PETE BUTTIGIEG.
[ SPEAKING SPANISH ]
>> MANY OF YOUR COLLEAGUES ON
STAGE SUPPORT FREE COLLEGE.
YOU DO NOT.
WHY NOT?
>> SURE.
COLLEGE AFFORDABILITY IS
PERSONAL FOR US.
WE HAVE SIX-FIGURE STUDENT DEBT.
I BELIEVE IN REDUCING STUDENT
DEBT.
IT'S H LOGICAL TO ME IF YOU CAN
REFINANCE YOUR HOUSE YOU OUGHT
TO BE ABLE TO REFINANCE YOUR
STUDENT DEBT.
I BELIEVE IN FREE COLLEGE FOR
LOW AND MIDDLE INCOME STUDENTS
FOR WHOM COSTS COULD BE A
BARRIER.
I DON'T BELIEVE IT MAKES SENSE
TO HAVE FAMILIES SUBSIDIZE T
BILLIONAIRES.
THE CHILDREN OF THE WEALTHIEST
AMERICANS CAN PAY A LITTLE BIT
OF TUITION.
WHILE I WANT TUITION COSTS TO GO
DOWN I DON'T THINK WE CAN BUY
DOWN EVERY LAST PENNY.
SOMETHING ELSE DOESN'T GET
TALKED ABOUT IN THE COLLEGE
AFFORDABILITY DEBATE.
YES, IT NEEDS TO BE MORE
AFFORDABLE TO GO TO COLLEGE.
IT NEEDS TO BE MORE AFFORDABLE
TO NOT GO TO COLLEGE.
YOU SHOULD BE ABLE TO LIVE WELL,
AFFORD RENT, BE GENEROUS TO YOUR
CHURCH AND LITTLE LEAGUE WHETHER
YOU WENT TO COLLEGE OR NOT.
>> I HAVE $100,000 IN STUDENT
LOAN DEBT MYSELF.
YOU CAN'T COUNT ON PEOPLE IN
GOVERNMENT WHO WERE HERE WHEN
THE PROBLEM WAS CREATED TO SOLVE
IT.
IT'S THE NEXT GENERATION, THE 40
MILLION OF US WHO CAN'T START A
FAMILY, CAN'T TAKE A GOOD IDEA
AND START A BUSINESS AND CAN'T
BUY OUR FIRST HOME.
THIS IS THE GENERATION THAT CAN
SOLVE STUDENT LOANN DEBT.
THIS GENERATION IS READY TO
LEAVE.
>>DY MR. YANG, YOUR SIGNATURE
POLICY IS TO GIVE EVERY ADULT IN
THE UNITED STATES $1,000 A
MONTH, NO QUESTIONS ASKED.
>> THAT'S NORIGHT.
>> THAT'S LIKE $3.2 TRILLION A
YEAR.
HOW WOULD YOU DO THAT?
>> I'M SORRY?
>> HOW WOULD YOU DO THAT?
>>U  OH, SO IT'S DIFFICULT TO D
IFIF YOU HAVE COMPANIES LIKE
AMAZON, TRILLION DOLLAR TECH
COMPANIES PAYING ZERO IN TAXES
WHILE THEY CLOSE L 30% OF OUR
STORES.
WE NEENGD TO PUT THE AMERICAN
PEOPLE IN A POSITION TO BENEFIT
FROM THE ECONOMY.
IF WE HAD A VALUE-ADDED TAX EVEN
HALF THE EUROPEAN LEVEL COMBINED
WITH THE MONEY IN OUR HANDS IT
WOULD BE A TRICKLE-UP ECONOMY
FROM PEOPLE AND COMMUNITIES UP.
WE WOULD SPEND THE MONEY.Y.
IT WOULD CIRCULATE THROUGH OUR
NEIGHBORHOODS CREATING JOBS,
MAKING OUR FAMILIES STRONGER AND
HEALTHIER.
WE WOULD SAVE MONEY ON
INCARCERATION, HOMELESSNESS
SERVICES, EMERGENCY ROOM HEALTH
CARE.
AND HAVING A STRONGER, HEALTHIER
POPULATIONRO WOULD INCREASE GDPY
$700 BILLION.
THIS IS A MOVE WE HAVE TO MAKE
AS TECHNOLOGY AUTOMATES THE WAY
MILLIONS OF AMERICAN JOBS --
IT'S T WHY DONALD TRUMP IS OUR
PRESIDENT TODAY.
WE AUTOMATED AUTOMOTIVE JOBS AND
WE ARE DOING THE SAME TO RETAIL,
CALL CENTERS, FAST FOOD, TRUCK
DRIVING AND ON AND ON M THROUGH
THE ECONOMY.
>>
IF I CAN UNDERSTAND BETTER
YOU'RERE SAYING $1,000 A MONTH R
EVERYONE OVER 18 BUT A
VALUE-ADDED TAX SO YOU CAN SPEND
THAT $1,000 ON VALUE-ADDED TAX?
>> THE VALUE ADDED TAX YOU WOULD
INCREASE THE BUYING POWER OF THE
BOTTOM 94% OF AMERICANS.
YOU WOULD HAVE $12,000 PER
INDIVIDUAL PER
YEAR.
FOR THE AVERAGE HOUSEHOLD OF TWO
ADULTS IT WOULD BE $24,000 A
YEAR.
>> MANY TALK ABOUT SELF-DRIVING
CARS, ROBOTS, DRONES, ARTIFICIAL
INTELLIGENCE WILL COST THEM
JOBS.
WHAT WOULD YOU. DO TO HELP PEOPE
GET THEE SKILLS THEY NEED TO
ADAPT TO THESK NEW WORLD?
>> WE MUST ALWAYS BE A COUNTRY
WHERE TECHNOLOGY CREATES MORE
JOBS THAN IT DISPLACES.
I HAVE SEEN THE ANXIETY IN
AMERICA WHERE THE MANUFACTURING
FLOORSRS GO FROM 1,000 TO A
HUNDRED TO ONE.
WE HAVE TO MODERNIZE OUR
SCHOOLS.
VALUE THE TEACHERS WHO PREPARE
OUR KIDS, WIPE STUDENT DEBT WHO
GOES TO A COMMUNITY WHO NEEDS
IT.
JOSE, I WAS 6 YEARS OLD WHEN A
PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE CAME TO
THE CALIFORNIA DEMOCRATIC
CONVENTION AND SAID IT'S TIME TO
PASS THE TORCH TO A NEW
GENERATION OF AMERICANS.
THAT CANDIDATE WAS THEN SENATOR
JOE BIDEN.N.
JOE BIDEN WAS RIGHT WHEN HE SAID
IT WAS TIME TO PASS THE TORCH TO
A NEW GENERATION 32 YEARS AGO.
HE'S STILL RIGHT TODAY.
IF WE ARE GOING TO SOLVE THE
ISSUES OF AUTOMATION, PASS THE
TORCH, CLIMATE CHAOS, PASS THE
TORCH, STUDENT LOAN DEBT, PASS
THE TORCH, ENDING GUN VIOLENCE
FOR FAMILIES WHO ARE FEARFUL OF
SENDING THEIR KIDS TO SCHOOL,
PASS THE TORCH.
>> WOULD YOU LIKE TO SING A
TORCH SONG?
>> I WOULD.
ONTO THE LL HOLDING
TORCH.
WE HAVE TO MAKE SURE EVERYBODY
IS PREPARED BETTER TO GO ON FOR
AN EDUCATION.
THE FACT IS THAT'S WHY I PROPOSE
FOCUSING ON SCHOOLS THAT ARE IN
DISTRESS.
WE SHOULD TRIPLE THE AMOUNT OF
MONEY FORT  TITLE ONE SCHOOLS,
HAVE UNIVERSAL PRE-K.
EVERY PERSON WHO GRADUATES FROM
HIGH SCHOOL, 65 OUT OF A HUNDRED
NEED SOMETHING10 BEYOND HIGH
SCHOOL.
WE SHOULD PROVIDE FOR THEM TO
GET THE EDUCATION.
HAVE ANYONE HAVE TO PAY BACK
STUDENT DEBT WHEN THEY GET BACK
MAKING LESS THAN $25,000 A YEAR.
THEIR DEBT IS FROZEN, NO
INTEREST PAYMENT UNTIL THEY GET
BEYOND THAT.
WE CAN'T PUT PEOPLE IN A
POSITION WHERE THEY CAN'T MOVE
ON.ON
THERE IS A LOT WE CAN DO.
WE HAVE TOLK MAKE CONTINUING
EDUCATION AVAILABLE FOR
EVERYONE.
EVERYONE CAN COMPETE IN THE 21st
CENTURY.
WE ARE NOT DOING THAT NOW.
>> AS THE YOUNGEST GUY ON THE
STAGE I SHOULD CONTRIBUTE TO THE
GENERATION COMMENT.
>> BEFORE WE MOVE ON --
[ SPEAKING SIMULTANEOUSLY ]
>> -- TO TAKE ON THE FOSSIL FUEL
INDUSTRY, TO TAKE ON THE BIG
MONEY INTERESTS WHO HAVE
UNBELIEVABLE INFLUENCE OVER THE
ECONOMIC AND POLITICAL LIFE OF
THIS  TCOUNTRY.
>> SENATOR HARRIS --
>> I'M SORRY.
WE WILL LET YOU ALL SPEAK.
SENATOR HARRIS.
>> HEY, GUYS, YOU KNOW WHAT?
AMERICA DOESN'T WANT TO WITNESS
A FOOD FIGHT.
THEY WANT TO KNOW HOW WE'LL PUT
FOOD ON THE TABLE.
[ CHEERS AND APPLAUSE ]
ON THAT POINT PART OF THE ISSUE
IN AMERICA TODAY AND WE HAVE
BEEN TRAVELING THE COUNTRY.
I CERTAINLY HAVE.
I'M MEETING PEOPLE WORKING TWO,
THREE JOBS.
THIS PRESIDENT WALKS AROUND
TALKING ABOUT AND FLOUTING HIS
GREAT ECONOMY.
MY GREAT ECONOMY, MY GREAT
ECONOMY.
HOW ARE YOU MEASURING THE
GREATNESS OF THE ECONOMY?
HE TALKS ABOUT THE STOCK MARKET.
THAT'S FINE IF YOU OWN STOCKS.
SO MANY FAMILIES IN AMERICA DO
NOT.
YOU ASK HOW ARE YOU MEASURING
THE GREATNESS OF THE ECONOMY.
THEY POINT TO THE JOBS NUMBERS
AND UNEMPLOYMENT.
YEAH, PEOPLETH IN AMERICA ARE
WORKING TWO AND THREETH JOBS.
LET'S BE CLEAR.
IN OUR AMERICA NO ONE SHOULD
HAVE TO WORK MORE THAN ONE JOB
A ROOF OVER THEIR HEAD
ANDER FOOD ON THE TABLE.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
EXPRESSED AN
INTEREST IN TALKING ABOUT HEALTH
CARE.
THIS IS GOING TO BE A SHOW OF
HANDS  LQUESTION.
WE ASKEDED A QUESTION ABOUT HEAH
CARE LAST NIGHT.
IT SPURRED A LOT OF DISCUSSION,
AS YOU KNOW.
WE'LL DO IT AGAIN NOW.
MANY PEOPLE WATCHING AT HOME
HAVE HEALTH INSURANCE THROUGH
THEIR EMPLOYER.
WHO HERE WOULD ABOLISH PRIVATE
A LTH INSURANCE IN FAVOR OF
GOVERNMENT-RUN PLAN.
KIRSTEN GILLIBRAND.
>> THIS IS A VERY IMPORTANT
ISSUE.
THE PLAN IS HOW YOU GET TO
SINGLE PAYER.
IT HAS A BUY IN TRANSITION
PERIOD WHICH IS IMPORTANT.
I RAN IN A 2-1 DISTRICT.
I RAN ON MEDICARE FOR ALL AND
WON THAT DISTRICT TWICE.
THEDI WAY I FORMULATED IT WAS
SIMPLE.
ANYONEE  WITHOUT ACCESS COULD B
IN A PERCENTAGE OF INCOME THEY
COULD AFFORD.
THAT'S WHATAN WE PUT INTO THE
TRANSITION PERIOD FOR OUR
MEDICARE FOR ALL PLAN.
I BELIEVE WE NEED TO GET TO
UNIVERSAL HEALTH CARE AS AR
RIGHT, NOT A PRIVILEGE TO SINGLE
PAYER.
THE QUICKEST WAY YOU GET THERE
IS CREATE COMPETITION WITH THE
INSURERS.
GOD BLESS THEM IFF THEY WANT TO
COMPETE.
THEY CAN TRY.
THEY HAVE NEVER PUT PEOPLE OVER
PROFITS.
I DOUBT THEY EVER WILL.
WHAT WILL HAPPEN IS PEOPLE WILL
CHOOSE MEDICARE.
WE'LL GET TO MEDICARE FOR ALL
AND THE STEPS TO SINGLE PAYER IS
SO SHORT.
I WOULD MAKE IT AN EARNED
BENEFIT LIKE SOCIAL SECURITY.
SO YOU BUY IN YOUR WHOLE LIFE.
IT IS THERE FOR YOU, PERMANENT
AND UNIVERSAL.
>> SENATOR, I WANT TO PUT THE
SAME QUESTION TO MAYOR
BUTTIGIEG.
>> EVERYBODY WHO SAYS MEDICARE
FOR ALL, EVERY PERSON IN
POLITICS WHOAR ALLOWS THAT PHRA
TOHO ESCAPE THEIR LIPS HAS A
RESPONSIBILITY TO EXPLAIN HOW
YOU ARE
ACTUALLY SUPPOSED TO GET
FROM HERE TO THERE.
I WOULD CALL IT MEDICARE FOR ALL
WHO WANTSI IT.
YOU TAKE SOMETHING LIKE
MEDICARE, A FLAVOR OF THAT, MAKE
IT AVAILABLE ON THE EXCHANGES.
PEOPLE CAN BUY IN.
IF WE'RE RIGHT THAT IT WOULD BE
A MORE INCLUSIVE PLAN, A MORE
EFFICIENT PLAN THAN THE
CORPORATE ANSWERS IT WOULD BE A
NATURAL GLIDE PATH TO THE SINGLE
PAYER ENVIRONMENT.
LET'S REMEMBER, IN COUNTRIES
WITH OUTRIGHT SOCIALIZED
MEDICINES LIKE ENGLAND, THERE IS
A PRIVATE SECTOR.
FOR THE PRIMARY CARE WE CAN'T
RELY ON CORPORATE.
THIS IS PERSONAL FOR ME.
I STARTED THIS YEAR DEALING WITH
THE TERMINAL ILLNESS OF MY
FATHER.
I MAKEI  DECISIONS FOR A LIVING
AND NOTHING COULD HAVE PREPARED
ME FOR THE DECISIONS MY FAMILY
FACED.
WE NEVER HAD TO MAKE THE
DECISIONSMI BASED ON WHETHER IT
WAS GOING TO BANKRUPT OUR FAMILY
BECAUSE OF MEDICARE.
I WANT EVERY FAMILY TO HAVE THE
SEEM FREEDOM TO DO WHAT IS
MEDICALLY RIGHT.
>> YOUR TIME IS COMPLETE.
VICE PRESIDENT BIDEN, YOU WERE
ONE OF THE ARCHITECTS OF
OBAMACARE.
WHERE DO WE GO FROM HERE?
>> LOOK, THIS IS VERY PERSONAL
TO ME.
WHEN MY WIFE AND DAUGHTER WERE
KILLED IN AN AUTOMOBILE
ACCIDENT, MY BOYS WERE BADLY
INJURED, I COULDN'T IMAGINE WHAT
IT WOULD HAVE BEEN LIKE IF I
HADN'T HAD ADEQUATE HEALTH CARE.
WHEN MY SON CAME HOME FROM IRAQ
AND WAS DIAGNOSED WITH TERMINAL
CANCER AND WAS GIVEN MONTHS TO
LIVE, I CAN'T FATHOM WHAT WOULD
HAVE HAPPENED IF THEY SAID, BY
THE WAY, THE LAST SIX MONTHS OF
YOUR LIFE, YOU'RE ON YOUR OWN.
WE'RE CUTTING YOU OFF.
YOU USED UP YOUR TIME.
THE FACT IS THE QUICKEST WAY TO
DO IT IS BUILD ON OBAMACARE,
BUILD ON WHAT WE DID.
SECONDLY, MAKE SURE THAT
EVERYONE DOES HAVE AN OPTION.
EVERYONE WHETHER THEY HAVE
PRIVATE INSURANCE, EMPLOYER
INSURANCE OR NO INSURANCE.
THEY COULD BUY INTO THE EXCHANGE
IN A MED KARE-LIKE PLAN.
URGENCY MATTERS.
THERE'S PEOPLE RIGHT NOW FACING
WHAT I FACED AND WHAT WE FACED
WITHOUT THE HELP I HAD.
WE MUST MOVE MOW.
I AM AGAINST ANYONE WHO WANTS TO
TAKE DOWN OBAMACARE.
>> SENATOR SANDERS YOU BASICALLY
WANT TO SCRAP THE PRIVATE HEALTH
INSURANCE SYSTEM AS WERA KNOW I
AND REPLACE ITT WITH A
GOVERNMENT-RUN PLAN.
NONE OF THE STATES THAT TRIED
SOMETHING LIKE THAT --
CALIFORNIA, VERMONT STRUGGLED
WITH IT AND HAVE BEEN
SUCCESSFUL.
IF POLITICIANS CAN'T MAKE IT
WORK THERE HOW DO YOU IMPLEMENT
IT ON A NATIONAL LEVEL?
>> I FIND IT HARD TO BELIEVE
THAT EVERY OTHER MAJOR COUNTRY
INCLUDING CANADA SOMEHOW HASIN
FIGURED OUT A WAY TO PROVIDE
HEALTH CARE TO EVERY MAN, WOMAN
AND CHILD.
IN MOST CASES THEY ARE SPENDING
50% PER CAPITA WHAT THEY ARE
SPENDING.
LET'S BE CLEAR.
LET US BE VERY CLEAR.
THE FUNCTION OF HEALTH CARE
TODAY FROM THE INSURANCE AND
DRUG COMPANY PERSPECTIVE IS NOT
TO PROVIDE QUALITY CARE TO ALL
IN A COST EFFECTIVE WAY.
THE FUNCTION OF THE HEALTH CARE
SYSTEM TODAYTI IS TO MAKE BILLIS
IN PROFITS FOR THE INSURANCE
COMPANIES AND LAST YEAR IF YOU
COULD BELIEVEIE IT, WHILE WE PA
THEE HIGHEST PRICES IN THE WORL
FOR PRESCRIPTION DRUGS AND I
WILL LOWER PRESCRIPTION DRUG
PRICES IN HALF IN THIS COUNTRY,
TOP TEN COMPANIES MADE $69
BILLION IN PROFITS.
THEY WILL SPEND HUNDREDS OF
MILLIONS OF DOLLARS LYING TO THE
AMERICAN PEOPLE TELLING US WHY
WE CANNOTT HAVE A MEDICARE FOR
ALL --
>> I HAVE TO FOLLOW UP.
HOW DO YOU IMPLEMENT IT ON A
NATIONAL LEVEL
GIVEN THE FACT
THAT IT'S NOT SUCCEEDED AND
OTHER STATES HAVEE TRIED.
>> WE'LL DO IT THE WAY REAL
CHANGE HAS ALWAYS TAKEN PLACE.
WHETHER IT WAS THE LABOR
MOVEMENT, CIVIL RIGHTS MOVEMENT
OR THE WOMEN'S MOVEMENT.
WE WILL HAVE MEDICARE FOR ALL.
WHEN TENS OF MILLIONS OF PEOPLE
AREEN PREPARED TO STAND UP AND
TELL THE INSURANCECE COMPANIES D
THE DRUG COMPANIES THEIR DAY IS
GONE, THAT HEALTH CARE IS A
HUMAN RIGHT, NOT SOMETHING TO
MAKE HUGE PROFITS WITH.
>> THIS IS A QUESTION FOR MS.
WILLIAMSON.
WE HAVEE TALKED ABOUT ACCESS TO
HEALTH INSURANCE.
FOR MANY AMERICANS THE MOST
PRESSING CONCERN IS THE HIGH
COST OF HEALTH CARE.
HOW WOULD YOU LOWER THE COST OF
PRESCRIPTION DRUGS?
>> FIRST OF ALL, THE GOVERNMENT
SHOULD NEVER HAVE MADE THE DEAL
BIG PHARMA THEY COULDN'T
NEGOTIATE.
CORPORATIONS HAD THEIR WAYT  WI
US.
WHILE I AGREE -- I'M WITH
SENATOR BENNET AND OTHERS.
I'LL TELL YOU ONE THING.
IT'S NICE WE HAVE ALL THE PLANS
BUT IF YOU THINK WE ARE GOING TO
BEAT DONALD TRUMP BY HAVING
PLANS YOU'VE T GOT ANOTHER THIN
COMING.
HE DIDN'T WIN BYNO SAYING HE HAA
PLAN.
HE WON BY SAYING MAKE AMERICA
GREAT AGAIN.
WE HAVE TO GETET DEEPER THAN
SUPERFICIAL FIXES, AS IMPORTANT
AS THEY ARE.
EVEN TALKING ABOUT SUPERFICIAL
FIXES, LADIES AND GENTLEMEN, WE
DON'T HAVE A HEALTH CARE SYSTEM
IN THE UNITED STATES.
WE HAVE A SICKNESS CARE SYSTEM
WE WAITT FOR SOMEBODY TO GET
SICK, TALK ABOUT WHO WILL PAY
FOR THE TREATMENT AND HOW THEY
WILL BY E TREATED.
WE NEED TO TALK ABOUT WHY SO
MANY AMERICANS HAVE UNNECESSARY
CHRONICY  ILLNESSES, SO MANY MO
COMPARED TO OTHER COUNTRIES.
THAT GETS BACK TO NOT JUST THE
BIG PHARMA, NOT JUST HEALTH
INSURANCE COMPANIES.
IT HAS TO DO WITH CHEMICAL
POLICIES, ENVIRONMENTAL
POLICIES.
>> THAT'S YOUR TIME.
>> IT HAS TO DO WITH DRUG
POLICIES.
>> THANK YOU.
DO YOU WANT TO KEEP THE SYSTEM
WE HAVE IN PLACE WITH OBAMACARE
AND BUILD ON IT?
YOU MENTIONED IT.
IS THAT ENOUGH TO GET US TO
UNIVERSAL COVERAGE?
>> THAT WILL GET US THE QUICKEST
WAY THERE.
I HAD PROSTATE CANCER AND THAT'S
WHY I WAS LATE GETTING IN THE
RACE.
THE SAME WEEK MY KID HAD HER
APPENDIX OUT.
I FEEL STRONGLY FAMILIES SHOULD
HAVE THE CHOICE.
THAT'S WHAT THE AMERICAN PEOPLE
WANT.
I BELIEVE IT WILL GET US THERE
QUICKLY.
THERE ARE MILLIONS OF PEOPLE IN
AMERICA THAT DO NOT HAVE HEALTH
INSURANCE TODAY BECAUSE THEY ARE
TOO WEALTHY.
THEY MAKE TOO MUCH MONEY TO BE
ON MEDICAID.
THEY CAN'T AFFORD HEALTH
INSURANCE.
WHEN SENATOR SANDERS SAID THAT
CANADA IS SINGLE PAYER, THERE
ARE 35 MILLION P PEOPLE IN CANA.
THERE ARE 330 MILLION PEOPLE IN
THE UNITED STATES.
EASILY THE NUMBER OF PEOPLE ON A
PUBLIC OPTION.
THEY COULD BE 35 MILLION.
FOR THEM THAT WOULD BE MEDICARE
FOR ALL BUT FOR OTHERS WHO WANT
TO KEEPTO IT THEY SHOULD BE ABL
TO KEEP IT.
THAT WOULD BE  THE FASTEST WAY O
GET WHERE WE GO.
HE SAID OVER AND OVER AGAIN THIS
WILL BAN MAKING ILLEGAL ALL
INSURANCE EXCEPT COSMETIC.
EXCEPT INSURANCE FOR, I GUESS
THAT'S FOR PLASTIC SURGERY.
EVERYTHING ELSE IS BANNED UNDER
THE MEDICARE FOR ALL PROPOSAL.
>> I LET YOU GO LONGER, BUT
OBVIOUSLY SENATOR SANDERS GETS A
RESPONSE.
>> I HAVE A POINTNTE  HERE.
>> SENATOR SANDERS?
>> H YOU KNOW, MIKE, MEDICARE I
THE MOST POPULAR INSURANCE
PROGRAM IN THE COUNTRY.
PEOPLE DON'T LIKE THEIR PRIVATE
INSURANCE COMPANIES.
THEY LIKE THEIR DOCTORS AND
HOSPITALS.
PEOPLE GO TO ANY DOCTOR THEY
WANT, ANY HOSPITAL THEY WANT.
WE WILL LOWER THE COST OF HEALTH
CARE IN THE COUNTRY.
WE'LL STOP THE GREED OF THE
INSURANCE --
>> THE REALITY OF HOW THIS
AFFECTS REAL PEOPLE ISIS CAPTUR
IN A STORY MANY OF US HEARD AND
I WILL PARAPHRASE.
ANY NIGHT IN AMERICA THERE IS A
PARENT WHO SEES THEIR CHILD HAS
A TEMPERATURE THAT'S OUT OF
CONTROL, CALLS 911, WHAT SHOULD
I DO?
THEY SAY TAKE THE CHILD TO THE
EMERGENCY ROOM.
GET IN THEIR CAR AND
DRIVE AND THEY ARE SITTING IN
THE PARKING LOT OUTSIDE OF THE
EMERGENCY ROOMOM LOOKING AT THE
SLIDING GLASSER DOORS WHILE THE
HAVE THE HAND ON THE FOREHEAD OF
THEIR N CHILD, KNOWING THAT IF
THEY WALK THROUGHTH THE SLIDING
GLASS DOORS, EVEN THOUGH THEY
HAVE INSURANCE THEY WILL BE OUT
ASU $5,000 DEDUCTIBLE WHEN THEY
WALK THROUGH THE DOORS.
THAT'S WHAT INSURANCE COMPANIES
ARE DOING IN AMERICA TODAY.
>> WE'LL CONTINUE THIS
DISCUSSION.
[ SPEAKING SIMULTANEOUSLY ]
>> I WAS JUST IN THE EMERGENCY
ROOM.
WE FIGHT HEALTH INSURANCE
COMPANIES EVERY SINGLE WEEK.
>> THANK YOU.
>> WE STAND IN LINE AND PAY
EXPENSIVE PRESCRIPTION DRUGS.
WE HAVE TO HAVE A HEALTH CARE
GUARANTEE.
IF YOU'RE SICK, YOU ARE SEEN.
IN AMERICA YOU NEVER GO BROKE
BECAUSE OFO  IT.
>> OKAY.
A LOT OF YOU HAVE BEEN TALKING
TONIGHT ABOUT THE GOVERNMENT
HEALTH CARE PLANS YOUBE PROPOSE
INME ONE FORM OR ANOTHER.
THIS IS A SHOW OF HANDS
QUESTION.
HOLD THEM UP FOR A MOMENT SO
PEOPLEQU CAN SEE.
RAISE YOUR HAND IF YOUR
GOVERNMENT PLAN WOULD PROVIDE
COVERAGE FOR UNDOCUMENTED
IMMIGRANTS.
LET ME START WITH YOU, MAYOR
BUTTIGIEG.
WHY?
>> OUR COUNTRY IS HEALTHIER WHEN
EVERYBODY IS HEALTHIER.
REMEMBER, WE ARE TALKING ABOUT
SOMETHING PEOPLE ARE GIVEN A
CHANCE TO BUY INTO.
IN THE SAME WAY THERE ARE
UNDOCUMENTED IMMIGRANTS IN MY
COMMUNITY WHO PAY SALES TAX.
THEY PAY PROPERTY TAXES DIRECTLY
OR INDIRECTLY.
THIS IS NOT ABOUT A HANDOUT.
THIS IS AN INSURANCE PROGRAM.
WE DO OURSELVES NO FAVORS BY
HAVING 11 MILLION UNDOCUMENTED
PEOPLE IN OUR COUNTRY BE UNABLE
TO ACCESS HEALTH CARE.
THE REAL PROBLEM IS WE SHOULDN'T
HAVE 11 MILLION UNDOCUMENTED
PEOPLE WITH NO PATHWAY TO
CITIZENSHIP.
IT MAKES NO SENSE.
THE AMERICAN PEOPLE AGREE ON
WHAT TO DO.
THIS IS A CRAZY THING.
IF LEADERSHIP CONSISTS OF
FORMING A CONSENSUS AROUND A
DIVISIVE ISSUE, THIS WHITE HOUSE
HAS DIVIDED US AROUND A
CONSENSUS ISSUE.
THE AMERICAN PEOPLE WANT A
PATHWAY TO U CITIZENSHIP,
PROTECTION FOR DREAMERS.
WE NEED TO CLEAN UP THE LAWFUL
IMMIGRATION SYSTEM LIKE HOW MY
FATHER CAME TO THIS COUNTRY.
WE CAN DO
WHATEVER COMMON SENSE
MEASURES ARE NEEDED AT THE
BORDER.
WASHINGTON CAN'T DELIVER ON
SOMETHING THE AMERICAN PEOPLE
WANT.
WHAT DOES THAT TELL YOU ABOUT
THE SYSTEM WE ARE LIVING IN?
>> MAYOR, THANK YOU.
>> STRUCTURAL REFORM.
>> VICE PRESIDENT BIDEN, I
BELIEVE YOU  SAID YOUR HEALTH
CARE PLAN WOULD NOT COVER
UNDOCUMENTED IMMIGRANTS.
COULD YOU EXPLAIN YOUR POSITION?
>> I BEG YOUR PARDON?
>> I BELIEVE WITH A SHOW OF
HANDS YOUME CAN'T RAISE YOUR HA.
DID YOU?
>> I DID.
>> SORRY.
YOU SAID THEY WOULD BE COVERED
UNDER YOUR PLAN WHICH IS
DIFFERENT FROM OBAMACARE.
CAN YOUU EXPLAIN THAT?
>> YES.
YOU CANNOT LET PEOPLE WHO ARE
SICK NOS  MATTER WHERE THEY COM
FROM, NO MATTER THEIR STATUS GO
UNCOVERED.
YOU CAN'T DO THAT.
IT WILL BE TAKEN CARE OF,
PERIOD.
IT'S THE HUMANE THING TO DO.
HERE'S THE DEAL.
HE'S RIGHT ABOUT THREE THINGS.
NUMBER ONE, THEY, IN FACT,
CONTRIBUTE TO THE WELL-BEING OF
THE COUNTRY.
THEY ALSO, FOR EXAMPLE, INCREASE
THE LIFE SPAN OF SOCIAL
SECURITY.
THEY ARE PAYING THE SOCIAL
SECURITY TAX.
IT INCREASED THE LIFE SPAN.
THEY WOULD DO THE SAME THING IN
TERMS OF THE OVERALL COST OF
HEALTH CARE BY THEMM BEING
TREATED AND NOT WAIT.
THE OTHER THING IS WE CAN DEAL
WITH INSURANCE COMPANIES BY
PUTTING INSURANCE EXECUTIVES IN
JAIL FOR MISLEADING ADVERTISING,
WHATTER THIS DOING WITH OPIOIDS,
PAYING DOCTORS TOTO PRESCRIBE.
WE CAN MAKE SURE EVERYONE WHO IS
ON MEDICARE THAT THE GOVERNMENT
SHOULD BE ABLE TO NEGOTIATE THE
PRICE FOR WHATEVER THE DRUG
COSTS HEARE.
THEY CAN DO THIS BY MAKING SURE
THEY ARE IN A POSITION THAT WE,
IN T FACT, ALLOW PEOPLE.
>> TIME'S UP.
>> WE NEED TO TAKE A SHORT
BREAK.
WE HAVE A LOT MORE TO TALK TO
YOU ABOUT.
STICK WITH US.
WE'RE JUST GETTING STARTED.
WE'LL BE RIGHT BACK AFTER THIS.
L
STAY WITH US.
WE'RE JUST GETTING STARTED.
WE'LL BE RIGHT BACK FROM MIAMI
RIGHT AFTER THIS.
>>>
.
>>> WELCOME BACK FROM MIAMI.
JOSE WILL LEAD OFF THE
QUESTIONING THIS ROUND.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
SENATOR HARRIS, LAST MONTH MORE
THAN 130,000 MIGRANTS WERE
APPREHENDED AT THE SOUTHERN
BORDER.
MANY OF THEM ARE BEING DETAINED,
INCLUDING SMALL CHILDREN IN
PRIVATE DETENTION CENTERS IN
FLORIDA AND THROUGHOUT OUR
COUNTRY.
MOST OF THE CANDIDATES ON THIS
STAGE SAY THE CONDITIONS OF
THESE FACILITIES ARE ABHORRENT.
ON JANUARY 20, 2021, IF YOU ARE
PRESIDENT, WHAT SPECIFICALLY
WOULD YOU DO WITH THE THOUSANDS
OF PEOPLE WHO TRY TO REACH THE
UNITED STATES EVERY DAY AND WANT
A BETTER LIFE THROUGH ASYLUM?
>> IMMEDIATELY ON JANUARY 20 OF
2021, I WILL FIRST OF ALL -- WE
CANNOT FORGET OUR DACA
RECIPIENTS.
I'M GOING TO STOP THERE.
I WILL IMMEDIATELY BY EXECUTIVE
ACTION REINSTATE DACA STATUS AND
PROTECTION TO THOSE YOUNG
PEOPLE.
I WILL FURTHER EXTEND
PROTECTIONS FOR DEFERRAL OF
DEPORTATION FOR THEIR PARENTS
AND FOR VETERANS WHO WE HAVE SO
MANY UNDOCUMENTED AND WHO HAVE
SERVED OUR COUNTRY AND FOUGHT
FOR OUR DEMOCRACY.
I WILL ALSO IMMEDIATELY PUT IN
PLACE A MEANINGFUL PROS FOR
REVIEWING THE CASES FOR ASYLUM.
I WILL RELEASE CHILDREN FROM
CAGES, GET RID OF THE PRIVATE
DETENTION CENTERS AND I WILL
ENSURE THAT THIS MICROPHONE THAT
THE PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED
STATES HOLDS IN HER HAND IS USED
IN A WAY --
[ CHEERS ]
-- THAT IS ABOUT RESPECTING THE
VALUES OF OUR COUNTRY AND NOT
ABOUT LOCKING CHILDREN UP,
SEPARATING THEM FROM THEIR
PARENTS.
I HAVE TO SAY WE HAVE TO THINK
ABOUT THIS ISSUE IN TERMS OF
REAL PEOPLE.
A MOTHER WHO PAYS A COYOTE TO
TRANSPORT HER CHILD THROUGH
MEXICO FACING UNKNOWN PERIL TO
COME HERE, WHY WOULD THAT MOTHER
DO THAT?
I WILL TELL YOU.
BECAUSE TO REMAIN WHERE THEY ARE
IS WORSE.
WHAT DOES DONALD TRUMP DO?
HE SAYS GO BACK TO WHERE YOU
CAME FROM.
THAT'S NOT REFLECTIVE OF OUR
AMERICA AND OUR VALUES AND IT'S
GOT TO END.
>> GOVERNOR HICKENLOOPER, DAY
ONE, IF YOU ARE -- DAY ONE AT
THE WHITE HOUSE, HOW DO YOU --
>> DEAL WITH THESE CHILDREN?
>> LET ME GET TO YOU IN JUST A
SECOND.
>> I'M SORRY.
>> GOVERNOR.
DAY ONE?
THOUSANDS OF MEN, WOMEN AND
CHILDREN ASK FOR ASYLUM FOR A
BETTER LIFE.
WHAT DO YOU DO?
DAY ONE, HOUR ONE.
>> CERTAINLY THE IMAGES WE HAVE
SEEN THIS WEEK COMPOUND THE
EMOTIONAL IMPACT THE WORLD IS
JUDGING US BY.
IF YOU TOLD ME AT MY TIME IN MY
LIFE THIS COUNTRY WOULD SANCTION
FEDERAL AGENTS TO TAKE CHILDREN
FROM THE ARMS OF THEIR PARENTS,
PUT THEM IN CAGES, PUT THEM UP
FOR ADOPTION -- IN COLORADO WE
CALL THAT KIDNAPPING.
I WOULD HAVE TOLD YOU IT WAS
UNBELIEVABLE.
FIRST YOU HAVE TO RECOGNIZE THE
HUMANITARIAN CRISIS ON THE
BORDER FOR WHAT IT IS.
MAKE SURE THERE ARE SUFFICIENT
FACILITIES IN PLACE SO WOMEN AND
CHILDREN AREN'T SEPARATED FROM
THEIR FAMILIES.
THE CHILDREN ARE WITH THEIR
FAMILIES.
WE HAVE TO MAKE SURE I.C.E. IS
REFORMED AND THEY BEGIN LOOKING
AT THEIR JOB IN A HUMANITARIAN
WAY WHERE THEY ARE ADDRESSING
THE WHOLE NEEDS OF THE PEOPLE
THAT THEY ARE ENGAGED WITH ALONG
THE BORDER.
WE HAVE TO MAKE SURE ULTIMATELY
WE PROVIDE NOT JUST SHELTER BUT
FOOD, CLOTHING AND ACCESS TO
MEDICAL CARE.
MS. WILLIAM SON?
>> WHAT DONALD TRUMP HAS DONE TO
THE CHILDREN AND IT'S NOT JUST
COLORADO.
IT IS KIDNAPPING.
YOU'RE RIGHT.
IT IS EXTREMELY IMPORTANT TO
REALIZE THAT.
IF YOU TAKE A CHILD FROM THEIR
PARENT'S ARMS YOU ARE KIDNAPPING
THEM.
IF YOU TAKE A LOT OF CHILDREN
AND PUT THEM IN A DETAINMENT
CENTER THAT INFLICTS TRAUMA UPON
THEM.
THIS IS COLLECTIVE CHILD ABUSE.
BOTH OF THOSE THINGS ARE A
CRIME.
IF YOUR GOVERNMENT DOES IT THAT
DOESN'T MAKE IT LESS OF A CRIME.
THESE ARE STATE-SPONSORED
CRIMES.
WHAT PRESIDENT TRUMP HAS DONE IS
NOT ONLY ATTACKED THESE
CHILDREN, NOT ONLY DEMONIZED
IMMIGRANTS HE'S ATTACKING A
BASIC PRINCIPLE OF AMERICA'S
MORALE CORE.
WE OPEN OUR HEARTS TO THE
STRANGER.
THIS IS EXTREMELY IMPORTANT.
IT IS ALSO IMPORTANT FOR ALL OF
US AND I HAVE GREAT RESPECT FOR
EVERYONE ON THIS STAGE.
WE ARE GOING TO TALK ABOUT WHAT
TO DO ABOUT HEALTH CARE.
WHERE HAVE YOU BEEN, GUYS?
IT'S NOT JUST A MATTER OF A
PLAN.
I HAVEN'T HEARD ANYBODY ON THIS
AND HOW WE MIGHT HAVE
CONTRIBUTED TO SOMETHING --
>> SENATOR GILLIBRAND, WHAT
WOULD YOU DO WITH A PRESIDENT
WITH THIS REALITY?
>> THIS PRESIDENT HAS TORN APART
THE MORAL FABRIC OF WHO WE ARE.
WHEN HE STARTED SEPARATING
CHILDREN AT THE BORDER FROM
THEIR PARENTS.
THE FACT THAT SEVEN CHILDREN
HAVE DIED IN HIS CUSTODY, THE
FACT THAT DOZENS OF CHILDREN
HAVE BEEN SEPARATED FROM THEIR
PARENTS AND THEY HAVE NO PLAN TO
REUNITE THEM, I WOULD DO A FEW
THINGS.
FIRST I WOULD FIGHT FOR
COMPREHENSIVE IMMIGRATION REFORM
WITH A PATHWAY TO CITIZENSHIP.
SECOND, I WOULD REFORM HOW WE
TREAT SLIME SEEKERS AT THE
BORDER.
I WOULD HAVE A COMMUNITY-BASED
TREATMENT CENTER WHERE YOU ARE
DOING WITHIN THE COMMUNITIES
WHERE SLIME SEEKERS ARE GIVEN
LAWYERS, WHERE THERE IS REAL
IMMIGRATION JUDGES, NOT
EMPLOYEES OF THE ATTORNEY
GENERAL BUT APPOINTED FOR LIFE
AND HAVE A COMMUNITY-BASED
SYSTEM.
THE WORST THING PRESIDENT TRUMP
HAS DONE IS DIVERTED FUNDS AWAY
FROM CROSS-BORDER TERRORISM,
HUMAN TRAFFICKING, DRUG AND GUN
TRAFFICKING AND HE'S GIVEN THE
MONEY TO THE FOR PROFIT PRISONS.
I WOULD NOT SPEND MONEY ON FOR
PROFIT PRISONS TO LOCK UP
CHILDREN AND ASYLUM SEEKERS.
>> WE HAD A SPIRITED DEBATE ON
THE TOPIC OF DECRIMINALIZATION
OF THE BORDER.
RAISE YOUR HAND IF YOU THINK IT
SHOULD BE A CIVIL OFFENSE RATHER
THAN A CRIME TO CROSS A BORDER
WITHOUT DOCUMENTATION?
KEEP YOUR HANDS UP SO WE CAN SEE
THEM.
>> THAT'S NOT A THEORETICAL
EXERCISE.
CRIMINALZATION IS THE BASIS FOR
FAMILY SEPARATION.
YOU DO AWAY WITH THAT IT'S NO
LONGER POSSIBLE.
OF COURSE IT WOULDN'T BE
POSSIBLE IN MY PRESIDENCY
BECAUSE IT IS DEAD WRONG.
THE REPUBLICAN PARTY LIKES TO
CLOAK ITSELF IN THE LANGUAGE OF
RELIGION.
OUR PARTY DOESN'T TALK ABOUT
THAT AS MUCH.
WE ARE COMMITTED TO THE
SEPARATION OF CHURCH AND STATE
AND WE STAND FOR PEOPLE OF EVERY
RELIGION AND NO RELIGION.
WE SHOULD CALL OUT HYPOCRISY
WHEN WE SEE IT.
FOR A PARTY THAT ASSOCIATES
ITSELF WITH CHRISTIANITY, TO SAY
THAT IT IS OKAY TO SUGGEST THAT
GOD WOULD SMILE ON THE DIVISION
OF FAMILIES AT THE HANDS OF
FEDERAL AGENTS, THAT GOD WOULD
CONDONE PUTTING CHILDREN IN
CAGES HAS LOST ALL CLAIM TO EVER
USE RELIGIOUS LANGUAGE AGAIN.
>> VICE PRESIDENT -- MR. VICE
PRESIDENT, I DON'T KNOW IF YOU
RAISED YOUR HAND OR WERE ASKING
TO SPEAK.
WOULD YOU DECRIMINALIZE CROSSING
THE BORDER WITHOUT DOCUMENTS?
>> THE FIRST THING I WOULD DO IS
UNITE FAMILIES.
I WOULD SURGE IMMEDIATELY
MILLIONS OF DOLLARS IN HELP TO
THE REGION IMMEDIATELY.
LOOK, I TALK ABOUT FOREIGN
POLICY.
I'M THE GUY THAT GOT A
BIPARTISAN AGREEMENT AT THE END
OF THE CAMPAIGN, OUR TERM TO
SPEND $740 MILLION TO DEAL WITH
THE PROBLEM.
THAT WAS TO GO TO THE ROOT
PROBLEM OF WHY PEOPLE ARE
LEAVING IN THE FIRST PLACE.
WE SAW A NET DECREASE IN THEM
COMING.
THE CRISIS WAS ABATED.
THIS PRESIDENT DISCONTINUED
THAT.
I DID IT.
SECOND THING WE HAVE TO DO, THE
LAW NOW REQUIRES THE REUNITING
OF FAMILIES.
WE WOULD REUNITE THOSE FAMILIES,
PERIOD.
IF NOT WE'D PUT CHILDREN IN A
CIRCUMSTANCE WHERE THEY WERE
SAFE UNTIL WE COULD FIND THEIR
PARENTS.
LASTLY, THE IDEA THAT THE
JUSTICE DEPARTMENT IS SAYING
CHILDREN IN CAGES DO NOT NEED A
BED, DO NOT NEED A BLANKET, DO
NOT NEED A TOOTHBRUSH IS
OUTRAGEOUS.
>> THE OBAMA/BIDEN
ADMINISTRATION DEPORTED MORE
THAN 3 MILLION AMERICANS.
MY QUESTION TO YOU IS IF AN
INDIVIDUAL IS LIVING IN THE
UNITED STATES OF AMERICA WITHOUT
DOCUMENTS AND THAT IS HIS ONLY
OFFENSE, SHOULD THAT PERSON BE
DEPORTED?
>> NO.
>> DEPENDING IF THEY COMMITTED A
MAJOR CRIME.
THEY SHOULD BE DEPORTED.
PRESIDENT OBAMA, I THINK, DID A
HECK OF A JOB.
COMPARE HIM TO WHAT THIS GUY IS
DOING IS ABSOLUTELY IMMORAL.
THE FACT IS THAT, LOOK, WE
SHOULD NOT BE LOCKING PEOPLE UP.
WE SHOULD MAKE SURE WE CHANGE
THE CIRCUMSTANCE AS WE DID, WHY
THEY WOULD LEAVE IN THE FIRST
PLACE.
THOSE WHO COME SEEKING ASYLUM,
WE SHOULD IMMEDIATELY HAVE THE
CAPACITY TO ABSORB THEM, KEEP
THEM SAFE UNTIL THEY COULD BE
HEARD.
>> 15 SECONDS, IF YOU WOULD, TO
ANSWER.
SHOULD SOMEONE WHO IS HERE
WITHOUT DOCUMENTS AND THAT'S HIS
ONLY OFFENSE, SHOULD THAT PERSON
BE DEPORTED?
>> THAT PERSON SHOULD NOT BE THE
FOCUS OF DEPORTATION.
WE SHOULD FUNDAMENTALLY CHANGE
THE WAY WE DEAL WITH THINGS.
>> SENATOR --
>> I THINK IT'S IMPORTANT --
>> I AGREE WITH WHAT KAMALA
HARRIS SAID.
ON DAY ONE WE TAKE OUT THE
EXECUTIVE ORDER PEN AND RESCIND
EVERY DAMN THING ON THE ISSUE
THAT TRUMP HAS DONE.
>> ABSOLUTELY.
>> PICKING UP ON A POINT JOE
MADE, WE HAVE TO LOOK AT THE
ROOT CAUSES.
YOU HAVE A SITUATION WHERE
HONDURAS, AMONG OTHER THINGS IS
A -- MASSIVE CORRUPTION.
TELLING FAMILIES IF A
10-YEAR-OLD DOESN'T JOIN THE
GANG THEIR FAMILY WILL BE
KILLED.
WHAT WE HAVE TO DO ON DAY ONE IS
INVITE THE PRESIDENT AND THE
LEADERSHIP OF CENTRAL AMERICA
AND MEXICO TOGETHER.
THIS IS A HEMISPHERE PROBLEM.
>> THANK YOU.
>> WHAT DO YOU DO?
>> DAY ONE.
IF SOMEONE IS HERE WITHOUT
DOCUMENTS AND THAT'S THEIR ONLY
OFFENSE, IS THAT PERSON TO BE
DEPORTED?
>> NO.
THAT PERSON CAN BE A PART OF
THIS GREAT AMERICAN EXPERIENCE.
MY CONGRESSIONAL DISTRICT IS ONE
OF THE MOST DIVERSE IN AMERICA.
WE SEE THE BENEFITS WHEN PEOPLE
CONTRIBUTE AND BECOME PART OF
THE COMMUNITY AND THEY ARE NOT
IN THE SHADOW ECONOMY.
DAY ONE FOR ME, FAMILIES ARE
REUNITED.
THIS PRESIDENT FOR IMMIGRANTS,
THERE IS NOTHING HE WILL NOT DO
TO SEPARATE A FAMILY, CAGE A
CHILD OR ERASE THEIR EXISTENCE
BY WEAPONIZING THE CENSUS.
THERE IS NOTHING WE CANNOT DO IN
THE COURTS AND THAT I WILL NOT
DO AS PRESIDENT TO REVERSE THAT
AND TO MAKE SURE FAMILIES ALWAYS
BELONG TOGETHER.
>> SENATOR HARRIS.
>> THANK YOU.
ABSOLUTELY NOT, THEY SHOULD NOT
BE DEPORTED.
THIS WAS ONE OF THE VERY FEW
ISSUES WITH WHICH I DISAGREED
WITH THE ADMINISTRATION WITH
WHOM I HAVE HAD A GREAT
RELATIONSHIP AND A GREAT DEAL OF
RESPECT.
I WAS ATTORNEY GENERAL OF
CALIFORNIA.
I LED THE SECOND LARGEST
DEPARTMENT OF JUSTICE IN THE
UNITED STATES.
SECOND ONLY TO THE UNITED STATES
DEPARTMENT OF JUSTICE IN A STATE
OF 40 MILLION PEOPLE.
ON THIS ISSUE, I DISAGREED WITH
MY PRESIDENT.
THE POLICY WAS TO ALLOW
DEPORTATION OF PEOPLE WHO, BY
I.C.E.'S OWN DEFINITION WERE
NONCRIMINALS.
AS ATTORNEY GENERAL AND THE
CHIEF LAW OFFICER OF THE STATE
OF CALIFORNIA, I ISSUED A
DIRECTIVE TO THE SHERIFF OF THE
STATE THEY DIDN'T HAVE TO COMPLY
WITH DETAINERS AND TO MAKE
DECISIONS BASED ON THE PUBLIC
SAFETY OF THE COMMUNITY.
WHAT I SAW, AND I WAS TRACKING
IT EVERY DAY.
I WAS TRACKING IT AND SAW THAT
PARENTS, PEOPLE WHO HAD NOT
COMMITTED A CRIME WERE BEING
DEPORTED.
I HAVE TO ADD A POINT HERE.
THE PROBLEM WITH THIS KIND OF
POLICY, AND I KNOW IT AS A
PROSECUTOR.
>> SENATOR.
>> I WANT A RAPE VICTIM TO BE
ABLE TO RUN IN THE MIDDLE OF THE
STREET AND WAVE DOWN A POLICE
OFFICER AND REPORT THE CRIME
AGAINST HER.
I WANT ANYBODY --
>> SENATOR.
>> -- WHO HAS BEEN THE VICTIM OF
A CRIME TO DO THAT AND NOT BE
AFRAID THAT IF THEY DO THAT THEY
WILL BE DEPORTED BECAUSE THE
ACCUSER WILL TELL THEM IT IS
THEY WHO ARE THE CRIMINAL.
IT IS WRONG.
>> WE'RE GOING TO TURN TO THE
ISSUE OF TRADE NOW, IF WE CAN.
LAST NIGHT WE ASKED THE
CANDIDATES ON STAGE TO NAME THE
GREATEST GEOPOLITICAL THREAT IN
THE U.S.
FOUR MENTIONED CHINA.
U.S. BUSINESSES SAY CHINA STEALS
OUR INTELLECTUAL PROPERTY AND
KEEP THE COST OF GOODS
ARTIFICIALLY LOW.
SENATOR BENNET, HOW WOULD YOU
STAND UP TO CHINA?
>> FIRST OF ALL, THE BIGGEST
THREAT TO OUR NATIONAL SECURITY
IS RUSSIA, NOT CHINA.
BECAUSE OF WHAT THEY HAVE DONE
WITH THE ELECTION.
IN CHINA, I THINK THE PRESIDENT
HAS BEEN RIGHT TO PUSH BACK ON
CHINA BUT HAS DONE IT IN
COMPLETELY THE WRONG WAY.
WE SHOULD MOBILIZE THE ENTIRE
REST OF THE WORLD WHO ALL HAVE
SHARED SBRENS IN PUSHING BACK ON
TRADE POLICIES.
I WOULD LIKE TO ANSWER THE OTHER
QUESTION BEFORE AS WELL.
>> YOU HAVE THE TIME.
>> WHEN I SEE THE KIDS AT THE
BORDER, I SEE MY MOM BECAUSE I
KNOW SHE SEES HERSELF.
SHE WAS SEPARATED FROM HER
PARENTS FOR YEARS DURING THE
HOLOCAUST IN POLAND.
FOR DONALD TRUMP TO DO WHAT HE'S
DOING, I SAY IT AS SOMEBODY WHO
WROTE THE IMMIGRATION BILL THAT
CREATED A PATHWAY TO CITIZENSHIP
FOR 11 MILLION PEOPLE IN THIS
COUNTRY THAT HAD THE MOST
PROGRESSIVE DREAM ACT THAT'S
EVER BEEN CONCEIVED, MUCH LESS
PASSED.
68 VOTES IN THE SENATE.
IT HAD 46 BILLION DOLLARS OF
BORDER SECURITY.
IT WAS SOPHISTICATED 21st
CENTURY BORDER SECURITY, NOT A
MEDIEVAL WALL.
>> SENATOR, TIME HAS EXPIRED.
>> THE BORDER OF THE UNITED
STATES INTO A SYMBOL OF
HOSTILITY THAT THE WHOLE WORLD
IS LOOKING AT WHEN WHAT WE
SHOULD BE --
>> SENATOR, THANK YOU.
>> -- IS THE STATUE OF LIBERTY
WHICH BROUGHT MY PARENTS TO THIS
COUNTRY TO BEGIN WITH.
WE NEED TO MAKE A CHANGE.
>> MR. YANG, ON THE ISSUE OF
CHINA YOU HAVE EXPRESSED
CONCERNS ABOUT TECHNOLOGY AND
TAKING JOBS.
ARE YOU WORRIED ABOUT CHINA?
IF SO, HOW WOULD YOU STAND UP
AGAINST IT?
>> I WANT TO AGREE THAT I THINK
RUSSIA IS OUR GREATEST THREAT.
THEY HAVE BEEN HACKING OUR
DEMOCRACY SUCCESSFULLY, LAUGHING
ABOUT IT FOR THE LAST COUPLE OF
YEARS.
WE SHOULD FOCUS ON THAT BEFORE
WE START LOOKING AT OTHERS.
THE TARIFFS AND THE TRADE WAR
ARE PUNISHING BUSINESSES AND
PRODUCERS AND WORKERS ON BOTH
SIDES.
I MET WITH A FARMER IN IOWA WHO
SPENT SIX YEARS BUILDING UP A
RELATIONSHIP IN CHINA THAT'S
DISAPPEARED AND GONE FOREVER.
THE BENEFICIARIES HAVEN'T BEEN
AMERICAN WORKERS OR PEOPLE IN
SOUTHEAST ASIA AND OTHER
PRODUCERS THAT STEPPED INTO THE
VOID.
WE NEED TO CRACK DOWN ON CHINESE
MALFEASANCE IN THE TRADE
RELATIONSHIP AND THE TARIFFS AND
THE TRADE WAR ARE THE WRONG WAY
TO GO.
>> MAYOR BUTTIGIEG, HOW WOULD
YOU STAND UP AGAINST CHINA?
>> WE HAVE TO RECOGNIZE THE
CHINA CHALLENGE IS A SERIOUS
ONE.
THIS ISN'T ONE TO DISMISS OR
WAVE AWAY.
IF YOU LOOK AT WHAT CHINA IS
DOING, THEY ARE USING TECHNOLOGY
FOR THE PERFECTION OF
DICTATORSHIP.
THEIR FUNDAMENTAL ECONOMIC MODEL
WON'T CHANGE BECAUSE OF TARIFFS.
FOLKS WHO AREN'T IN THE SHADOW
OF A FACTORY OR NEAR A SOY FIELD
WHERE I LIVE.
MANUFACTURERS AND SOY FARMERS
ARE HURTING.
AMERICANS PAY $800 MORE A YEAR
BECAUSE OF TARIFFS.
CHINA IS INVESTING SO THEY COULD
SOON RUN CIRCLES AROUND US IN
ARTIFICIAL INTELLIGENCE.
THIS PRESIDENT IS FIXATED ON THE
CHINA RELATIONSHIP AS IF ALL
THAT MATTERED WAS THE EXPORT
BALANCE ON DISHWASHERS.
WE HAVE A BIGGER ISSUE ON OUR
HANDS.
AT THE MOMENT WHEN THEIR
AUTHORITARIAN MODEL IS AN
ALTERNATIVE TO OURS BECAUSE OURS
IS CHAOS COMPARED TO THEIRS
BECAUSE OF OUR INTERNAL DIVISION
THE BIG THING WE HAVE TO DO IS
INVEST IN OUR OWN DOMESTIC
COMPETITIVENESS.
IF WE --
>> THANK YOU.
>> IN OUR OWN INFRASTRUCTURE,
EDUCATION WE WILL NEVER BE ABLE
TO COMPETE.
IF WE WANT TO BE A DEMOCRATIC
ALTERNATIVE WE ACTUALLY HAVE TO
DEMONSTRATE WE CARE ABOUT
DEMOCRATIC VALUES AT HOME AND
AROUND THE WORLD.
>> THANK YOU.
>> WE'RE GOING TO TAKE A QUICK
BREAK.
LET ME COME BACK WITH CHUCK TODD
AND RACHEL MADDOW.
MUCH MORE WITH THE CANDIDATES
AHEAD.
CHUCK TODD, RACHEL MADDOW WILL
BE HERE, MUCH MORE WITH OUR
CANDIDATES STRAIGHT AHEAD.
3 F2
(MU
>>> WELCOME BACK TO THE
DEMOCRATIC PRESIDENTIAL DEBATES
IN MIAMI.
>> AS WE CONTINUE THE
QUESTIONING WE WANT TO BRING IN
MORE MEMBERS OF THE TEAM.
>> LET'S GO TO CHUCK TODD AND
RACHEL MADDOW.
[ CHEERS AND APPLAUSE ]
>> RACHEL, I HAD A DREAM THAT WE
HAVE DONE THIS BEFORE.
>> NO.
THIS IS DEFINITELY THE FIRST
TIME.
>> DEFINITELY.
THANK YOU, LESTER, SAVANNAH AND
JOSE.
LET'S RECAP THE RULES.
20 CANDIDATES QUALIFIED FOR THE
FIRST DEBATE.
WE HAVE HEARD FROM TEN OF THEM
LAST NIGHT.
WE HEAR FROM TEN MORE TONIGHT.
BREAKDOWN FOR EACH NIGHT WAS
SELECTED AT RANDOM.
CANDIDATES HAVE 60 SECONDS TO
ANSWER DIRECT QUESTIONS, 30 FOR
FOLLOW UPS IF NECESSARY.
>> BECAUSE OF THE LARGE FIELD,
NOT EVERY PERSON CAN BE ABLE TO
COMMENT ON EVERYTHING, BUT THE
LESS AUDIENCE REACTION THERE IS,
THE MORE TIME THEY ALL GET.
>> OVER THE COURSE OF THE NEXT
HOUR WE'LL HEAR FROM ALL OF
THESE CANDIDATES, BUT WE ARE
GOING TO BEGIN THIS HOUR WITH
MAYOR BUTTIGIEG.
IN THE LAST FIVE YEARS CIVIL
RIGHTS ACTIVISTS HAVE LED A
NATIONAL DEBATE OVER RACE AND
THE CRIMINAL JUSTICE SYSTEM.
YOUR COMMUNITY OF SOUTH BEND,
INDIANA, HAS BEEN IN
INDIANA, HAS BEEN REASONSLY IN
AN UPROAR OFFER AN
OFFICER-INVOLVED SHOOTING.
THE POLICE IN SOUTH DAKOTA BEND
IS NOW 6% BLACK IN A CITY THAT'S
26% BLACK.
WHY HAS THAT NOT IMPROVED OVER
YOUR TWO TERMS AS MAYOR?
>> BECAUSE I COULDN'T GET IT
DONE.
MY COMMUNITY IS IN AND WISH
RIGHT NOW BECAUSE OF AN
OFFICER-INVOLVED SHOOTING, A
BLACK MAN, ERIC LOGAN, KILLED BY
A WHITE OFFICER.
I'M NOT ALLOWED TO TAKE SIDES
UNTIL THE INVESTIGATION COMES
BACK.
THE OFFICER SAYS HE WAS ATTACKED
AND HE DIDN'T HAVE HIS BODY
CAMERA ON.
WE'RE HURTING.
I CAN WALK YOU THROUGH ALL THE
THINGS WE HAVE DONE AS A
COMMUNITY, ALL OF THE STEPS THAT
WE'VE TOOK FROM BIAS TRAINING TO
DE-ESCALATION BUT IT DIDN'T SAVE
THE LIFE OF ERIC LOGAN, AND WHEN
I LOOK INTO HIS MOTHER'S EYES, I
HAVE TO FACE THE FACT AND
NOTHING THAT I SAY WILL BRING
HIM BACK.
THIS IS AN ISSUE THAT IS FACING
OUR COMMUNITY AND SO MANY
COMMUNITIES AROUND THE COUNTRY,
AND UNTIL WE MOVE POLITICIAN OUT
FROM THE SHADOW OF SYSTEMIC
RACISM, WHATEVER THIS PARTICULAR
INCIDENT TEACHES US, WE'LL LEFT
WITH A BIGGER PROBLEM OF THE
FACT THAT THERE'S A WALL OF
MISTRUST, PUT UP ONE RACIST ACT
AT A TIME, NOT JUST WHAT HAS
HAPPENED IN THE PAST BUT WHAT'S
HAPPENING AROUND THE COUNTRY IN
THE PRESENT.
IT'S THREATENED THE WELL-BEING
OF EVERY COMMUNITY AND I'M
DETERMINE TO BRING ABOUT A DAY
WHEN A WHITE PERSON DRIVING A
VEHICLE AND A BLACK PERSON
DRIVING A VEHICLE, WHEN THEY SEE
A POLICE OFFICER FEEL THE EXACT
SAME THING, A FEELING OF SAFETY
NOT FEAR.
>> THANK YOU, MR. MAYOR.
>> IF I COULD ASK YOU ONE
QUESTION.
>> I'LL GIVE YOU 30 SECONDS.
>> THE QUESTION THAT THEY ARE
ASKING IN SOUTH BEND AND ACROSS
THE COUNTRY IS WHY HAS IT TAKEN
SO LONG?
WE HAD A SHOOTING WHEN I FIRST
BECAME MAYOR, STEP YEARS BEFORE
FERGUSON AND THE COMMUNITY GAME
TOGETHER AND WE CREATED AN
OVERSIGHT COMMISSION AND
DIVERSEIFIED POLICE FORCE IN TWO
YEARS AND DID DE-ESCALATION
TRAINING.
I THINK THE REAL QUESTION THAT
AMERICA IS ASKING IS WHY FIVE
YEARS AFTER FERGUSON EVERY CITY
DOESN'T HAVE THIS LEVEL OF
POLICE ACCOUNTABILITY?
>> GOVERNOR HICKENLOOPER.
>> I'VE GOT TO RESPOND TO THAT.
>> LOOK, WE'VE TAKEN THAT MANY
STEPS TOWARDS POLICE
ACCOUNTABILITY THAT THE SOP JUST
SAID THERE'S TOO MUCH
ACCOUNTABILITY AND WE'RE
DEFINITELY NOT THERE YET AND I
ACCEPT RESPONSIBILITY.
SO UNDER INDIANA LAW THIS WILL
BE INVESTIGATED, AND THERE WILL
BE ACCOUNTABILITY INVOLVED.
>> IF YOU'RE THE MAYOR FIRE THE
CHIEF.
IF THAT'S THE POLICY WHEN SUN
DIES.
>> ALL OF THESE ISSUES ARE
EXTREMELY IMPORTANT.
THEY ARE SYMPTOMS AND THE
UNDERLYING CAUSE HAS TO DO WITH
DEEP, DEEP GROUNDS OF RACIAL
INJUSTICE AND IN OUR CRIMINAL
JUSTICE SYSTEM AND ECONOMIC
SYSTEM AND THE DEMOCRATIC PARTY
SHOULD ON THE SIDE OF
REPARATIONS FOR SLAVERY FOR THIS
VERY REASON.
I DO NOT BELIEVE -- I DO NOT
BELIEVE THAT THE AVERAGE
AMERICAN IS A RACIST, BUT
AVERAGE AMERICAN IS WILLFULLY
UNDEREDUCATED ABOUT THE HISTORY
RACE IN THE UNITED STATES.
>> I'M GOING -- WE'RE GOING TO
GET TO YOU.
>> I WOULD LIKE TO SPEAK ON THE
ISSUE OF RATS.
>> SENATOR HAITIAN AND WHAT I
WOULD SAY -- WE'LL GIVE YOU 30
SECONDS AND WE'RE GOING TO COME
BACK TO YOU ON THIS IN A MOMENT.
GO FOR 30 SECONDS.
>> OKAY.
SO ON THE ISSUE OF RACE I
COULDN'T AGREE MORE THAT THIS IS
AN ISSUE THAT IS STILL NOT BEING
TALKED ABOUT TRUTHFULLY AND
HONESTLY.
THERE'S NOT A BLACK MAN I KNOW
BEY HAD A RELATIVE, A FRIEND OR
CO-WALKER WHO HAS NOT BEEN THE
SUBJECT OF SOME SORT OF
PROFILING OR DISCRIMINATION.
GROWING UP MY SISTER AND I HAD
TO DEAL WITH THE NEIGHBOR WHO
TELL US SHE COULDN'T PLAY WITH
US BECAUSE WE WERE BLACK AND I
WOULD SAY ALSO THAT EVEN IN THIS
CAMPAIGN WE'VE ALSO HEARD, AND
I'M GOING TO NOW DIRECT THIS AT
VICE PRESIDENT BIDEN, I DO NOT
BELIEVE YOU HAD A RACIST, AND I
AGREE WITH YOU WHEN YOU COMMIT
YOURSELF TO THE IMPORTANCE OF
FINDING COMMON GROUND, BUT I
ALSO BELIEVE, AND IT'S PERSONAL,
AND IT WAS ACTUALLY VERY
HURTFUL, TO HEAR YOU TALK ABOUT
THE REPUTATIONS OF TWO UNITED
STATES SENATORS WHO BUILT THEIR
REPUTATION AND CAREER ON
SEGREGATION OF RACE IN THIS
COUNTRY, AND IT WAS NOT ONLY
THAT BUT YOU ALSO WORKED WITH
THEM TO OPPOSE BUSING, AND, YOU
KNOW, THERE WAS A LITTLE GIRL IN
CALIFORNIA WHO WAS PART OF THE
SECOND CLASS TO INTEGRATE INTO
PUBLIC SCHOOLS AND SHE WAS
BUSSED TO SCHOOL EVERY DAY, AND
THAT LITTLE GIRL WAS ME SO I
WILL TELL YOU THAT ON THIS
SUBJECT IT CANNOT BE AN
INTELLECTUAL DEBATE AMONG
DEMOCRATS.
WE HAVE TO TAKE IT SERIOUSLY.
WE HAVE TO ACT SWIFTLY.
AS ATTORNEY GENERAL OF
CALIFORNIA I WAS VERY PROUD TO
PUT IN PLACE A REQUIREMENT THAT
ALL MY SPECIALATES WOULD WEAR
BODY CAMERAS AND KEEP THOSE
CAMERAS ON.
>> SENATOR HARRIS, THANK YOU.
>> VICE PRESIDENT BIDEN, YOU
HAVE BEEN INVOKED.
WE'RE GOING TO GIVE YOU A CHANCE
TO RESPOND.
VICE PRESIDENT BIDEN.
>> THAT'S THE A
MISCHARACTERIZATION OF POSITION
ACROSS THE BOARD.
I DO NOT PARADES RACIST, THAT'S
NOT NUMBER NUMBER ONE.
NUMBER TWO, IF WE WANT TO HAVE
THIS CAMPAIGN LITIGATED ON WHO
SUPPORTS CIVIL RIGHTS I'M HAPPY
TO DO THAT.
I WAS A PUBLIC DEFENDER.
I DIDN'T BECOME A PROSECUTOR.
I CAME OUT AND LEFT A GOOD LAW
FIRM TO BECOME A PUBLIC
DEFENDER.
WHEN IN FACT -- WHEN IN FACT --
WHEN IN FACT MY CITY WAS
ENSLAVED BECAUSE OF THE
ASSASSINATION OF MARTIN LUTHER
KING, NUMBER UP WITH.
NUMBER TWO, AS THE VICE
PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED STATES I
WORKED WITH A MAN WHO IN FACT WE
WORKED VERY HARD TO SEE TO IT,
THAT WE DEALT WITH THESE ISSUES
IN A MAJOR MAJOR WAY.
THE FACT IS THAT IN TERMS OF
BHUSING, THE BUSING -- YOU WOULD
HAVE BEEN ABLE TO GO TO SCHOOL
THE SAME EXACT WAY BECAUSE IT
WAS A LOCAL DECISION MADE BY
YOUR CITY COUNCIL.
THAT'S FINE.
THAT'S ONE OF THE THINGS ARGUED
FOR THAT WE SHOULD BE BREAKING
DOWN THESE LINES, SO THE BOTTOM
LINE HERE IS, LOOK, EVERYTHING
I'VE COMMON MY CAREER, I RAN
BECAUSE OF CIVIL RIGHTS, I
CONTINUE TO THINK THAT WE HAVE
TO MAKE FUNDAMENTAL CHANGES IN
CIVIL RIGHTS AND THOSE CIVIL
RIGHTS INCLUDE NOT ONLY
AFRICAN-AMERICANS BUT LBGTQ
COMMUNITY.
>> VICE PRESIDENT BIDEN, DO YOU
AGREE TODAY -- DO YOU AGREE
TODAY THAT YOU WERE WRONG TO
OPPOSE BUSING IN AMERICA THEN?
>> NO.
>> DO YOU AGREE?
>> I DID NOT OPPOSE BUSSING IN
AMERICA.
WHAT I OPPOSED WAS BUGS ORDERED
BY THE DEPARTMENT OF EDUCATION.
THAT'S WHAT I OPPOSED.
I DID NOT OPPOSE --
>> IT'S A FAIL YOU'RE STATES
TO -- I WAS PART OF THE SECOND
CLASS TO INTEGRATE BERKELEY,
CALIFORNIA PUBLIC SCHOOLS ALMOST
TWO DECADES AFTER BROWN V. BOARD
OF EDUCATION.
>> BECAUSE YOUR CITY COUNCIL
MADE THAT DECISION.
>> SO THAT'S WHY THE FEDERAL
GOVERNMENT MUST STEP IN.
THAT'S WHY WE HAVE THE VOTING
RIGHTS ACT AND THE CIVIL RIGHTS
ACT.
THAT'S WHY WE NEED TO PASS THE
EQUALITY ACT AND THAT'S WHY WE
NEED TO PASS THE ERA BECAUSE
THERE ARE MOMENTS IN HISTORY IN
WHICH STATES FAIL TO PRESERVE
THE CIVIL RIGHTS OF ALL PEOPLE.
>> I'VE SPOTTED THE E.R.A. FROM
THE VERY BEGINNING.
>> 0 SECONDS.
>> I WANT TO BRING OTHER PEOPLE
INTO THIS.
>> I SUPPORTED THE E.R.A. FROM
THE VERY BEGINNING.
I'M THE GUY WHO EXTENDED THE
VOTING RIGHTS ACT FOR 25 YEARS.
WE GOT TO THE PLACE WHERE WE GOT
98 OUT OF 92 VOTES IN THE UNITED
STATES SENATE DOING IT.
I'VE ALSO ARGUED VERY STRONGLY
THAT WE IN FACT DEAL WITH THE
NOTION OF DENYING PEOPLE ACCESS
TO THE BALLOT BOX.
I AGREED THAT EVERYBODY WANTS --
ANYWAY.
MY TIME IS UP, I'M SORRY.
>> THANK YOU, VICE PRESIDENT.
>> ALL OF THESE THINGS --
>> SENATOR SANDERS, I'M GOING TO
GO.
YOU SAID ON THE DAY YOU LAUNCHED
YOUR CAMPAIGN THAT VOTERS SHOULD
FOCUS ON WHAT PEOPLE STAND FOR,
NOT A CANDIDATE'S RACE OR AGE OR
SEXUAL ORIENTATION.
MANY DEMOCRATS ARE VERY EXCITED
BY THE DIVERSITY OF THIS FIELD,
ON THIS STAGE AND ON LAST
NIGHT'S STAGE AND THE
PROSPECTIVE THAT DIVERSITY
BRINGS TO THE CONTEST AND TO
THESE ISSUES.
ARE YOU TELLING DEMOCRATIC
VOTERS THAT DIVERSITY SHOULDN'T
MATTER WHEN THEY MAKE THIS
DECISION?
>> NO, ABSOLUTELY NOT.
UNLIKE THE REPUBLICAN PARTY, WE
ENCOURAGE DIVERSITY.
WE BELIEVE IN DIVERSITY.
THAT'S WHAT AMERICA IS ABOUT,
BUT IN ADDITION TO THE
DIVERSITY.
IN TERMS OF HAVING MORE WOMEN,
MORE PEOPLE FROM THE LBGT
COMMUNITY, WE ALSO HAVE TO DO
SOMETHING ELSE, AND THAT IS WE
HAVE TO ASK OURSELVES A SIMPLE
QUESTION, AND THAT'S HOW COME
TODAY THE WORKER IN THE MIDDLE
OF OUR ECONOMY IS MAKING NO MORE
MONEY THAN HE OR SHE MADE 45
YEARS AGO AND THAT IN THE LAST
30 YEARS THE TOP 1% HAS SEEN A
$21 TRILLION INCREASE IN THEIR
WEALTH.
WE NEED A PARTY THAT'S DIVERSE
AND WE NEED A PARTY THAT HAS THE
GUTS TO STAND UP TO THE POWERFUL
SPECIAL INTERESTS WHO HAVE SO
MUCH POWER OVER THE ECONOMIC AND
POLITICAL LIFE OF THIS COUNTRY.
>> SENATOR GILL BRAND, I WANT TO
GIVE YOU 30 SECONDS.
>> FIRST OFF, WHERE BERNIE LEFT
OFF.
YOU'VE HEARD A LOT OF GOOD IDEAS
ON THIS STAGE TONIGHT AND A LOT
OF PLANS, BUT THE TRUTH IS THE
UNTIL YOU GO TO THE ROOT OF THE
CORRUPTION, THE MONEY IN
POLITICS, THE FACT THAT
WASHINGTON IS RUN BY THE SPECIAL
INTERESTS, YOU ARE NEVER GOING
TO SOLVE ANY OF THESE PROBLEMS.
I HAVE THE MOST COMPREHENSIVE
APPROACH THAT EXPERTS BELIEVE IS
THE MOST TRANSFORMATIVE PLAN TO
ACTUALLY TAKE ON POLITICAL
CORRUPTION, TO GET MONEY OUT OF
POLITICS TO PUBLICLY FUNDED
ELECTIONS AND HAVE CLEAN
ELECTIONS.
IF WE DO THAT AND GET MONEY OUT
OF HEALTHCARE, WE CAN HAVE
HEALTHCARE AND TAKE ON
INSTITUTIONAL RACISM AND TAKE ON
THE CORPORATE --
>> THE FIRST CONGRESSMAN TO DO
THAT WAS ME WHEN I WAS A YOUNG
CONGRESSMAN.
>> ON THE ISSUE OF PARTISAN
GRIDLOCK.
PRESIDENT OBAMA SAID AFTER HIS
ELECTION PEOPLE WOULD WANT TO
WORK WITH REPUBLICANS AND NOW
VICE PRESIDENT BIDEN IS SAYING
THE SAME THING, THAT IF HE'S
ELECTED IN 2020 BOTH PARTIES
WILL WANT TO WORK TOGETHER.
SHOULD VOTERS BELIEVE THAT
SOMEHOW IF THERE'S A DEMOCRATIC
PRESIDENT IN 2021 THAT GRIDLOCK
IS GOING TO MAGICALLY DISSIPATE?
>> GRIDLOCK WILL NOT MAGICALLY
DISAPPEAR AS LONG AS MITCH
McCONNELL IS THERE FIRST.
SECOND, SECOND, THAT'S WHY IT IS
SO IMPORTANT FOR US TO WIN NOT
JUST THE PRESIDENCY, TO HAVE
SOMEBODY THAT CAN RUN IN ALL 50
STATES, BUT TO -- BUT TO WIN THE
SENATE AS WELL, AND THAT'S WHY
WE HAVE TO PROPOSE POLICIES THAT
CAN BE SUPPORTED LIKE MEDICARE
"X" SO THAT WE CAN BUILD A BROAD
COALITION OF AMERICANS TO
OVERCOME BROKEN WASHINGTON, D.C.
I AGREE WITH WHAT SENATOR
GILLIBRAND WAS SAYING AND SHARE
A LOT OF HER VIEWS.
WE NEED TO END GERRYMANDERING IN
WASHINGTON AND WE NEED TO END
POLITICAL GERRYMANDERING IN
WASHINGTON.
THE COURT TODAY SAID THEY
COULDN'T DO ANYTHING ABOUT IT.
WE NEED TO OVERTURN CITIZENS
UNIT.
THE COURT WAS THE ONE THAT GAVE
US CITIZENS UNITED, AND THE
ATTACK ON INVESTIGATE RIGHTS IN
SHELBY VERSUS HOMER IS SOMETHING
THAT WE NEED TO DEAL WITH.
ALL OF THOSE THINGS HAVE
HAPPENED SINCE VICE PRESIDENT
BIDEN WAS IN THE SENATE, AND
WE'VE FACED STRUCTURAL PROBLEMS
THAT WE HAVE TO OVERCOME WITH A
BROAD COALITION.
IT'S THE ONLY WAY WE CAN DO IT.
WE NEED TO ROOT OUT THE
CORRUPTION IN WASHINGTON AND
EXPAND PEOPLE'S RIGHTS TO GET TO
POLLS AND I THINK THAT WE CAN
SUCCEED.
>> VICE PRESIDENT BIDEN, 30
SECONDS.
WHAT -- IT DOES SOUND AS IF YOU
HAVEN'T SEEN WHAT'S BEEN
HAPPENING IN THE UNITED STATES
SENATE OVER THE LAST 12 YEARS.
IT DIDN'T HAPPEN, WHY?
>> I HAVE SEEN WHAT HAPPENED.
JUST SINCE I WAS VICE PRESIDENT.
WE NEEDED THREE VOTES TO PASS AN
$800 BILLION RECOVERY ACT THAT
KEPT US FROM GOING INTO A
DEPRESSION.
I GOT THREE VOTES CHANGED.
WE NEEDED TO BE ABLE TO KEEP THE
GOVERNMENT FROM SHUTTING DOWN
AND GOING BANKRUPT.
I GOT MITCH McCONNELL TO RAISE
TAXES $600 BILLION BY RAISING
THE TOP RATE, AND AS RECENTLY
AFTER THE PRESIDENT GOT ELECTED
I WAS ABLE TO PUT TOGETHER A
COALITION THAT BILLIONS OF
DOLLARS GO INTO CANCER RESEARCH,
BIPARTISAN, BUT SOMETIMES YOU
CAN'T DO THAT.
SOMETIMES YOU'VE GOT TO GO OUT
AND BEAT THEM.
I WENT INTO 20 STATES, OVER 60
CANDIDATES AND GUESS WHAT, WE
BEAT THEM.
WE WON BACK THE SENATE.
>> THANK YOU.
>> CHUCK, THE PROBLEM WITH WHAT
THE VICE PRESIDENT --
>> 30 SECONDS, GO AHEAD.
>> SOMETIMES YOU DO HAVE TO BEAT
THEM, BUT THE DEAL THAT HE
TALKED ABOUT WITH MITCH
McCONNELL WAS A COMPLETE VICTORY
FOR THE TEA PARTY.
IT EXTENDED THE BUSH TAX CUTS
PERMANENTLY.
THE DEMOCRATIC PARTY HAS BEEN
RUNNING AGAINST THAT FOR TEN
YEARS.
WE'VE LOST THAT ECONOMIC
ARGUMENT BECAUSE THAT DEAL
EXTEND ALMOST ALL THE BUSH TAX
CUTS PERMANENTLY AND PUT IN
PLACE THE MINDLESS CUTS THAT WE
STILL ARE DEALING WITH TODAY
THAT ARE CALLED THE SEQUESTER.
THAT WAS A GREAT DEAL FOR
MR. McCONNELL AND A TERRIBLE
DEAL FOR AMERICA.
>> THE REASON THE TRUMP TAX CUTS
WERE PASSED BECAUSE THEY HAD TO
PAY BACK THE OWNERS, YOU HEARD
THEM SAY THE WORDS.
THE CORRUPTION IN WASHINGTON IS
REAL AND MAKES EVERY ONE OF THE
PLANS THAT WE'VE HEARD ABOUT
OVER THE NEXT SEVERAL MONTHS
IMPOSSIBLE AND I HAVE THE MOST
COMPREHENSIVE APPROACH TO DO IT
WITH CLEAN ELECTIONS, PUBLICLY
FUND ELECTIONS.
WE RESTORE THE POWER OF
DEMOCRACY INTO THE HANDS OF THE
VOTERS, NOT INTO THE KOCH
BROTHERS.
WE WERE TALKING ABOUT ISSUES.
WE'RE IN FLORIDA, IMAGINE THE
PARKLAND KIDS HAVING AS MUCH
POWER IN OUR DEMOCRACY AS THE
KOCH BROTHERS OR THE NRA.
IMAGINE THEIR VOICES ARE
CARRYING FARTHER AND WIDER THAN
ANYONE ELSE BECAUSE THEIR VOICE
IS NEEDED.
>> SENATOR GILLIBRAND.
THANK YOU.
>> NOTHING ELSE IS POSSIBLE
WHETHER IT'S EDUCATION OR
HEALTHCARE.
>> I'D LIKE TO PUT A DIFFERENT
QUESTION TO YOU.
"ROE V. WADE" HAS BEEN THE LAW
OF THE LAND SINCE 1973.
NOW THAT THERE IS A CONSERVATIVE
MAJORITY ON THE SUPREME COURT
SEVERAL REPUBLICAN-CONTROLLED
STATES HAVE PASSED LAWS TO
SEVERELY RESTRICT OR BAN
ABORTION.
ONE OF THOSE LAWS DO VERY WELL
MAKE IT TO THE SUPREME COURT
DURING YOUR PRESIDENCY IF YOU'RE
ELECTED PRESIDENT.
WHAT IS YOUR PLAN IF "ROE" IS
STRUCK DOWN WHILE YOU'RE IN
PRESIDENT.
>> MY PLAN AS SOMEBODY WHO
BELIEVES FOR A START THAT A
WOMAN'S RIGHT TO CONTROL HER OWN
BODY IS A CONSTITUTIONAL RIGHT
THAT GOVERNMENT AND POLITICIANS
SHOULD NOT INFRINGE ON THAT
RIGHT.
WE WILL DO EVERYTHING WE CAN TO
DEFEND "ROE V. WADE."
SECOND OF ALL, LET ME MAKE --
LET ME MAKE -- LET ME MAKE A
PROMISE HERE.
YOU ASKED ABOUT LITMUS TEST.
MY LITMUS TEST IS I WILL NEVER
APPOINT ANY NOMINATION --
NOMINATE ANY JUSTICE TO THE
SUPREME COURT UNLESS I THOUGHT
IT WAS 100% CLEAR THAT WE OR SHE
WOULD DEFEND "ROE V. WADE."
THIRD OF ALL, I DO NOT BELIEVE
IN PACKING THE COURT.
WE GOT A TERRIBLE 5-4 MAJORITY,
CONSERVATIVE COURT RIGHT NOW,
BUT I DO BELIEVE THAT
CONSTITUTIONALLY WE HAVE THE
POWER TO ROTATE JUDGES TO OTHER
COURT, AND THAT BRINGS THE NEW
BLOOD INTO THE SUPREME COURT AND
A MAJORITY I HOPE THAT WILL
UNDERSTAND THAT A WOMAN HAS THE
RIGHT TO CONTROL HER OWN BODY
AND THAT CORPORATIONS CANNOT RUN
THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA.
>> HOLD ON.
I'M GOING TO GIVE YOU TEN
ADDITIONAL SECONDS.
>> THE QUESTION IS WHAT IF THE
COURT HAS ALREADY OVERTURNED ROE
AND IT'S GONE.
ALL OF THE THINGS YOU JUST
DESCRIBED WOULD BE TRY TO
PRESERVE IT.
IF ROE IS GONE WHAT WILL YOU DO
AS PRESIDENT?
>> WELL, FIRST OF ALL, LET ME
TELL YOU THIS.
IT DIDN'T COME UP.
MEDICARE FOR ALL GUARANTEES
EVERY WOMAN IN THIS COUNTRY THE
RIGHT TO HAVE AN ABORTION IF SHE
WANTS IT.
>> THANK YOU, SENATOR.
>> CAN I JUST ADDRESS THIS FOR A
SECOND, AND I WANT TO TALK
DIRECTLY, DIRECTLY TO AMERICA'S
WOMEN AND TO MEN WHO LOVE THEM.
WOMEN'S REPRODUCTIVE RIGHTS ARE
UNDER ASSAULT BY PRESIDENT TRUMP
AND THE REPUBLICAN PARTY.
30 STATES ARE TRYING TO OVERTURN
"ROE V. WADE" RIGHT NOW, AND IT
IS MIND BOGGLING TO ME THAT WE
ARE DEBATING THIS ON THIS STAGE
IN 2019 AMONG DEMOCRATS WHETHER
WOMEN SHOULD HAVE ACCESS TO
REPRODUCTIVE RIGHTS.
I THINK WE HAVE TO STOP PLAYING
DEFENSE AND START PLAYING
OFFENSE, BUT LET ME TELL YOU ONE
THING ABOUT POLITICS BECAUSE IT
GOES TO THE CRUX OF THE
DEAL-MAKE.
WHEN THE DOORS CLOSE AND THE
NEGOTIATIONS ARE MADE, THERE ARE
CONVERSATIONS ABOUT WOMEN'S
RIGHTS AND COMPROMISES HAVE BEEN
MADE ON OUR BOOKS, THAT'S HOW WE
GOT TO HYDE, THAT'S HOW THE HYDE
AMENDMENT WAS CREATED, A
COMPROMISE BY LEADERS OF BOTH
PARTIES.
THEN VERY WITH THE ACA.
DURING THE ACA NEGOTIATION, I
HAD TO FIGHT LIKE HECK WITH
OTHER WOMEN TO MAKE SURE THAT
CONTRACEPTION WASN'T SOLD DOWN
THE RIVER OR ABORTION SERVICES
ARE AND SOY WHAT WE NEED TO KNOW
IS IMAGINE THIS ONE QUESTION,
WHEN WE BEAT PRESIDENT TRUMP AND
MITCH McCONNELL WALKS INTO THE
OVAL OFFICE, GOD FORBID TO DO
NEGOTIATIONS, WHO DO YOU WANT
WHEN THAT DOOR CLOSES SITTING
BEHIND THAT DESK TO FIGHT FOR
WOMEN'S RIGHTS?
I'VE BEEN THE FIERCEST ADVOCATE
FOR OVER A DECADE.
>> THANK YOU.
>> AND I PROMISE WHEN THAT DOOR
CLOSES I'LL GUARANTEE WOMEN'S
REPRODUCTIVE RIGHTS NO MATTER
WHAT.
>> THANK YOU, THANK YOU.
WE'RE MOVING TO CLIMATE, GUYS.
SENATOR HARRIS, I'M ADDRESS YOU
FIRST.
YOU LIVE IN A STATE THAT'S BEEN
HIT BY DROUGHT, WILDFIRES,
FLOODING, CLIMATE CHANGE IS A
MAJOR CONCERN FOR YOUR STATE,
PRETTY OBVIOUS.
LAST NIGHT VOTERS HEARD MANY OF
THE CANDIDATES WEIGH IN ON THEIR
PROPOSALS.
EXPLAIN SPECIFICALLY WHAT YOURS
IS.
>> WELL, FIRST OF ALL, I DON'T
EVEN CALL IT CLIMATE CHANGE.
IT'S A CLIMATE CRISIS
T.REPRESENTS AN EXISTENTIAL
THREAT TO US AS A SPECIES, AND
THE FACT THAT WE HAVE A
PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED STATES
WHO HAS EMBRACED SCIENCE PHIL
MICKELSON OVER FACT WILL BE TO
OUR COLLECTIVE PERIL.
I VISITED WHILE THE EMBERS WERE
SMOULDERING THE WILDFIRES IN
CALIFORNIA.
I SPOKE WITH FIREFIGHTERS WHO
WERE IN THE MIDST OF FIGHTING A
FIRE WHILE THEIR OWN HOMES WERE
BURNING, AND ON THIS ISSUE IT IS
A CRITICAL ISSUE THAT IS ABOUT
WHAT WE MUST DO TO CONFRONT WHAT
IS IMMEDIATE AND BEFORE US RIGHT
NOW.
THAT'S WHY I SUPPORT A GREEN NEW
DEAL.
IT'S WHY I BELIEVE ON DAY ONE
AND AS PRESIDENT WE'LL RE-ENTER
US INTO THE PARIS AGREEMENT
BECAUSE WE HAVE TO TAKE THESE
ISSUES SERIOUSLY, AND FRANKLY
VERY A PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED
STATES.
WE TALKED ABOUT -- YOU ASKED
BEFORE WHAT IS THE GREATEST
NATIONAL SECURITY THREAT TO THE
UNITED STATES IT'S DONALD TRUMP,
AND I'M GOING TO TELL YOU, WHY
BECAUSE I AGREE CLIMATE CHANGE
REPRESENTS AN EXISTENTIAL
THREAT.
HE DENIES THE SCIENCE.
YOU WANT TO TALK ABOUT NORTH
KOREA.
REAL THREAT IN TERMS OF NUCLEAR
ARSENAL, BUT WHAT DOES HE DO?
HE EMBRACES KIM JONG-UN, A
DICTATOR FOR THE SAKE OF A PHOTO
OP, PUTIN, YOU WANT TO TALK --
>> I WANT TO STICK TO CLIMATE.
>> HE TAKES THE WORD OVER THE
AMERICAN JENS COMMUNITY WHEN IT
TOMS TO A TOO THREAT TO OUR
DEMOCRACY AND OUR ELECTION.
THESE ARE THE ISSUES THAT ARE
BEFORE US, CHUCK.
>> I HEAR YOU.
THANK YOU, SENATOR HARRIS.
MAYOR BUTTIGIEG, IN YOUR CLIMATE
PLAN IF USUAL ELECTED PRESIDENT
IN YOUR FIRST TERM HOW IS THIS
GOING TO HELP FARMERS IMPACTED
BY CLIMATE CHANGE IN THE
MIDWEST?
>> WELL, THE REALITY IS WE NEED
TO BEGIN ADAPTING RIGHT AWAY BUT
WE ALSO CAN'T SKIP A BEAT ON
PREVENTING CLIMATE CHANGE FROM
GETTING EVEN WORSE.
THAT'S WHY WE NEED AGGRESSIVE
AND AMBITIOUS MEASURES.
THAT'S WHY WE NEED TO DO A
CARBON TAX AND DIVIDEND, BUT I
WOULD PROPOSE WE DO IT IN A WAY
THAT'S REBATED OUT TO THE
AMERICAN PEOPLE IN A PROGRESSIVE
FASHION SO THAT MOST AMERICANS
ARE MADE MORE THAN WHOLE.
THIS ISN'T THEORETICAL FOR US IN
SOUTH BEND EITHER.
PARTS OF CALIFORNIA ON FIRE.
RIGHT HERE IN FLORIDA THEY ARE
TALKING ABOUT SHE LEVEL RISE.
I HAD TO ENACT THE EMERGENCY
MEASURES IN OUR CITY, THE FIRST
WAS A THOUSAND YEAR FLOOD AND
THE NEXT WAS A 500-YEAR FLOOD.
THIS IS NOT JUST HAPPENING ON
THE ARCTIC ICE CAPS.
THIS IS HAPPENING IN THE MIDDLE
OF THE COUNTRY AND WE'VE GOT TO
BE DRAMATICALLY MORE AGGRESSIVE
MOVING FORWARD.
HERE'S WHAT VERY FEW PEOPLE TALK
ABOUT.
FIRST OF ALL, RURAL AMERICA CAN
BE PART OF THE SOLUTION INSTEAD
OF BEING TOLD THEY ARE PART OF
THE PROBLEM.
WITH THE RIGHT KIND OF SOIL
MANAGEMENT RURAL MANAGEMENT
COULD BE A HUGE PART OF HOW WE
GET THIS DONE AND SECONDLY WE'VE
GOT TO LOOK TO THE LEADERSHIP OF
LOCAL COMMUNITIES.
THE NETWORKS AND MAYORS AND
CITIES AROUND THE WORLD THAT
COME TOGETHER.
WE NEED TO HAVE A SUMMIT WHERE
WE BRING THEM TOGETHER.
>> THANK YOU, MAYOR BUTTIGIEG.
>> I WANT TO BRING GOVERNOR
HICKENLOOPER IN.
YOU'VE SAID THAT OIL AND GAS
COMPANIES SHOULD BE A PART OF
THE SOLUTION ON CLIMATE CHANGE.
LOTS OF YOUR COLLEAGUES ON STAGE
HAVE TALKED ABOUT MOVING AWAY
FROM FOSSIL FUELS ENTIRELY.
CAN OIL AND GAS COMPANIES BE
REAL PARTNERS IN THIS FIGHT?
>> WELL, I SHARE THE SENSE OF
URGENCY.
I'M A SCIENTIST SO I -- I
RECOGNIZE THAT IN SO OR 12 YEARS
OF ACTUALLY, YOU KNOW, SUFFERING
IRREVERSIBLE DAMAGE, BUT, YOU
KNOW, GUARANTEEING EVERYBODY A
GOVERNMENT JOB IS NOT GOING TO
GET US THERE.
SOCIALISM IN THAT SENSE IS NOT
THE SOLUTION.
WE HAVE TO LOOK AT WHAT REALLY
WILL MAKE A DIFFERENCE.
IN COLORADO WE'VE CLOSED A
COUPLE OF COOL PLANTS AND
REPLACED THEM WITH SOLAR AND
WIND AND BATTERY AND MONTHLY
BILLS HAVE GONE DOWN.
WE'RE BUILDING A NETWORK FOR
ELECTRIC VEHICLES.
WE'RE WORKING WITH THE OIL AND
GAS INDUSTRY, AND WE'VE CREATED
THE FIRST METHANE REGULATIONS IN
THE COUNTRY.
METHANE IS 25 TIMES WORSE THAN
CO2 AND THEN WE'VE GOT TO GET TO
THE LAST PART, THE HEAVY
INDUSTRIAL INDUSTRIES, WE
HAVEN'T SEEN THE PLANS YET.
IF YOU LOOK AT THE REAL
PROBLEMS, CO2, THE WORST
POLLUTERS OF CO2 IS CHINA, THE
UNITED STATES AND CONCRETE AND
EXHALATION AND BEYOND THAT ONLY
BY BRINGING PEOPLE TOGETHER,
BUSES AND NON-PROFITS, WE CAN'T
DEMONIZE EVERY BUSINESS.
WE WE'VE GO TO BRING THEM
TOGETHER BECAUSE ULTIMATELY IFFY
WITH EAR NOT ABLE TO DO THAT
WE'LL DOOMED FAILURE.
WE HAVE NO WAY OF DOING THIS
WITHOUT BRING EVERYONE TOGETHER.
>> VICE PRESIDENT BIDEN, ON THE
ISSUE OF HOW YOU DO THIS,
DEMOCRATS ARE ARGUING ROBUSTLY
AMONG THEMSELVES ABOUT WHAT'S
THE BEST WAY TO TACKLE CLIMATE
CHANGE, BUT IF WE'RE HONEST MANY
REAP WARNINGS INCLUDING THE
PRESIDENT, ARE STILL NOT SURE IF
THEY BELIEVE IT'S EVEN A SERIOUS
APPROXIMATE SO ARE THERE
SIGNIFICANT WAYS YOU CAN CUT
CARBON EMISSIONS IF YOU HAVE TO
DO IT WITH NO SUPPORT FROM
CONGRESS?
>> THE ANSWER IS YES.
NUMBER ONE, WHEN OUR
ADMINISTRATION, WE BUILT THE
LARGEST WIND FARM IN THE WORLD,
THE LARGEST SOLAR ENERGY
FACILITY IN THE WORLD.
WE DROVE DOWN THE PRICE,
COMPETITIVE PRICE OF BOAST THOSE
RENEWABLE SOURCES.
I WOULD IMMEDIATELY INSIST THAT
WE IN FACT BUILD 500,000
RECHARGING STATIONS THROUGHOUT
UNITED STATES OF AMERICA WORKING
WITH GOVERNORS, MAYORS AND
OTHERS SO THAT WE CAN GO TO A
FULL ELECTRIC VEHICLE FUTURE BY
THE YEAR 2030.
WOULD I MAKE SURE THAT WE
INVESTED $400 MILLION IN NEW
SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY TO BE THE
EXPORTER NOT ONLY OF THE GREEN
ECONOMY BUT AN ECONOMY THAT CAN
CREATE MILLIONS OF JOBS, BUT I
WOULD IMMEDIATELY JOIN THE PARIS
CLIMATE ACCORD.
I WOULD UP THE ANTE IN THAT
ACCORD WHICH IT CALLS FOR
BECAUSE WE MAKE UP 15% OF THE
PROBLEM.
85% OF THE WORLD MAKES UP THE
REST, AND SO WE HAVE TO HAVE
SOMEONE WHO KNOWS HOW TO CORRAL
THE REST WORLD, BRING THEM
TOGETHER AND GET SOMETHING DONE
IN OUR ADMINISTRATION.
>> I WANT TO GIVE YOU 30 SECONDS
TO FOLLOW UP AND I'M GOING TO
HOLD TO YOU 30.
>> THE OLD WAYS ARE NO LONGER
RELEVANT.
THE SCIENTISTS TELL US WE HAVE
12 YEARS BEFORE THERE'S
IRREPARABLE DAMAGE TO THIS
PLANET.
THIS IS A GLOBAL ISSUE.
WHAT THE PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED
STATES SHOULD DO IS NOT DENY THE
REALITY OF CLIMATE CHANGE BUT
TELL THE REST OF THE WORLD THAT
INSTEAD OF SPENDING A TRILLION
AND A HALF DOLLARS ON WE OFFENSE
DESTRUCTION LET US GET TOGETHER
FOR THE COMMON ENERGY AND THAT'S
TO TRANSFORM THE WORLD'S ENERGY
SYSTEM AWAY FROM FOSSIL FUEL TO
ENERGY EFFICIENCY AND
SUSTAINABLE ENERGY.
>> THANK YOU.
>> THE FUTURE OF THE PLANET
RESTS ON US DOING THAT.
>> BEFORE WE GO.
HANG ON.
>> BEFORE WE LEAVE THIS TOPIC.
>> LISTEN, PASS THE TORCH.
PASS THE TORCH TO THE GENERATION
THAT GOING TO FEEL THE EFFECTS
OF CLIMATE CHANGE.
>> BEFORE WE LEAVE THIS TOPIC,
HERE'S SOMETHING THAT YOU'LL
WANT TO WEIGH IN ON.
HOLD ONE MOMENT.
>> JUST BECAUSE YOU'RE IN A
YOUNGER BODY DOESN'T MEAN YOU
HAVE OLD IDEAS.
>> JOHN KENNEDY -- JOHN KENNEDY
DID NOT SAY I HAVE A PLAN TO GET
A MAN TO THE MOON AND SO WE'RE
GOING TO DO IT AND I THINK WE
CAN ALL WORK TOGETHER AND MAYBE
WE'LL GET A MAN ON THE MOON.
JOHN KENNEDY SAID BY THE END OF
THIS DECADE WE ARE GOING TO PUT
A MAN ON THE MOON BECAUSE JOHN
KENNEDY WAS BACK IN THE DAY WHEN
POLITICS INCLUDED THE PEOPLE AND
INCLUDED IMAGINATION AND
INCLUDED GREAT DREAMS AND
INCLUDED GREAT PLANS AND I HAVE
HAD A CAREER NOT MAKE MAKING THE
POLITICAL PLAN BUT I'VE HAD A
CAREER HARNESSING THE
INSPIRATION AND MOTIVATION AND
EXCITEMENT OF PEOPLE.
MASSES OF PEOPLE.
WHEN WE KNOW THAT WE SAY WE'RE
GOING TO TURN FROM A DIRTY
ECONOMY TO A CLEAN ECONOMY WE'RE
GOING TO HAVE A GREEN NEW DEAL,
WE'RE GOING TO CREATE MILLIONS
OF JOBS, WE'RE GOING TO DO THIS
WITHIN THE NEXT 12 YEARS BECAUSE
I'M NOT INTERESTED IN JUST
WINNING THE NEXT ELECTION.
WE ARE INTERESTED IN OUR
GRANDCHILDREN.
>> WE'RE GOING SNEAK IN A BREAK
IN A MINUTE BUT BEFORE WE GO I'M
GOING TO GO DOWN THE LINE HERE
AND I'M ASKING YOU TO PLEASE FOR
ONE OR TWO WORDS ONLY, ALL
RIGHT, PLEASE.
THE.
>> REALLY.
>> PRESIDENT OBAMA IN HIS FIRST
YEAR WANTED TO ADDRESS BOTH
HEALTHCARE AND CLIMATE AND ONLY
GET ONE SIGNATURE ISSUE
ACCOMPLISHED HEALTHCARE.
HE DIDN'T GET TO DO CLIMATE
CHANGE.
YOU MAY GET ONE SHOT AND THE
FIRST ISSUE YOU'RE GOING TO
PUSH.
YOU GET ONE SHOT THAT IT MAY BE
THE ONLY THING YOU GET PASSED.
WHAT IS THAT FIRST ISSUE FOR
YOUR PRESIDENCY, ERIC SWALWELL,
YOU'RE FIRST?
>> FOR PARKLAND AND EVERY
COMMUNITY AFFECTED BY GUN
VIOLENCE, ENDING GUN VIOLENCE.
>> SENATOR BEN.
>> CLIMATE CHANGE AND THE LACK
OF ECONOMIC MOBILITY BERNIE
TALKS ABOUT.
>> SENATOR GILLIBRAND.
>> PASSING A FAMILY BILL OF
RIGHTS THAT INCLUDES A NATIONAL
PAID LEAVE PLAN, UNIVERSAL
PRE-K, AFFORDABLE DAY CARE AND
MAKING SURE THAT WOMEN AND
FAMILIES CAN THRIVE IN THE
WORKPLACE NO MATTER WHO THEY
ARE.
>> OH, I LIKE THAT.
>> SENATOR HARRIS, PASSING A
MIDDLE CLASS AND WORKING FAMILY
TAX CUT, DACA, GUNS.
>> I'LL GIVE YOU CREDIT FOR THE
FIRST THING YOU SAID.
>> SENATOR SANDERS, ONLY ONE OR
TWO ISSUES OUT THERE.
>> I'M NOT SAYING THERE'S ONE OR
TWO.
>> SENATOR SANDERS.
>> YOU NEED A POLITICAL
REVOLUTION.
PEOPLE HAVE GOT TO STAND UP AND
TAKE ON THE SPECIAL INTERESTS.
WE CAN TRANSFORM THIS COUNTRY.
>> VICE PRESIDENT BIDEN, YOUR
FIRST ISSUE, MR. VICE PRESIDENT.
>> I THINK YOU'RE SO
UNDERESTIMATING WHAT BARACK
OBAMA DID.
HE'S THE FIRST MAN TO BRING
TOGETHER THE ENTIRE WORLD, 196
NATIONS TO COMMIT TO DEAL WITH
CLIMATE CHANGE.
I DON'T BUY THAT.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> THE FIRST THING I WOULD DO IS
MAKE SURE THAT WE DEFEAT DONALD
TRUMP.
>> OKAY.
>> PERIOD.
>> MAYOR BUTTIGIEG, YOUR FIRST
PRIORITY, YOUR FIRST ISSUE AS
PRESIDENT THAT YOU ARE GOING TO
BLOCK AND TACKLE.
>> FIX OUR DEMOCRACY BEFORE IT'S
TOO LATE.
GET THAT RIGHT, CLIMATE,
IMMIGRATION, TAXES AND EVERY
OTHER ISSUE GETS BETTER.
>> YANG.
>> I WOULD PASS A $1,000 FREEDOM
DIFFIDENT FOR EVERY AMERICAN
ADULT WHICH WOULD SPEED US UP ON
CLIMATE CHANGE BECAUSE IF YOU
GET THE BOOT OFF PEOPLE'S
THROATS THEY WILL FOCUS ON
CLIMATE CHANGE.
>> GOVERNOR HICKENLOOPER.
>> I WOULD DO A COLLABORATIVE
APPROACH TO CLIMATE CHANGE AND I
WOULD PRONOUNCE IT WELL BEFORE
THE ETHEROUX MAKE SURE WE DON'T
RE-ELECT THE WORST PRESIDENT IN
AMERICAN HISTORY.
>> AND MISS WILLIAMSON.
>> MY FIRST CALL IS TO THE PRIME
MINISTER OF NEW ZEALAND TO MAKE
THE PLACE THAT NEW ZEALAND IS
THE BEST PLACE IN THE WORLD FOR
A CHILD TO GROIN AND I WILL SAY
THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA IS
GOING TO BE THE BEST PLACE IN
THE WORLD FOR A CHILD TO GROW
UP.
WE ARE GOING --
>> THANK YOU.
YOU GRICE CLOSE -- AT LEAST IT
WAS SHORTER RESPONSES.
>> NOT AT ALL.
>> B-MINUS.
>> WE'RE GOING TO TAKE A QUICK
BREAK AND BE RIGHT BACK WITH
THESE CANDIDATES RIGHT AFTER
THIS.
K WITH THESE
CANDIDATES RIGHT AFTER THIS.
>>> WELCOME BACK TO THE
DEMOCRATIC CANDIDATES DEBATE IN
MIAMI.
WELL EAR GOING TO CONTINUE THE
QUESTIONING NOW WITH THE
AUDIENCE.
WE ARE?
WE ARE IN A SECOND GOING TO HAVE
A QUESTION FROM THE AUDIENCE BUT
THAT WAS JUST A FAKE-OUT.
>> GO AHEAD.
>> WE'RE GOING TO GO TO THE
ISSUE OF GUNS.
>> CONGRESSMAN SWALWELL, YOU
HAVE YOU A UNIQUE POSITION ON
GUN REFORM.
YOU'RE PROPOSE THE GUN SHOULD
BUY BACK EVERY ASSAULT WEAPON IN
AMERICA AND IT SHOULD BE MANNED
TRIP.
HOW DO YOU ENVISION THAT WORKING
ESPECIALLY IN STATES WHERE GUN
RIGHTS ARE A STRONG PLATFORM?
>> KEEP YOUR PISTOLS, YOUR
RIFLES, YOUR SHOTGUNS BUT WE CAN
TAKE THE MOST DANGEROUS WEAPONS
FROM THE MOST DANGEROUS PEOPLE.
WE HAVE THE NRA ON THE ROPES
BECAUSE OF THE MOMS, BECAUSE OF
THE BRADY GROUP, BECAUSE OF
DIFFERENT -- BECAUSE OF MARCH
FOR OUR LIFE, BUT I'M ONLY
CANDIDATE ON THIS STAGE CALLING
FOR A BAN AND BUYBACK OF EVERY
SINGLE ASSAULT WEAPON IN MERGE
I'VE SEEN THE PLANS OF THE OTHER
CANDIDATES HERE.
THEY WOULD ALL LEAVE 15 MILLION
ASSAULT WEAPONS IN OUR COMMUNITY
AND WOULDN'T DO A SINGLE THING
TO SAVE A SINGLE LIFE IN
PARKLAND.
I'LL APPROACH THIS ISSUE AS A
PROSECUTOR.
I'LL APPROACH IT AS THE ONLY
PERSON ON THE STAGE WHO HAS
VOTED AND PASSED BACKGROUND
CHECKS BUT ALSO AS A PARENT OF A
GENERATION WHO SENDS OUR
CHILDREN TO SCHOOL AND WE LOOK
AT WHAT THEY ARE WEARING, SO WE
CAN REMEMBER IT IN CASE WE HAVE
TO IDENTIFY THEM LATER.
A GENERATION WHO HAS SEEN
THOUSAND OF BLACK CHILDREN
KILLED IN OUR STREETS AND A
GENERATION WHO GOES TO THE
THEATER AND WE ACTUALLY LOOK
WHERE THE FIRE EXITS ARE.
WE DON'T HAVE TO LIVE THIS WAY.
WE MUST BE A COUNTRY WHO LOVES
OUR CHILDREN MORE THAN WE LOVE
OUR GUNS.
>> SENATOR SANDERS, A VERMONT
NEWSPAPER RECENTLY RELEASED
PORTIONS OF AN INTERVIEW YOU
GAVE IN 2013 IN WHICH YOU SAID,
QUOTE, MY OWN VIEW ON GUNS IS
EVERYTHING BEING EQUAL STATES
SHOULD MAKE THOSE DECISIONS.
HAS YOUR THINKING CHANGED SINCE
THEN, DO YOU THINK THERE'S A
FEDERAL ROLE TO PLAY.
>> THAT'S A MISCHARACTERIZATION.
>> THAT'S A QUOTE OF YOURS.
>> WE HAVE A GUN CRISIS RIGHT
NOW, 40,000 PEOPLE A YEAR ARE
GETTING KILLED.
IN 1988, RACHEL, WHEN IT WASN'T
POPULAR, I RAN ON A PLATFORM OF
BANNING ASSAULT WEAPONS.
I HAVE A D-MINUS INVESTIGATE
RECORD FROM THE NRA, AND I
BELIEVE THAT WHAT WE NEED IS
COMPREHENSIVE GUN LEGISLATION
THAT AMONG OTHER THINGS PROVIDE
UNIVERSAL BACKGROUNDS, WE END
THE GUN SHOW LOOPHOLES AND END
THE STRAW MAN POSITION AND I
BELIEVE IN 1988 AND TODAY.
ASSAULT WEAPONS --
>> YOU LEAVE 15 MILLION WEAPONS.
>> AND THEY SHOULD NOT BE ON THE
STREETS OF AMERICA.
>> YOU WOULD -- YOUR PLAN LEAVES
THEM ON THE STREET.
LEAVES 15 MILLION ON THE STREET.
>> WE BAN THE SALE.
>> WOULD YOU BUY THEM BACK?
>> THAT'S WHAT I BELIEVE FOR
MANY YEARS.
>> WOULD YOU BUY THEM BACK?
>> IF THE GOVERNMENT WANTS TO DO
THAT, IF PEOPLE WANT TO DO THAT.
>> SENATOR HARRIS.
>> I THINK YOUR IDEA IS A GREAT
ONE, CONGRESSMAN SWALWELL, AND I
WOULD SAY THERE'S A LOT OF GREAT
IDEAS.
THE PROBLEM IS CONGRESS HAS NOT
HAD THE COURAGE OF ACT WHICH IS
WHY WHEN I'M ELECTED PRESIDENT
OF THE UNITED STATES I'LL GIVE
THE UNITED STATES CONGRESS 100
DAYS TO PULL THEIR ACT TOGETHER,
BRING ALL THESE GOOD IDEAS
TOGETHER AND PUT A BILL ON MY
DESK FOR SIGNATURE AND IF THEY
DO NOT I WILL TAKE EXECUTIVE
ACTION AND I WILL PUT IN PLACE
THE MOST COMPREHENSIVE
BACKGROUND CHECK POLICY WE'VE
H.I WILL REQUIRE THE ATF TO TAKE
THE LICENSES OF GUN DEALERS WHO
VIOLATE THE LAW AND I WILL BAN
BY EXECUTIVE ORDER THE
IMPORTATION OF ASSAULT WEAPONS
BECAUSE I'M GOING TO TELL YOU AS
A PROSECUTOR I HAVE SEEN MORE
AUTOPSY PHOTOGRAPHS THAN I CARE
TO TELL YOU, I HAVE HUGGED MORE
MOTHERS WHO ARE THE MOTHERS OF
HOMICIDE VICTIMS AND I HAVE
ATTENDED MORE POLICE OFFICER
FUNERALS.
IT IS ENOUGH.
THERE'S BEEN PLENTY OF GOOD
IDEAS FROM MEMBERS OF THE UNITED
STATES CONGRESS BUT THERE'S BEEN
NO ACTION.
AS PRESIDENT I WILL TAKE ACTION.
>> MAYOR BUTTIGIEG, I WANT TO
BRING YOU IN ON THIS, SIR.
A LOT OF CONVERSATIONS ABOUT
ASSAULT RIFLES THAT ARE OFTEN
DESIGNATED AS MILITARY STYLE
WEAPONS.
YOU'RE THE ONLY PERSON ON THE
STAGE WITH MILITARY EXPERIENCE
AT A VETERAN OF THE IRAQ WAR.
DO YOU BELIEVE THAT MILITARY
FAMILIES OR AMERICA'S VETERANS
WILL AT LARGE HAVE A DIFFERENT
TAKE ON THIS THAN THE OTHER
AMERICANS WHO WE'VE OPINION
TALKING ABOUT?
>> YEAH, OF COURSE, BECAUSE WE
TRAINED ON SOME OF THESE KINDS
OF WEAPONS.
LOOK, EVERY PART OF MY LIFE
EXPERIENCE INFORMS ME, BEING THE
MAYOR OF A CITY WHERE THE WORST
PART OF THE JOB IS DEALING WITH
VIOLENCE.
WE LOSE AS MANY AS WERE LOST TO
PARKLAND EVERY TWO OR THREE
YEARS IN MY CITY ALONE, AND THIS
IS TEARING COMMUNITIES APART.
IF MORE GUNS MADE US SAFER, WE'D
BE THE SAFEST COUNTRY ON EARTH.
IT DOESN'T WORK THAT WAY.
AND COMMON SENSE MEASURES LIKE
UNIVERSAL BACKGROUND CHECKS
CAN'T SEEM TO GET DELIVERED BY
WASHINGTON, EVEN WHEN MOST
REPUBLICANS, LET ALONE MOST
AMERICANS, AGREE IT'S THE RIGHT
THING TO DO AND AS SOMEBODY WHO
TRAINED ON WEAPONS OF WAR I CAN
TELL YOU THAT THERE ARE WEAPONS
THAT HAVE ABSOLUTELY NO PLACE IN
AMERICAN CITIES OR NEIGHBORHOODS
IN PEACETIME EVER.
>> VICE PRESIDENT BIDEN, 30
SECONDS.
>> REAL 30 SECONDS.
>> A REAL 30 SECONDS.
>> I'M ONLY PERSON THAT'S BEATEN
THE NRA NATIONALLY.
I'M THE GUY THAT GOT THE BRADY
BILL PASSED, NUMBER ONE.
NUMBER TWO, WE INCREASE THAT HAD
BACKGROUND CHECK WHEN -- DURING
THE OBAMA/BIDEN ADMINISTRATION
AND I'M ALSO THE ONLY GUY THAT
GOT ASSAULT WEAPONS BANNED AND
THE NUMBER OF CLIPS IN A GUN
BAND, AND SO, FOLKS, LOOK, AND I
WOULD BUY BACK THOSE WEAPONS.
WE ALREADY STARTED TALKING ABOUT
THAT.
WE TRIED TO GET IT DONE.
I THINK IT CAN BE DONE, AND IT
SHOULD BE DEMANDED THAT WE DO IT
AND THAT'S A GOOD EXPENDITURE OF
MONEY AND LASTLY WE SHOULD HAVE
SMART GUNS.
NO GUN SHOULD BE ABLE TO SHOW
UNLESS YOUR BIOMETRIC MEASURE
CAN PULL THE TRIGGER.
IT'S WITHIN OUR TRYING DO THAT.
OUR ENEMY IS THE GUN
MANUFACTURERS, NOT THE NRA, THE
GUN MANUFACTURER.
>> THE NRA IS TAKING ORDERS FROM
THE GUN MANUFACTURERS.
>> LESTER HOLT HAS OUR NEXT
QUESTION.
>> TAKE IT AWAY.
>> A QUESTION FROM OUR VIEWERS.
WE PUT SOME SUGGESTIONS THAT
MAYBE THEY COULD SHARE ONE.
THIS IS FROM KATHLEEN IN OREGON.
MANY FEAR THE CURRENT
ADMINISTRATION HAS INFLICTED
IRREVOCABLE HARM ON OUR
GOVERNING INSTITUTIONS AND NORMS
AND THE PROCESS ON OUR
REPUTATION ABROAD.
THE QUESTION IS WHAT DO YOU SEE
AS IMPORTANT EARLY STEPS IN
REVERSING THE DAMAGE DONE, AND
WE'LL PUT THIS ONE TO SENATOR
BENNETT.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH, WHAT AN
EXCELLENT QUESTION.
FIRST OF ALL, WE HAVE TO RESTORE
OUR DEMOCRACY AT HOME.
THE REST OF THE WORLD IS LOCKING
FOR US IN LEADERSHIP.
WE HAVE A PRESIDENT WHO DOESN'T
BELIEVE IN THE RULE OF LAW OR
THE FREEDOM OF PRESS OR OR
INDEPENDENT JUDICIARY BUT
BELIEVES IN THE CORRUPTION THAT
HE'S BROUGHT TO WASHINGTON, D.C.
AND THAT IS WHAT WE HAVE TO
CHANGE AND THAT'S WHY EVERYBODY
IS UP HERE TONIGHT AND I
APPRECIATE THE FACT THAT THEY
ARE UP HERE FOR THAT REASON.
SECOND, WE'VE GOT -- WE'VE GOT
TO RESTORE THE RELATIONSHIPS
THAT HE'S DESTROYED WITH OUR
ALLIES, NOT JUST IN EUROPE.
HE FLEW TO THE G20 LAST NIGHT
AND ATTACKED JAPAN, GERMANY AND
A THIRD ALLY OF OURS WITHOUT
SAYING ANYTHING ABOUT NORTH
KOREA OR RUSSIA, AND -- AND WHEN
YOU'VE GOT A SITUATION WHERE YOU
HAVE A PRESIDENT WHO SAYS
SOMETHING HAPPENED IN THE STRAIT
OF HORMUZ AND THE WHOLE WORLD
DOESN'T KNOW WHETHER TO BELIEVE
IT OR NOT, THAT'S A HUGE PROBLEM
WHEN IT COMES TO THE NATIONAL
SECURITY OF THE UNITED STATES OF
AMERICA?
THIS IS A PERFECT TIME FOR ME TO
DO ANOTHER ONE OF THESE DOWN THE
LINE AND THIS IS WHAT THIS
QUESTION IS WHICH IS WHAT YOU'VE
GOT TO HAVE TO -- YOU'RE LIKELY
GOING HAVE TO RESET A
RELATIONSHIP BETWEEN AMERICA AND
ANOTHER COUNTRY OR ENTITY IF YOU
BECOME PRESIDENT BECAUSE OF
PERHAPS -- PERHAPS BECAUSE OF
SOME RELATIONSHIP YOU JUST
MENTIONED ABOUT PRESIDENT TRUMP.
WHAT'S THE FIRST RELATIONSHIP
YOU WOULD LIKE TO RESET AS
PRESIDENT AND I'LL GO DOWN THE
LINE STARTING WITH MISS
WILLIAMSON.
>> ONE OF MY FIRST PHONE CALLS
WOULD BE TO CALL THE EUROPEAN
LEADERS TO SAY WE'RE BACK
BECAUSE I TOTALLY UNDERSTAND HOW
IMPORTANT IT IS THAT THE UNITED
STATES BE PART OF THE WESTERN
ALLIANCE.
>> TRYING TO GET ONE OR TWO
WORDS HERE.
I HEAR YOU.
GOVERNOR HICK LOOPER.
>> I TALK ABOUT CONSTANT
ENGAGEMENT AND THE FIRST COUNTRY
I WOULD GO TO, AND I UNDERSTAND
THEY HAVE BEEN CHEATING AND
STEALING, WOULD BE CHINA.
>> OKAY.
>> WE HAVE TO DEAL WITH ALL THE
CHALLENGES OF THE GLOBE, WE'VE
GOT TO HAVE RELATIONSHIPS WITH
EVERYBODY.
>> WE'RE TRYING TO SQUEEZE IN A
COUPLE MORE THINGS.
>> CHINA, WE NEED TO COOPERATE
WITH THEM ON CLIMATE CHANGE AND
AI AND OTHER ISSUES.
>> THANKS FOR THE QUICK SGLES
MAYOR BUTTIGIEG.
>> WE DON'T KNOW WHO THE ALLIES
HE'LL PISS OFF WORSE BETWEEN NOW
AND THEN.
THE RELATIONSHIP WITH THE ENTIRE
WORLD NEEDS TO CHANGE AND IT
STARTS BY MODELING AMERICAN
VALUES AS HOME.
>> MR. VICE PRESIDENT, TRYING TO
BE QUICK.
>> WE KNOW NATO WILL FALL APART
IF HE'S ELECTED FOUR MORE YEARS,
THE SINGLE MOST CONSEQUENCE
ALLIANCE IN THE UNITED STATES.
>> SENATOR SANDERS.
>> IT'S NOT ONE COUNTRY.
I THINK IT'S REBUILDING TRUST IN
THE UNITED NATIONS AND
UNDERSTAND THAT WE CAN SOLVE
CONFLICTS WITHOUT WAR BUT WITH
DIPLOMACY.
>> SENATOR HARRIS.
>> ALL THE MEMBERS OF THE NATO
ALLIANCE.
>> SENATOR GILLIBRAND.
>> PRESIDENT TRUMP IS HELL BENT
ON STARTING A WAR WITH IRAN.
MY FIRST ACT WILL BE TO ENGAGE
IRAN, TO STABILIZE THE MIDDLE
EAST AND MAKE SURE WE DO NOT
START AN UNWANTED NEVER ENDING
WAR.
>> SENATOR BENNETT QUICKFULLY.
>> OUR EUROPEAN ALLIES AND EVERY
LATIN AMERICAN COUNTRY THAT'S
WILLING TO HAVE A CONVERSATION
ABOUT HOW TO DEAL WITH THE
REFUGEE CRISIS.
>> CONGRESSMAN SWALWELL.
>> FIRST ACT AS FOREIGN POLICY
WAS BREAKING UP WITH RUSSIA AND
MAKING UP WITH NATO.
>> THANK YOU ALL.
>> ONE QUESTION FOR VICE
PRESIDENT BIDEN TONIGHT.
YOU'VE MADE YOUR DECADES OF
EXPERIENCE IN FOREIGN POLICY A
PILLAR OF YOUR CAMPAIGN, BUT
WHEN THE TIME CAME TO SAY YES OR
NO ON ONE OF THE MOST
CONSEQUENTIAL FOREIGN POLICY
DECISIONS OF THE LAST CENTURY
YOU VOTED FOR THE IRAQ WAR.
YOU HAVE SINCE SAID YOU REGRET
THAT VOTE.
WHY SHOULD VOTERS TRUST YOUR
JUDGMENT WHEN IT COMES TO MAKING
A DECISION ABOUT TAKING THE
COUNTRY TO WAR THE NEXT TIME?
>> BECAUSE ONCE THE -- ONCE BUSH
BOOZE THAT HAD POWER WHAT
HAPPENED WAS HE GOT ELECTED
AFTER THAT I MADE THE PRESIDENT
TURNED TO ME AND SAID GET OUR
COMBAT TROOPS OUT OF IRAQ.
I WAS RESPONSIBLE FOR GETTING
150,000 COMBAT TROOPS OUT OF
IRAQ AROUND MY SON WAS ONE OF
THEM.
I ALSO THINK WE SHOULD NOT HAVE
COMBAT TROOPS IN AFGHANISTAN.
IT'S HONG OVERDUE.
IT SHOULD END, AND THIRDLY I
BELIEVE THAT YOU'RE NOT GOING TO
FIND ANYBODY WHO HAS PULLED
TOGETHER MORE OF OUR ALLIANCES
TO DEAL WITH WHAT IS THE REAL
STATED THREAT OUT THERE.
WE CAN'T GO IT ALONE IN TERMS OF
DEALING WITH TERRORISM SO I
WOULD ELIMINATE THE ACT THAT
ALLOWED US TO GO INTO WAR AND
NOT THE AMF AND MAKE SURE THAT
IT CAN ONLY BE USED FOR WHAT ITS
INTENT WAS, AND THAT IS TO GO
AFTER TERRORISTS BUT NEVER DO IT
ALONE.
THAT'S WHY WE HAVE TO REPAIR OUR
ALLIANCES.
WE PUT TOGETHER 56 COUNTRIES TO
MAKE SURE WE DEALT WITH ISIS IN
IRAQ AND OTHER PLACES.
THAT'S WHAT I WOULD DO.
THAT'S WHAT I HAVE DONE AND I
KNOW HOW TO DO IT.
>> SENATOR SANDERS, 30 SECONDS.
>> ONE OF THE DIFFERENCES IS
THAT JOE AND I HAVE IN OUR
RECORD IS JOE VOTED FOR THAT
WAR, I HELPED LEAD THE
OPPOSITION TO THAT WAR WHICH WAS
A TOTAL DISASTER.
SECOND OF ALL, I HELPED LEAD THE
EFFORT FOR THE FIRST TIME TO
UTILIZE THE WAR POWERS ACT TO
GET THE UNITED STATES OUT OF THE
SORTIE-LED INTERVENTION IN YEMEN
WHICH IS THE MOST HORRIFIC
HUMANITARIAN DISASTER ON EARTH,
AND THIRDLY, LET ME BE VERY
CLEAR, I WILL DO EVERYTHING I
CAN TO PREVENT A WAR WITH IRAN
WHICH WOULD BE FAR WORSE THAN
DISASTROUS WAR WITH IRAQ.
>> THANK YOU, GUYS.
YOU GET MORE TIME TO TALK BUT I
HAVE TO SNEAK IN ONE MORE BREAK.
WE'LL BE RIGHT BACK WITH MORE
DEBATE.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> WE ARE BACK IN MIAMI.
NOW EACH CANDIDATE WILL HAVE A
FINAL CHANCE TO MAKE THEIR CASE
TO THE VOTERS.
45 SECONDS EACH.
WE BEGIN WITH CONGRESSMAN
SWALWELL.
>> WE CAN'T BE A FORWARD LOOKING
PARTY IF WE LOOK TO THE PAST FOR
OUR LEADERSHIP.
I'M A CONGRESSMAN BUT ALSO A
FATHER OF A 2-YEAR-OLD AND AN
INFANT.
WHEN I'M NOT CHANGING DIAPERS,
I'M CHANGING WASHINGTON.
MOST OF THE TIME THE DIAPERS
SMELL BETTER.
I WENT TO CONGRESS AT 31 AND I
FOUND A WASHINGTON THAT DOESN'T
WORK FOR PEOPLE LIKE YOU AND ME.
IT'S MADE OF THE RICH AND THE
DISCONNECTED.
I WAS THE FIRST IN MY FAMILY TO
GO TO COLLEGE AND HAVE STUDENT
LOAN DEBT SO I'VE LED THE EFFORT
TO ELECT THE NEXT GENERATION OF
MEMBERS OF CONGRESS AND WE HAVE
A MOMENT TO SEIZE.
THIS IS A CAN-DO GENERATION.
THIS IS A GENERATION THAT WILL
END CLIMATE CHAOS.
SOLVE STUDENT LOAN DEBT AND THIS
IS THE GENERATION THAT WILL SAY
ENOUGH IS ENOUGH AND END GUN
VIOLENCE THIS.
GENERATION DEMANDS BOLD
SOLUTIONS.
THAT'S WHY I'M RUNNING FOR
PRESIDENT.
>> CONGRESSMAN, THANK YOU.
>> MISS WILLIAMSON, 45 SECONDS.
>> I'M SORRY WE HAVEN'T TALKED
MORE TONIGHT ABOUT HOW WE'RE
GOING TO BEAT DONALD TRUMP.
I HAVE AN IDEA ABOUT DONALD
TRUMP.
DONALD TRUMP IS NOT GOING TO BE
BEATEN JUST BY INSIDER POLITICS.
HE'S NOT GOING TO BE BEATEN BY
SOMEBODY WHO HAS A PLAN.
HE'S GOING TO BE BEATEN BY
SOMEBODY WHO HAS AN IDEA WHAT
THIS MAN HAS DONE.
THIS HAN HAS REACHED INTO THE
PSYCHE OF THE AMERICAN PEOPLE
AND HE'S HARNESSED FEAR FOR
POLITICAL PURPOSES.
SO, MR. PRESIDENT, IF YOU'RE
LISTENING, I WANT YOU TO HEAR
ME, PLEASE.
YOU HAVE HARNESSED FEAR FOR
POLITICAL PURPOSES AND ONLY LOVE
CAN CAST THAT OUT SO I, SIR, I
HAVE A FEELING YOU KNOW WHAT
YOU'RE DOING.
I'M GOING TO HARNESS LOVE FOR
POLITICAL PURPOSES.
I WILL MEET YOU ON THAT FIELD
AND, SIR, LOVE WILL WIN.
>> THANK YOU.
>> SENATOR BENNETT.
>> THANK YOU, THANK YOU.
>> MY MOM AND HER PARENTS CAME
TO THE UNITED STATES TO REBUILD
THEIR SHATTERED LIVES.
IN THE ONLY COUNTRY THAT THEY
COULD.
300 YEARS BEFORE THAT MY
PARENT'S FAMILY CAME SEARCHING
RELIGIOUS FREEDOM HERE.
THE ABILITY FROM ONE GENERATION
TO DO BETTER THAN THE NEXT IS
NOW SEVERELY AT RISK IN THE
UNITED STATES, ESPECIALLY AMONG
CHILDREN LIVING IN POVERTY LIKE
THE ONES I USED TO WORK FOR IN
THE DENVER PUBLIC SCHOOLS.
THAT'S WHY I'M RUNNING FOR
PRESIDENT.
I'VE HAD TWO TOUGH RACES IN
COLORADO BY BRINGING PEOPLE
TOGETHER AND NOT BY MAKING EMPTY
PROMISES AND I BELIEVE WE NEED
TO BUILD A BROAD COALITION OF
AMERICANS TO BEAT DONALD TRUMP
AND THE CORRUPTION IN WASHINGTON
AND BUILD A NEW ERA OF THE
AMERICAN DEMOCRACY AND AMERICAN
OPPORTUNITY.
THIS IS GOING TO BE HARD TO DO,
BUT IT'S WHAT OUR PARENTS WOULD
HAVE EXPECTED.
IT'S WHAT OUR KIDS DESERVE.
I HOPE YOU JOIN ME IN THIS
EFFORT.
THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU.
>> GOVERNOR HICKENLOOPER.
>> I'M A SMALL BUSINESS OWNER
WHO BROUGHT THAT SAME SCRAPPY
SPIRIT TO COLORADO, ONE OF THE
MOST PROGRESSIVE STATES IN
AMERICA.
WE STAND IN REPRODUCTIVE HEALTH
TO REDUCE TEENAGE ABORTION BY
64%.
WE'RE THE FIRST STATE TO
LEGALIZE MARIJUANA AND WE
TRANSFORMED OUR DEFICITS INTO
THE PROCESS.
WE PASSED UNIVERSAL BACKGROUND
CHECKS IN A PURPLE STATE AND GOT
TO NEAR UNIVERSAL HEALTHCARE
COVERAGE AND ATTACKED CLIMATE
CHANGE WITH THE TOUGHEST METHANE
REGULATIONS IN THE COUNTRY AND
FOR THE LAST THREE YEARS WE'VE
BEEN THE NUMBER ONE ECONOMY IN
AMERICA.
YOU DON'T NEED BIG GOVERNMENT TO
DO BIG THINGS.
I KNOW THAT BECAUSE I'M THE ONE
PERSON UP HERE WHO HAS ACTUALLY
DOESN'T BIG PROGRESSIVE THINGS
EVERYONE SELLS TALKING ABOUT.
IF WE TURN TOWARDS SOCIALISM, WE
RUN THE RISK OF HELPING TO
RE-ELECT THE WORST PRESIDENT IN
AMERICAN HISTORY.
>> THANK YOU, GOVERNOR.
>> SENATOR GILL BRAND, YOU HAVE
THE FLOOR FOR 45 SECONDS.
>> WOMEN IN AMERICA ARE ON FIRE.
WE'VE MARCHED, WE'VE ORGANIZED
AND WE'VE RUN FOR OFFICE AND WE
WON, BUT OUR RIGHTS ARE UNDER
ATTACK LIKE NEVER BEFORE BY
PRESIDENT TRUMP AND THE
REPUBLICANS WHO WANT TO REPEAL
"ROE V. WADE" WHICH IS WHY I
WENT TO THE FRONT LINES IN
GEORGIA TO FIGHT FOR THEM.
AS PRESIDENT I WILL TAKE ON THE
FIGHTS THAT NO ONE ELSE WILL.
I STOOD UP TO THE PENTAGON AND
REPEALED DON'T ISN'T DON'T TELL.
I STOOD UP TO THE BANKS AND
VOTED AGAINST THE BAILOUT TWICE.
I STOOD UP TO TRUMP MORE THAN
ANY OTHER SENATOR IN THE U.S.
SENATE AND I HAVE THE MOST
COMPREHENSIVE APPROACH FOR
GETTING MONEY OUT OF POLITICS
WITH PUBLICLY FUNDED ELECTIONS
TO DEAL WITH POLITICAL
CORRUPTION.
NOW IS NOT THE TIME TO PLAY IT
SAFE.
NOW IS NOT THE TIME TO BE AFRAID
OF FIRSTS.
WE NEED A PRESIDENT WHO WILL
TAKE ON THE BIG CHALLENGES EVEN
IF SHE STANDS ALONE.
JOIN ME IN FIGHTING FOR THIS.
>> SENATOR GILLIBRAND, THANK
YOU.
>> MR. YANG, YOU HAVE HAD A
SECONDS FOR YOUR CLOSING.
>> AFFIRMATIVE ACTION I WANT TO
THANK EVERYONE WHO PUT ME ON THE
STAGE TONIGHT.
I AM PROOF THAT OUR DEMOCRACY
STILL WORKS.
DEMOCRATS AND AMERICANS AROUND
THE COUNTRY HAVE ONE QUESTION
FOR THEIR NOMINEE AND THAT IS
WHO CAN BEAT DONALD TRUMP IN
2020.
THAT IS THE RIGHT QUESTION, AND
THE RIGHT CANDIDATE TO BEAT
DONALD TRUMP WILL BE SOLVING THE
PROBLEMS THAT GOT DONALD TRUMP
ELECTED AND WILL HAVE A VISION
OF A TRICKLE UP ECONOMY THAT'S
ALREADY DRAWING THOUSANDS OF
DISAFFECTED TRUMP VOTERS,
CONSERVATIVES AND LIBERTARIANS
AS WELL AS DEMOCRATS AND
PROGRESS I WAS, I AM THAT CANNED
DAY.
I CAN BUILD A MUCH BROADER
COALITION TO BEAT DONALD TRUMP.
IT'S NOT LEFT.
IT IS NOT RIGHT.
IT IS FORWARD AND THAT'S WHERE I
I'LL TAKE THE COUNTRY IN 2020.
>> MR. YANG, THANK YOU.
>> SENATOR HARRIS, THE FLOOR IS
YOURS.
>> THANK YOU.
I JUST WANT TO LEAVE YOU WITH A
COUPLE OF THINGS.
ONE, WE NEED A NOMINEE WHO HAS
THE ABILITY TO PROSECUTE THE
CASE AGAINST FOUR MORE YEARS OF
DONALD TRUMP AND I WILL DO THAT.
SECOND, THIS ELECTION IS ABOUT
YOU.
THIS IS ABOUT YOUR HOPES AND
YOUR DREAMS AND YOUR FEARS AND
WHAT WAKES YOU UP AT 3:00 IN THE
MORNING, AND THAT'S WHY I HAVE
WHAT I CALL AL 3:00 A.M. AGENDA
THAT'S ABOUT EVERYTHING FROM
WHAT WE NEED TO DO TO DELIVER
HEALTHCARE TO HOW YOU WILL BE
ABLE TO PAY THE BILLS BY THE END
OF THE MONTH, AND WHEN I THINK
ABOUT WHAT OUR COUNTRY NEEDS,
YOU PROMISE YOU I WILL BE A
PRESIDENT WHO LEADS WITH A SENSE
OF DIGNITY, WITH HONESTY,
SPEAKING THE TRUTH AND GIVING
THE AMERICAN FAMILY ALL THAT
THEY NEED TO GET THROUGH THE END
OF THE MONTH IN A WAY THAT
ALLOWS THEM TO PROSPER SO I HOPE
TO EARN YOUR SUPPORT.
PLEASE JOIN US AT
KAMALAHARRIS.ORG.
>> SENATOR, THANK YOU.
>> MAYOR BUTTIGIEG, 45 SECONDS.
>> NOTHING ABOUT POLITICS IS
THEORETICAL TO ME.
I'VE HAD THE EXPERIENCE OF
WRITING A LETTER TO MY FAMILY,
PUTTING IT IN AN ENVELOPE MARKED
JUST IN CASE AND LEAVING IT
WHERE THEY WOULD KNOW WHERE TO
FIND IT IN CASE I DIDN'T COME
BACK FROM AFGHANISTAN.
I'VE HAD THE EXPERIENCE OF
INCOME A MARRIAGE THAT EXISTS BY
THE GRACE OF A SINGLE VOTE ON
THE U.S. SUPREME COURT.
I HAVE THE EXPERIENCE OF GUIDING
A COMMUNITY WHERE THE PER CAPITA
INCOME WAS BELOW $20,000 WHEN I
TOOK OFFICE INTO A BRIGHTER
FUTURE.
I'M RUNNING BECAUSE THE
DECISIONS WE MAKE IN THE NEXT
THREE OR FOUR YEARS WILL DECIDE
HOW THE NEXT 30 OR 40 GO AND
WHEN I GET TO THE CURRENT AGE OF
THE CURRENT PRESIDENT IN THE
YEAR 205 5I WANT TO BE ABLE TO
LOOK BACK ON THESE YEARS AND SAY
MY GENERATION DELIVERED CLIMATE
SOLUTIONS, RACIAL EQUALITY AND
AN END TO ENDLESS WAR.
HELP ME DELIVER THAT NEW
GENERATION TO WASHINGTON BEFORE
IT'S TOO LATE.
>> THANK YOU.
>> SENATOR SANDERS, 25 SECONDS.
THE FLOOR IS YOURS.
>> I SUSPECT PEOPLE OF THE
COUNTRY WHO ARE WATCHING THIS
DEBATE ARE SAYING THESE ARE THE
PEOPLE, THEY HAVE GREAT IDEAS,
BUT HOW COME NOTHING REALLY
CHANGES?
HOW COME FOR THE LAST 45 YEARS
WAGES HAVE BEEN STAGNANT FOR THE
MIDDLE CLASS?
HOW COME WE HAVE THE HIGHEST
RATE OF CHILDHOOD POVERTY?
HOW COME 45 MILLION PEOPLE STILL
HAVE STUDENT DEBT?
HOW COME THREE PEOPLE ARE MORE
WEALTHY THAN THE BOTTOM HALF OF
AMERICA AND HERE IS THE ANSWER?
NOTHING WILL CHANGE UNLESS WE
HAVE THE GUTS TO TAKE ON WALL
STREET, THE INSURANCE INDUSTRY,
THE PHARMACEUTICAL INDUSTRY, THE
MILITARY INDUSTRIAL COMPLEX AND
THE FOSSIL FUEL INDUSTRY.
IF WE DON'T HAVE THE GUTS TO
TAKE THEM ON, WE'LL CONTINUE TO
HAVE PLANS.
WE'LL CONTINUE TO HAVE THOUGHTS
AND THE RICH WILL GET RICHER AND
EVERYBODY ELSE WILL BE
STRUGGLING.
>> THANK YOU, SENATOR.
>> AND LASTLY WE'LL HEAR FROM
VICE PRESIDENT BIDEN.
SIR, YOU HAVE 45 SECONDS.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
I'M RUNNING TO LEAD THIS COUNTRY
BECAUSE I THINK IT'S IMPORTANT
TO RESTORE THE SOUL THE NATION
OF THE PRESIDENT.
THIS PRESIDENT HAS RIPPED IT
OUT.
THE ONLY PRESIDENT WHO HAS
EQUATED RACIST AND WHITE
SUPREMACISTS WITH OTHER DEESE
END PEOPLE AND HE'S THE ONLY
PRESIDENT WHO HAS EMBRACED
DICTATORS AND THUMBED THEIR NOSE
AT YOU'RE ALLY.
I'M SECONDLY RUNNING FOR
PRESIDENT BECAUSE I THINK WE
HAVE TO RESTORE THE BACKBONE OF
AMERICA.
THE POOR AND HARD WORKING MIDDLE
CLASS PEOPLE YOU CAN'T DO THAT
WITHOUT REPLACING THEM WITH THE
DIGNITY THEY ONCE HAD.
LASTLY WE'VE GOT TO UNITE THE
UNITED STATES OF AMERICA AS MUCH
AS ANYBODY SAYS WE CAN'T.
IF WE DO THERE'S NOT A SINGLE
THING THAT THE PEOPLE CAN'T DO.
THIS IS THE UNITED STATES OF
AMERICA.
WE CAN DO ANYTHING IF WE'RE
TOGETHER, TOGETHER.
SO GOD BLESS YOU ALL AND MAY GOD
PROTECT OUR TROOPS.
>> VICE PRESIDENT BIDEN, THANK
YOU.
>> WE WANT TO THANK OUR
CANDIDATES.
WE'VE HAD TWO NIGHTS OF SPIRITED
DEBATE ON A RANGE OF ISSUES.
20 CANDIDATES IN ALL.
THANK ALL OF THE CANDIDATES LAST
NIGHT AND TONIGHT.
>> THANKS FOR STICKING YOUR NECK
OUT LIKE THIS.
>> I WOULD ALSO LIKE TO THANK
THE AUDIENCE FOR COMPLETELY
IGNORING OUR SUGGESTIONS.
>> THANKS TO THE DEMOCRATIC
NATIONAL COMMITTEE AND THE
DEMOCRATIC PARTY.
>> AND, OF COURSE, THANK YOU TO
EVERYONE HERE FOR HOST IS US
HERE AND OUR TERRIFIC AUDIENCE.
FOR SAVANNAH, JOSE, CHUCK AND
RACHEL, I'M LESTER HOLT.
GOOD NIGHT, EVERYONE, FROM
MIAMI.
♪
EVERYONE HERE FOR HOST IS US
>> WHAT A DEBATE NIGHT.
WELCOME BACK TO OUR SPECIAL
COVERAGE OF THE SECOND NIGHT OF
THE FIRST DEMOCRATIC DEBATE
RIGHT HERE ON "NBC NEWS NOW."
THERE YOU HAVE IT, TWO NIGHTS,
20 CANDIDATES IT.
THE CANDIDATES ARE WALKING OFF
THE STAGE AS WE SPEAK.
JOE BIDEN, BERNIE SANDERS,
KAMALA HARRIS, PETE BOURGET WERE
IN THE FRONT.
THEY WERE THE FRONT-RUNNERS
COMING INTO TONIGHT.
THEY TALKED ABOUT RACE.
IMMIGRATION, POLICE VIOLENCE,
HEALTH CARE, CLIMATE CHANGE, GUN
CONTROL, JUST TO NAME A FEW.
AND THOSE CANDIDATES TRIED TO
STICK THEIR CLAIM ON THE ISSUES
AND MANY OF THEM TRIED TO
INTRODUCE THEMSELVES TO
AMERICANS WHO ARE MEETING THEM
FOR THE FIRST TIME TONIGHT.
HERE ARE SOME OF THE HIGHLIGHTS.
>> IT'S TIME FOR CHANGE, REAL
CHANGE.
>> I WAS 6 YEARS OLD WHEN A
PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE CAME TO
THE CALIFORNIA DEMOCRATIC
CONVENTION AND SAID, IT'S TIME
TO PASS THE TORCH TO A NEW
GENERATION OF AMERICANS.
THAT CANDIDATE WAS THEN SENATOR
JOE BIDEN.
JOE BIDEN WAS RIGHT WHEN HE SAID
IT WAS TIME TO PA -- TO PASS THE
TORCH TO A NEW GENERATION OF
AMERICANS, AND HE IS STILL RIGHT
TODAY.
>> AMERICA DOES NOT WANT TO
WITNESS A FOOD FIGHT, THEY WANT
TO KNOW HOW WE PUT FOOD ON THEIR
TABLE.
>> IF YOUR GOVERNMENT PLAN WOULD
PROVIDE FOR UNDOCUMENTED
IMMIGRANTS?
>> LADIES AND GENTLEMEN, WE
DON'T HAVE A HEALTH CARE SYSTEM
IN THE UNITED STATES, WE HAVE A
SICKNESS CARE SYSTEM IN THE
UNITED STATES.
AND I WILL ENSURE THAT THE
MICROPHONE THAT THE PRESIDENT OF
THE UNITED STATES HOLDS IN HER
HAND IS USED IN A WAY THAT IS
ABOUT RESPECTING THE VALUES OF
OUR COUNTRY.
>> FOR A PARTY THAT
ASSOCIATESIST WITH CHRISTIAN --
CHRISTIANITY, TO SAY THAT GOD
WOULD SMILE ON THE DIVISION OF
FAMILIES AT THE HANDS OF FEDERAL
AGENTS THAT GOD WOULD CONDON
PUTTING KIDS IN CAGES.
>> IF YOU FORCIBLY TAKE A CHILD
FROM A PARENT'S ARMS YOU ARE
KIDNAPPING THEM.
>> WITH THIS BORDER SECURITY,
NOT A WALL, THE BORDER OF THE
UNITED STATES HAS BEEN TURNED IN
TO A SYMBOL OF HOSTILITY.
WE NEED TO MAKE A CHANGE.
>> I'M DETERMINED TO BRING ABOUT
A DAY WHEN A WHITE PERSON
DRIVING A VEHICLE AND A BLACK
PERSON DRIVING A VEHICLE, WHEN
THEY SEE A POLICE OFFICER
APPROACHING, FEELS THE EXACT
SAME THING.
>> WE WILL GET TO YOU, HANG ON.
>> I WOULD LIKE TO SPEAK ON THE
ISSUE OF RACE.
AND I'M GOING THE NOW DIRECT
THIS AT VICE PRESIDENT ABIDE
KNOW.
UM, I -- I DO NOT BELIEVE YOU
ARE A RACIST AND I BELIEVE YOU
WHEN YOU COMMIT YOURSELF TO THE
IMPORTANCE OF FINDING COMMON
GROUND.
BUT I ALSO BELIEVE AND IT'S
PERSONAL, AND IT WAS HURTFUL, TO
HEAR YOU TALK ABOUT THE
REPUTATIONS OF TWO UNITED STATES
SENATORS WHO BUILT THEIR
REPUTATIONS AND CAREER ON THE
SEGRAGATION OF RACE IN THE
COUNTRY.
>> I DID NOT PRAISE RACISTS.
>> DO YOU AGREE TODAY, DO YOU
AGREE TODAY, THAT YOU WERE WRONG
TO OPPOSE BUSSING IN AMERICA
THEN?
>> NO, I DID NOT OPPOSE BUSSING
IN AMERICA.
WHAT I OPPOSED IS BUSSING
ORDERED BY THE DEPARTMENT OF
EDUCATION.
THAT IS WHAT I OPPOSED.
I DID NOT OPPOSE --
>> IT WAS A FAILURE OF STATES
TO -- I WAS PART OF THE SECOND
CLASS TO INTEGRATE BERKELEY,
CALIFORNIA PUBLIC SCHOOLS TWO
DECADES OUT OF BROWN--V-BOARD OF
EDUCATION.
>> IT WAS A LOCAL DECISION.
>> THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT --
THAT'S WHY WE HAVE THE VOTING
RIGHTS ACT AND THE CIVIL RIGHTS
ACT.
THAT'S WHY WE NEED TO PASS THE
EQUALITY ACT AND THE E.R.A,
THERE'S MOMENTS IN HISTORY WHERE
STATES FAIL TO PRESERVE THE
CIVIL RIGHTS OF OUR PEOPLE.
WHO DO YOU WANT WHEN THAT DOOR
CLOSES TO BE SITTING BEHIND THE
DESK?
TO FIGHT FOR WOMEN'S RIGHTS?
I HAVE BEEN THE FIERCEST
ADVOCATE FOR WOMEN'S
REPRODUCTIVE FREEDOM FOR OVER A
DECADE.
>> IT WOULD SPEED US UP ON
CLIMATE CHANGE, IF YOU GET YOUR
BOOT OFF OF PEOPLE'S THROATS, WE
WILL HAVE CLIMATE CHANGE FOR
QUICKLY.
>> IF MORE GUNS MADE US SAFER,
WE WOULD BE THE SAFEST COUNTRY
ON EARTH.
IT DOESN'T WORK THAT WAY.
>> HERE TO HELP ME DIVE IN TO
ALL OF THOSE ISSUES WE HEARD
TONIGHT ON THE DEBATE STAGE.
WE HAVE NANCY SANTIAGO, AND
ZERLINA MAXWELL.
WHO DO YOU THINK WON THE DEBATE
TONIGHT, ALEX?
>> IT WAS KAMALA HARRIS AND THAT
EXCHANGE SHE HAD WITH JOE BIDEN
WAS SOMETHING THAT WE WILL BE
DISCUSSED.
IT'S NOT EVEN OVER, KAMALA'S
CAMPAIGN IS SAYING THAT BIDEN
NEEDS TO APOLOGIZE.
AND THERE'S AN OPEN QUESTION,
BIDEN IN THEIR DEFENDED HIS
PASSED VIEWS.
THAT IS NOT CLEAR, THEY ARE
GOING TO KEEP PUSHING HIM TO
CHANGE HIS POSITION.
>> DO YOU THINK HE WAS RIGHT TO
DOUBLE DOWN WHEN SHE HELD HIS
FEET TO THE FIRE?
>> NO, HE WAS WRONG.
HE IS WRONG.
AND SHE ARTICULATED
FUNDAMENTALLY A REALLY IMPORTANT
DEBATE IN THE DEMOCRATIC PARTY,
WHICH IS THE ROLE OF THE FEDERAL
GOVERNMENT WHEN IT STEPS IN.
WHEN THE STATES ARE NOT DOING
WHAT THE SUPREME COURT SAYS IT
SHOULD DO, RIGHT?
SO, HER POINT ON THE SUBSTANCE
IS CORRECT.
SO, HE WAS WRONG IN THAT MOMENT
AND WRONG TO DOUBLE DOWN.
>> AND THEN YOU WERE THERE LAST
NIGHT IN MIAMI CORRECT?
>> THAT'S RIGHT.
>> ONE THING I COULD NOT HELP
BUT NOTICE WAS THE WAY THAT
IDENTITY POLITICS WAS TREATED
TONIGHT VERSE LAST NIGHT.
TO ME, AND TELL ME IF I'M WRONG,
IT FELT LIKE LAST NIGHT WAS MORE
ABOUT WHO I AM.
AND TONIGHT, IT WAS MORE OF WHAT
I HAVE SPECIALSED.
YOU SAW THE CANDIDATES CONNECT
ON THINGS LIKE HEALTH CARE.
I HAD A SICK DAD OR A TERMINAL
ILLNESS AND IT SEEMED TO BE
ABOUT THE MARROW OF THEIR
EXPERIENCES.
DO YOU THINK THAT AFFECTED WHY
THAT MOMENT WITH KAMALA WAS SO
POWERFUL?
>> I DON'T THINK IT WAS THAT PER
SAY FOR ME, THERE WAS IDENTITY
POLITICS LAST NIGHT.
AND IT WAS AROUND THE
IMMIGRATION PIECE.
IT'S NOT BLACK AND WHITE, RIGHT?
IT'S A VERY DIFFERENT THING.
SO IN THAT RESPECT, THAT WAS A
HEATED EXCHANGE BETWEEN -- SO,
WE THINK ABOUT THAT PIECE, IT'S
JUST PLAYING OUT DIFFERENTLY.
WHAT I THINK THE PROBLEM, OR THE
MISSED OPPORTUNITY FOR BIDEN
WAS, HE HAD A CHANCE TO MODEL
FOR AMERICA HOW TO SAY, I AM
SORRY, LET'S FIX THIS.
BECAUS -- BECAUSE SHE SAID, I
WAS HURT PERSONALLY.
IT WAS HIS MOMENT TO SHOW HOW
YOU COME TOGETHER, HE SAID IT,
I'M THE BRIDGE.
DO THAT, AND THAT DIDN'T HAPPEN
IN THE EXCHANGE.
>> I THINK SHE SPOKE TORE OTHER
BLACK PEOPLE TOO.
SAYING IT WAS HURTFUL.
WE ARE JUST SAYING THAT YOU
KNOW, YOUR WORDS HAD AN IMPACT
IN A NEGATIVE WAY, BECAUSE IT
SEEMED THAT YOU DID NOT
UNDERSTAND WHAT YOU WERE SAY IN
THE MOMENT.
YOU ARE COMPLIMENTING, NOT
PRAISING, SPECIFICALLY TO BE
CLEAR, BUT SAYING SOMETHING
COMPLIMENTARY ABOUT
SEGREGATIONIST, SEEMS LIKE
SOMETHING YOU DO NOT SAY IF YOU
WANT TO WIN THE NOMINATION.
>> WHAT I THINK WAS POWERFUL WAS
WHEN SHE SAID, I DO NOT THINK
YOU ARE A RACIST.
FOR US IN THE FIELD, WE HEAR
THAT WORD BEING THROWN AROUND,
AND AUTOMATICALLY YOU ARE A
RACIST IF YOU VOTED FOR TRUMP.
HEY, TO SAY PLAINLY, I THINK I
BELIEVE I KNOW WHAT IS IN YOUR
HEART, BUT THIS IS AN ISSUE
ABOUT POLICY.
AND THAT IS WHY WE ARE ALL
STANDING HERE ON THE DEBATE
STAGE.
DO YOU THINK, HOWEVER, THAT SHE
IS KEEPING THE ISSUE AROUND, YOU
SAID THE WORD PRAISE, PRAISING
THE SEGREGATIONIST.
HE SAID THAT HE DID NOT DO.
>> HE SAID HE DID NOT DO THAT.
>> DO YOU THINK, SHE AND SENATOR
BOOKER ARE KEEPING THE ISSUE
ALIVE FOR POLITICAL REASONS?
>> SURE, YEAH.
ALEX, YEAH, OKAY, OKAY.
>> YEAH.
YEAH, YEAH.
>> ONLY ONE OF THEM CAN BE
PRESIDENT, IF YOU ARE GOING TO
PROSECUTE THAT CASE.
DOESN'T MEAN THE FEELINGS ARE
NOT SINCERE AND THAT SHE WAS NOT
OFFENDED OR HURT.
SHE IS GOING TO KEEP PUSHING
THIS, BECAUSE SHE WANTS TO SHOW
THAT SHE CAN PROSECUTE THE CASE
AGAINST FRUMP -- AGAINST TRUMP
AND THE FRONT-RUNNER.
>> LOOKING LIKE SOMEBODY THAT
WANTS TO WIN THE ELECTION.
SHE DID NOT COME IN TO GO UP IN
THE POLLS A BIT.
SHE CAME OUT WITH THE
CONVICTION, IT WAS LIKE, IN THE
EYES.
SHE HAD CONVICTION, SHE LOOKED
DIRECTLY IN THE CAMERA AND SAID
THINGS, YOU KNOW, WITH SUCH
CONFIDENCE.
WHEN I'M PRESIDENT, WHEN I'M IN
THE OVAL OFFICE.
SHE WILL HOLD THE MIC IN HER
HAND.
IT'S SUBTLE.
BUT, YOU KNOW, I DON'T KNOW IF
YOU FEEL THIS WAY AS WELL.
-- THE FIRST AFRICAN-AMERICAN
WOMAN.
>> RIGHT.
?
I HAVE NOT --
>> THAT WAS THE '90s.
>> AND I DID NOT WATCH THE
DEBATE.
THIS IS THE FIRST TIME IN MY,
YOU KNOW, ADULT LIFE I HAVE SEEN
A BLACK WOMAN --
>> SO SENATOR HARRIS IS THE
FIRST AFRICAN-AMERICAN FEMALE
SENATOR, BUT BACK IN THE '90s --
>> THERE WERE THREE BLACK WOMEN
THAT EVER HAD RUN.
THIS IS THE FIRST TIME I HAVE
SEEN A BLACK WOMAN ON THE STAGE
AT THIS LEVEL.
THAT THEY ARE TAKING IT TO THE
FRONT-RUNNER.
NOT JUST THE FRONT-RUNNER, TO
THE FORMER VICE PRESIDENT.
SHE IS GOING TO WIN OVER A LOT
OF FANS THAT, AGAIN, GOING BACK
TO THE AP POLL THAT I CITED.
>> SO, NANCY, I HAVE TO GET YOU
TO WEIGH IN ON THIS FOR ME.
WHY WAS THAT MOMENT WITH KAMALA
READ SO DIFFERENTLY THEN THE
MOMENT WITH BETHEL YESTERDAY,
WHEN HE WAS SPEAKING TODAY?
>> IT'S ONE OF THOSE MOMENTS WE
HAVE BEEN USING THE WORD
APPROPRIATION QUITE A BIT.
IT WAS THAT MOMENT, OF COME ON,
LET'S NOT DO THAT MOMENT.
>> THIS IS BROADCAST ON
TELEMUNDO -- HE WAS SPEAKING
SPANISH TO A LATINO AUDIENCE.
>> THAT WAS RUMOR THAT WE WERE
SEEING AND JULIAN HAD NOTHING TO
LOSE AND BETO DRUG IT OUT OF
HIM.
AND HERE ARE THE POLICIES THAT
YOU ARE NOT ANSWERING TO, THAT
YOU ARE NOT TALKING ABOUT HOW
YOU ARE GOING TO CHANGE.
AND NO ONE TONIGHT MENTIONED
1325.
>> ONLY WITH HIM YESTERDAY.
>> AND NOTHING HAPPENED TODAY.
>> AND 1325 FOR THE AUDIENCE IS
ASYLUM.
>> IT'S WHAT MAKES IT ILLEGAL TO
GET ACROSS A BORDER WITHOUT A
DOCUMENT.
THIS IS THE STRUGGLE.
SO, THAT IS WHAT IS CAUSING IT
AND MAKE NO MISTAKE ABOUT IT,
NOBODY BROUGHT UP THE RAIDS THAT
ARE PENDING.
MY HOMETOWN IS ABOUT TO BE ONE
OF THE LARGEST STAGING SITES AND
THEY ARE COMING.
NO ONE BROUGHT IT UP.
I THINK WHAT HAPPENED, SPEAKING
SPANISH IS NICE.
DOING SOMETHING MATTERS.
AND THAT IS WHAT I THINK REALLY
GOT IN HIS CRAW LAST NIGHT AND
THAT'S WHAT WE SAW.
THERE WAS A FIRE IN THE BELLY
THAT I HAD NEVER SEEN, THAT I
WAS EXCITED TO SEE.
AND WHEN YOU SEE EVERYONE
GOOGLING HAD HIM, WHERE DID YOU
COME FROM?
I THINK WE WILL HAVE THE SAME
REACTION SENATOR HARRIS, IT WAS
A DIFFERENT SENATOR THAT WAS ON
STAGE.
>> THE GOOGLE SEARCH FOR KAMALA
HARRIS INCREASED BY 500% AND SHE
WAS THE TOP SEARCH OF ALL OF THE
CANDIDATES.
WE WERE TALKING ABOUT IT IN
PREDEBATE SHOW, SENATOR SANDERS.
DID HE HURT OR HELP HIS LEAD
TONIGHT?
>> HE CLEARLY CAME IN NOT
WANTING TO ENGAGE BIDEN.
THERE WAS SPECULATION THAT HE
WAS GOING TO TAKE ON BIDEN AND
ON ONE OF THE SIGNATURE ISSUES A
LAY-UP FOR BERNIE ABOUT THE IRAQ
WAR VOTE, WHERE BERNIE OF WAS IN
THE CONGRESS AND VOTED THE
OPPOSITE WAY, THEY NOTED IT,
DISAGREED AND MOVED ON.
HE DID NOT WANT TO GET IN A
BOXING MATCH WITH BIDEN.
>> WAS HE SCARED?
>> WE WOULD HAVE TO ASK HIM.
I THINK HE CAME IN TO TALK ABOUT
HIS ISSUES AND NOT TRY TO GET IN
A SLUGGING MATCH WITH BIDEN.
>> SPEAKING OF ASKING THE
CANDIDAT
CANDIDATES.
I WANT TO DO THAT JUST NOW.
WITH VONN HILLIARD, HE IS THERE
HAD IN THE SPIN ROOM, WHO HAVE
YOU BEEN A I BELIEVE TO TALK TO
TONIGHT?
I SEE THE CAMERAS MOVING.
THERE HE IS.
HE IS PULLING -- OKAY --
>> THERE'S TWO SENATORS RIGHT
THERE ON THE STAGE.
SENATOR BERNIE SANDERS AND
KAMALA HARRIS AND THEY RAISED
THEIR HANDS AND TALKED ABOUT
ELIMINATING PRIVATE HEALTH
INSURANCE, FROM YOUR EXPERIENCE
IN THE SENATE AND WORKING ON
LEGISLATION, WHAT IS IT THAT
THEY ARE MISSING IN THE
EQUATION?
>> FIRST OF ALL, THEY WERE
HONEST ABOUT WHAT WAS IN THE
BILL, THAT IS GOOD, THERE'S
PEOPLE THAT SAY, IT DOES NOT
ELIMINATE PRIVATE INSURANCE.
IT SOMEHOW IS LIKE AUSTRALIA.
WHERE IT'S A GOOD SYSTEM.
WHERE YOU HAVE PUBLIC AND
PRIVATE INSURANCE.
THAT IS POINT ONE.
BUT GOOD FOR HONESTY AND WHAT
THEY ARE MISSING, THERE'S A LOT
OF PEOPLE, AS BERNIE SAID
TONIGHT, THERE'S A LOT OF PEOPLE
THAT HATE PRIVATE INSURANCE.
THAT IS TRUE.
I HEAR FROM A LOT OF PEOPLE LIKE
THAT.
AND THERE'S A LOT OF PEOPLE THAT
LIKE THE INSURANCE THAT THEY
HAVE AND WANT TO KEEP IT AND I
THINK, IF THE OBJECTIVE IS TO
GET TO UNIVERSAL HEALTH CARE
COVERAGE AS QUICKLY AS WE CAN,
GIVING PEOPLE AN OPTION TO
CHOOSE FOR THEIR FAMILY, I THINK
IS ABSOLUTELY GOING TO BE THE
FASTEST WAY.
I THINK WE WILL BE DEAD BEFORE
WE TAKE IT AWAY FROM PEOPLE THAT
ARE HOLDING IT AT HOME OR WITH
THEIR FAMILY.
>> THERE'S A SURPRISE FROM
SENATOR HARRIS RAISING HER HAND
FOR THE RESPONSE AND I THINK
THERE'S A CONCERN, WHAT IMPACT
DOES IT HAVE?
>> I WAS NOT SURPRISED.
I THINK SHE IS FOR IT AND SHE
SAID THAT SHE WANTS IT.
IN STATES LIKE COLORADO, AND
OTHER STATES, WHERE, THAT WE
NEED TO WIN THE MAJORITY IN THE
SENATE, WE ARE GOING TO HAVE A
HARD TIME IF THE POSITION IS
THAT WE ARE GOING TO TAKE
INSURANCE AWAY FROM 180MILLION
PEOPLE.
REMEMBER WHAT HAPPENED AFTER THE
AFFORDABLE CARE ACT.
PRESIDENT OBAMA SAID IF YOU LIKE
YOUR INSURANCE, YOU CAN KEEP IT.
A RELATIVELY SMALL NUMBER OF
PEOPLE LOST IT BECAUSE OF THE
WAY THAT THE SYSTEM CAME IN TO
PLACE.
AND THAT WAS A POLITICAL
DISASTER.
AND IT CONTINUES TO BE ONE
TODAY.
SO, IMAGINE A SITUATION WHERE,
WHAT WE ARE SAYING TO PEOPLE IS,
IF YOU LIKE YOUR INSURANCE, WE
ARE GOING TO TAKE IT AWAY FROM
YOU.
THAT DOESN'T SEEM TO BE WHAT WE
SHOULD BE ARGUING.
WHAT WE SHOULD BE ARGUING IS FOR
UNIVERSAL HEALTH CARE COVERAGE.
AND WE CAN ACHIEVE THAT THROUGH
A PUBLIC OPTION AND I THINK WE
CAN WITH ACHIEVE IT QUICKLY.
AND WITH MUCH LESS DISRUPTION,
AND BY THE WAY, EVERYBODY WHO
HAS PRIVATE INSURANCE AND WHO
HATES IT NO LONGER NEEDS IT,
THEY CAN COME ON TO MEDICARE-X.
>> THE CONVERSATION ABOUT
PASSING THE TORCH TO THE NEXT
GENERATION.
DO YOU BELIEVE THAT TWO MEN IN
THE MIDDLE OF THAT STAGE SHOULD
PASS THE TORCH?
>> I THINK IT'S TIME, I ANSWERED
BERNIE'S QUESTION HE ASKED AT
THE END, 40 YEARS OF IMMOBILITY
IN THE COUNTRY AND WE HAVE NOT
FIGURED OUT HOW TO ADDRESS IT
AND IT'S TIME TO CHANGE THAT.
I AGREE WITH THAT.
THANK YOU FOR HAVING ME.
>> GOOD TO SEE YOU.
>> DID SENATOR BENNETT CONSIDER
HIMSELF PART OF THE NEW
GENERATION OF LEADERSHIP?
OKAY.
I THINK WE LOST HIM TO THE SPIN
ROOM, WHICH IS WHERE HE OUGHT TO
BE, GETTING MORE ANSWERS FROM
THE CANDIDATES.
AND THANK YOU FOR WATCHING STAY
TUNED WE ARE JUST GOING TO TAKE
A VERY SHORT BREAK, WE WILL BE
RIGHT HERE WITH SPECIAL COVERAGE
OF THE FIRST PRESIDENT AAL
DEBATE ON NBC NEWS NOW.
STAY TUNED.
♪ ♪
>>> THANKS FOR JOINING US HERE
ON NBC NEWS NOW AND ONE OF THE
BIG ISSUES THAT THE CANDIDATES
HIT EARLY WAS THEIR PLANS FOR
HEALTH CARE.
WE ALSO HERD A LOT ABOUT THAT,
FROM CANDIDATE SWALWELL WHO IS
TALKING TO VONN.
LET US KNOW WHAT SWALWELL SAID,
HE IS STANDING BEHIND YOU.
I WANT TO ASK ABOUT THE QUESTION
HE PLACED TO JOE BIDEN ABOUT
TORCH BEARERS.
CAN WE ASK ABOUT THAT?
>> YEAH, CONGRESSMAN SWALWELL,
THE QUESTION OFF THE BAT WAS THE
IDEA OF PASSING THE TORCH.
WHY COME OFF WITH THAT QUESTION?
>> THERE'S A URGENCY TO THE
ISSUES OF THIS GENERATION.
STUDENT DEBT, I HAVE IT AND 40
MILLION PEOPLE HAVE IT.
WE NEED SOMEBODY THAT WILL DO IT
NOW.
GUN VIOLENCE, SEND MY KIDS TO
SCHOOL, WORRY ABOUT THEIR
SAFETY.
WE CANNOT WAIT FOR PEOPLE TO
EVOLVE TO THE ISSUES.
WE NEED SOMEONE THAT UNDERSTANDS
THE URGENCY, WE NEED TO INVEST
IN A CLIMATE CHANGE DEAL.
JOE BIDEN OF WAS RIGHT.
I'M STANDING ON THE STAGE AS
SOMEBODY WHO IS READY TO RECEIVE
THE TORCH.
>> DID YOU MAKE THE ARGUMENT A
THAT SANDERS AND BIDEN HAD THE
HISTORY TO LEND CREDIBILITY AT
THIS MOMENT IN TIME TO WHAT
POLICIES SHOULD BE PRESSED
FORWARD?
>> I HAPPEN TO THINK THAT THE
ISSUES ARE SO URGENT A THAT WE
CANNOT COUNT ON PEOPLE WHO HAVE
BEEN AROUND FOR DOZENS OF
DECADES AS THESE PROBLEMS HAVE
BEEN AROUND.
WE NEED NEW EYES ON THE PROBLEM
SET AND NEW ENERGY TO SOLVE THEM
AND I'M READY TO DO THAT.
>> THE QUESTION IS, THERE'S 20
PEOPLE ON THE STAGE, YOU ARE NOT
THE ONLY ONE IN YOUR GENERATION,
IF I MAY, WHY YOU AMONG THE
GENERATION THAT INCLUDES SENATOR
KAMALA HARRIS AND MAYOR
BUTTIGIEG.
>> I AM DAY ONE READY.
I SHAPED WASHINGTON MORE THAN IT
SHAPED ME, I HAVE PUT EFFORT IN
TO BRINGING MORE YOUNGER
CONGRESSMAN, I'M ONE OF THE
THREE PEOPLE IN THE HOUSE THAT
HAVE THE ACCESS TO THE M--
>> THE TORCH BEARERS HAVE NOT
EARNED THE TRUST OF THE PEOPLE
YET.
WHY DOES HE THINK THAT THE
YOUNGER GENERATION AND THE
AMERICAN ELECTORATE SHOULD TRUST
HIM AS THE TORCH BEARER?
>> THERE'S FOLKS THAT HAVE
SUGGESTED THAT THIS YOUNGER
GENERATION HAS NOT EARNED THE
TRUST YET TO HAVE THAT TORCH BE
PASSED, ESPECIALLY WHEN THEY ARE
IN THE ROLES THEY ARE AND DO NOT
HAVE MUCH CREDIBILITY TO THEIR
NAMES?
>> I WENT TO CONGRESS AT 31
YEARS OLD AND SAW A LOT OF
MILLIONAIRES AND PEOPLE
DISCONNECTED.
I WENT RIGHT TO WORK.
I AM ON THE HOUSE INTELLIGENCE
COMMITTEE.
I HAVE GONE TO THE WAR ZONE.
I HAVE SPOKEN WITH LEADERS.
I'M READY TAKE ONE.
>> WHY NOT SENATOR HARRIS?
>> I'M A BIG FAN OF SENATOR
HARRIS, I THINK WE BRING
DIFFERENT EXPERIENCES.
FOR ME, I BRING WORKING CLASS
BACKGROUNDS, BORN IN IOWA.
EDUCATED IN THE SOUTH.
MARRIED TO A HOOSIER.
ELECTED IN A DIVERSE PART OF
CALIFORNIA.
I KNOW THIS COUNTRY AND I CAN
REPRESENT IT AND BEAT DONALD
TRUMP.
>> THANK YOU.
MORGAN?
>> CONGRESSMAN SWALWELL, THANK
YOU SO MUCH, AND PLEASE, STAY IN
THE SPIN ROOM, WE WOULD LOVE TO
COME BACK TO YOU LATER.
AND AS YOU JUST HEARD FROM
CONGRESSMAN SWALWELL, ONE OF THE
BIG ISSUES THAT THE CANDIDATES
HIT EARLY WAS THEIR PLANS FOR
HEALTH CARE.
FROM OBAMA CARE TO HEALTH CARE
FOR ALL.
COVERING UNDOCUMENTED IMMIGRANTS
AND DOING AWAY WITH PRIVATE
HEALTH PLANS.
EVERYTHING WAS ON THE TABLE
TONIGHT.
AND THE CANDIDATES GOT RIGHT IN
TO IT, TAKE A LOOK.
>> WHO HERE WOULD GET RID OF
THEIR PRIVATE HEALTH INSURANCE
IN FAVOR OF GOVERNMENT RUN PLAN.
>> WHEN MY WIFE AND DAUGHTER
WERE KILLED IN AN AUTOMOBILE
ACCIDENT.
I CANNOT IMAGINE WHAT IT WOULD
BE LIKE TO NOT HAVE ADEQUATE
HEALTH CARE AVAILABLE.
WHEN MY SON CAME HOME FROM IRAQ
AND DIAGNOSED WITH CANCER AND
GIVEN MONTHS TO LIVE, I CANNOT
THINK OF WHAT HAPPENED, WHEN
THEY SAID, THE LAST SIX MONTHS
OF YOUR LIFE, YOU ARE ON YOUR
OWN, YOU HAVE USED UP YOUR TIME.
THE FACT OF THE MATTER IS, THE
QUICKEST, FASTEST WAY TO DO IT
IS BUILD TO OBAMA CARE.
WE WILL HAVE MEDICARE FOR ALL!
>> WHEN 10s OF MILLIONS PEOPLE
ARE PREPARED TO STAND UP AND
TELL THE INSURANCE COMPANIES AND
THE DRUG COMPANIES THAT THEIR
DAY IS GONE, THAT HEALTH CARE IS
A HUMAN RIGHT, NOT SOMETHING TO
MAKE HUGE PROFIT OFF OF.
>> THIS WAS PERSONAL FOR ME.
.
I STARTED OUT THIS YEAR DEALING
WITH A TERMINAL ILLNESS WITH
WITH MY FATHER.
THE THING WE HAD GOING FOR US,
WE NEVER HAD TO MAKE THE
DECISIONS BASED ON WHETHER IT
WAS GOING TO BANKRUPT OUR FAMILY
BECAUSE OF MEDICARE.
AND I WANT EVERY FAMILY TO HAVE
THAT SAME FREEDOM TO DO WHAT IS
MEDICALLY RIGHT .
>> LADIES AND GENTLEMEN, WE
DON'T HAVE A HEALTH CARE SYSTEM
IN THE UNITED STATES, WE HAVE A
SICKNESS CARE SYSTEM IN THE
UNITED STATES.
>> RAISE YOUR HAND IF YOUR
GOVERNMENT PLAN WOULD PROVIDE
COVERAGE FOR UNDOCUMENTED
IMMIGRANTS.
OKAY.
>> CANNOT LET PEOPLE WHO ARE
SICK, NO MATTER WHERE THEY ARE
FROM OR THEIR STATUS GO
UNCOVERED.
YOU CAN'T DO THAT.
IT'S GOT TO BE TAKEN CARE OF,
PERIOD, YOU HAVE TO.
IT'S THE HUMANE THING TO DO.
BUT HERE'S THE DEAL, THEY
CONTRIBUTE TO THE WELL-BEING OF
THE COUNTRY.
THEY INCREASE THE LIFE SPAN OF
SOCIAL SECURITY BECAUSE THEY
HAVE A JOB, THEY ARE PAYING IN
TO SOCIAL SECURITY TAX.
THAT'S WHAT THEY ARE DOING.
IT'S INCREASED THE LIFE SPAN.
THEY WOULD DO THE SAME THING IN
TERMS OF REVIEWSING THE OVERALL
COST OF HEALTH CARE BY THEM
BEING TREATED AND NOT WAIT UNTIL
THEY ARE IN AN EMERGENCY.
>> THE WAY TO BEAT PRESIDENT
TRUMP, AND McCONNELL WALKS IN,
WHO DO YOU WANT WHEN THE DOOR IS
CLOSING, TO FIGHT FOR WOMEN'S
RIGHTS?
I HAVE BEEN THE FIERCE ESTIMATE
ADVOCATE FOR WOMEN'S
REPRODUCTIVE FREEDOM FOR OVER A
DECADE, WHEN THAT DOOR CLOSES I
WILL GUARANTEE WOMEN'S
REPRODUCTIVE RIGHTS NO MATTER
WHAT.
>> THANK YOU.
>> AS YOU SAW, THE GLOVES WERE
OFF TONIGHT, HOW MANY OF THOSE
CLAIMS WERE TRUE?
WE ARE IN MIAMI RIGHT NOW, WHERE
WE HAVE BEEN FACT CHECKING THE
CANDIDATES.
WHAT CAUGHT YOUR EYE TONIGHT?
>> HEY, MORGAN.
TONIGHT WAS DEFINITELY A MUCH
DICEYER NIGHT, A LOT OF
DIFFERENT FACTS, SOME OF THEM
RIGHT AND SOME NOT RIGHT.
ONE OF THE FIRST ONES THAT
JUMPED OUT, KAMALA HARRIS SAYING
THAT THE ECONOMY IS NOT WORKING
FOR SOME PEOPLE BECAUSE PEOPLE
ARE WORKING MULTIPLE JOBS.
THIS IS SOMETHING YOU HEAR A LOT
FROM THE LEFT BECAUSE THE
ECONOMY LOOKS PRETTITY GOOD AND
IT'S ONE OF TRUMP'S BIGGEST
CLAIMS FOR RE-ELECTION.
BUT THE BUREAU OF LABOR
STATISTICS TRACKED HOW MANY
PEOPLE WORK MULTIPLE JOBS, 5% OF
AMERICA.
THAT IS 8 MILLION PEOPLE, SO A
LOT OF PEOPLE, YOU CAN SAY
THERE'S A LOT OF PEOPLE DOING
IT, BUT IT DOWN SLIGHTLY FROM 20
YEARS AGO.
A COUPLE OF THEY ARE THINGS,
MARE PETE BUTTIGIEG TALKING
ABOUT THE PATHWAY TO CITIZENSHIP
AND THE VAST MAJORITY OF PEOPLE
SUPPORT THAT.
A KIND OF PATHWAY TO
CITIZENSHIP.
IT'S TRUE.
THE GALLUP POLL SAID 80% OF
AMERICANS FEEL THAT WAY.
AND MEDICARE FOR ALL DOESN'T GET
RID OF ALL PRIVATE INSURANCE, IT
DOES FOR EVERYTHING BUT COSMETIC
CARE.
WHICH IS WHAT PEOPLE DO NOT
THINK OF FOR INSURANCE PURPOSE
AND THE BIG ONE IS BIDEN AND
BUSSING.
SO KAMALA HARRIS WENT AFTER HIM,
FOR THE TOPIC FROM YEARS AGO.
SHE IS CAREFUL WHEN WHAT THEY
SAID, THAT HE WORKED WITH AVOWED
SEGREGATIONISTS TO OPPOSE
BUSSING.
AND IT'S ONE OF THE THINGS THAT
IS HITTING HIM HARD AS HE TRIES
TO SAY, HE CAN TAKE THE BANNER
FOR HIS PARTY.
BUT IF PEOPLE IN HIS PARTY SAY
MAYBE HE IS NOT WHERE THE
MAINSTREAM OF THE PARTY IS NOW.
>> THAT WAS INTERESTING, THAT
WAS THE MOMENT FOR EVERY
PANELIST, THAT CAUGHT THEIR EYE,
THE QUESTION ON BUSSING AND THE
FACT THAT SENATOR HARRIS DID
HOLD HAD HIS FEET TO THE FIRE.
SO, WE DEFINITELY APPRECIATE YOU
CLEARING THAT UP FOR US.
>>> RIGHT NOW, WE WILL TAKE A
QUICK BREAK, WE HOPE YOU STAY
WITH US FOR SPECIAL COVERAGE OF
THE FIRST PRESIDENTIAL
DEMOCRATIC DEBATE, RIGHT HERE ON
NBC NEWS NOW.
>>> WELCOME BACK TO NBC NEWS
NOW, LET'S GO STRAIGHT WHERE WE
ARE WATCHING THE DEBATE WITH THE
COLLEGE STUDENTS.
WHO DO THE STUDENTS THINK
CAPTURED THEIR ATTENTION?
>> OH, MAN, IT WAS A LIVELY ROOM
IN HERE TONIGHT.
A LOT OF HOT PICKS.
AND I WILL ASK FOR THEM NOW.
YOU HAD A LOT TO SAY WHEN WE
WERE WATCHING AND I WANT THE TOP
LINE REACTIONS RIGHT NOW.
WHAT STOOD OUT AND WHAT WAS THE
TAKE ON THE DEBATE OVERALL,
COMPARED TO LAST NIGHT?
>> I THINK VICE PRESIDENT BIDEN
AND SENATOR -- BUCKLED UNDER THE
PRESSURE.
WHEN THE HEAT WAS TURNED UP,
THEY COULD NOT HOLD THEIR OWN.
THAT WAS BIG, AND FOR SOMEBODY
LIKE VICE PRESIDENT BIDEN, HE
IS, YOU KNOW, KAMALA HARRIS WAS
TOUGH ON HIM TONIGHT.
THE PRESIDENT WILL BE TOUGH ON
HIM IN A GENERAL ELECTION.
WILL HE HANDLE THAT?
>> SPEAKING OF KAMALA HARRIS.
I FELT THAT EVEN THOUGH TONIGHT
A LOT OF THE CANDIDATES WERE
ABLE TO COME AT JOE BIDEN FOR
HIS CONTROVERSIAL PAST, I THINK
THAT KAMALA BENEFITTED FROM
PEOPLE NOT PICKING UP ON HER
PAST AS SHE TALKED ABOUT HER
ROLE IN REGARDS TO PRISON REFORM
AND IMMIGRATION.
I FEEL LIKE OTHER CANDIDATES
SHOULD HAVE HELD HER FEET TO THE
FIRE AS THEY HELD JOE BIDEN TO
THAT STANDARD AS WELL.
THAT SHOULD BE INTERESTING TO
SEE WHAT IS GOING TO HAPPEN IN
THE FUTURE.
HOWEVER, I DO FEEL THAT SHE WAS
ABLE TO MAKE A VERY STRONG
QUOTES THAT ARE GOING TO BE
HEADLINERS AND FROM THAT, PEOPLE
ARE GOING TO BE UNDER THE
IMPRESSION THAT SHE QUOTE
UNQUOTE WON THE DEBATE.
I, HOWEVER DON'T THINK SO.
>> YOU DON'T THINK PEOPLE
CHECKED HER ENOUGH.
BUT THE FACT THAT THAT DID NOT
HAPPEN AND SHE WAS ABLE TO HOLD
JOE BIDEN'S FEET TO THE FIRE AND
NOBODY CAME BACK AT HER, WHAT
DOES THAT SAY ABOUT HER
PERFORMANCE?
>> DEFINITELY VERY WORRYSOME, IN
THAT REGARD, AND ESPECIALLY, I'M
GOING TO KEEP GOING BACK TO HER
STATEMENTS ABOUT PRISON REFORM.
SHE HAS A CONTROVERSIAL PAST
ABOUT THAT AND THE FACT THAT
NOBODY WAS ABLE TO BRING IT UP,
AND SHE WAS ABLE TO KIND OF
PAINT THE NARRATIVE OF
INDIVIDUAL THAT HAS ALWAYS BEEN
FIGHTING FOR THESE RIGHTS IS
SOMEWHAT A PROBLEM TO ME.
>> DID SHE RESONATE WITH YOU
GUYS TONIGHT?
>> IT WAS IMPRESSIVE WHAT SHE
HAD TO SAY.
AND THE CURRENT POSITIONS AND
THINGS SHE SAID RESONATED WITH
ME.
BUT I DEFINITELY FEEL LIKE WHAT
SHE BROUGHT ON OUT OF JOE BIDEN
WAS LIKE -- WAS A LOT OF
DISAPPOINTMENT THAT I FELT THAT
HE DOUBLED DOWN ON THE PAST
POSITION.
SHE WAS ABLE TO BRING OUT THE
NASTY RACIAL TENSIONS THERE.
AND THE FACT THAT HE STILL IS
KIND OF HOLDING SOME OF THOSE
OLD VIEWS TODAY.
SO --
>> YEAH, I MEAN, YOU GUYS WHEN I
ASKED YOU ABOUT JOE BIDEN BEFORE
THE DEBATE.
I ASKED WHO WAS EXCITED, NOBODY
RAISED THEIR HANDS.
WHAT DID HIS PERFORMANCE TONIGHT
DO TO CHANGE YOUR OPINION OF
HIM?
>> HE IS HE WAS A DISTRACTION, I
FEEL LIKE THE ENTIRE DEBATE,
BECAUSE A LOT OF THE CANDIDATES
WERE USING THEIR TIME TO ATTACK
HIM AND GOAD HIM AND HE SPENT
THE TIME DEFENDING HIMSELF,
SAYING THIS IS WHAT I DID, THIS
IS WHAT I DID.
AND HE RARELY TALKED ABOUT WHAT
HE PLANNED TO DO.
THERE WAS NOT A LOT OF SUBSTANCE
TO THAT.
I WAS MORE INTERESTED IN THE
CANDIDATES LIKE PETE BUTTIGIEG
AND ANDREW YANG, THEY WERE MORE
FOCUSED ON WHAT THEY WERE
PLANNING TO DO.
THEY DID NOT GET AS MANY
OPPORTUNITIES TO SPEAK AS THE
HEADLINERS THEY USED THEIR TIME
TO EXPLAIN WHAT THEY PLANNED TO
DO.
>> RIGHT, WE TALKED ABOUT HOW
YOU GUYS ARE INTERESTED IN
HEARING SUBSTANCE AND POLICY,
YOU TALKED ABOUT WANTING MORE
CIVIL DISCOURSE, TRYING TO
ELEVATE THE RHETORIC.
HOW DID THE CANDIDATES DO WITH
THAT TONIGHT?
AND COMPARE IT TO LAST NIGHT?
>> I FELT THAT THE MOST
DISAPPOINTING THING ABOUT THE
NIGHT, WE DID GET TO SEE THEIR
PERSONALITIES BUT NOT THEIR
POLICIES AND HOW THEY
DISTINGUISH THEMSELVES THROUGH
THE POLICY.
THAT IS NOT WHAT WE GOT TO SEE.
AND I THINK THAT WAS SOMETHING
THAT I DID NOT KNOW WHAT THEIR
PLAN IS TO BE AND HOW THEY SET
THEMSELVES APART FROM EACH
OTHER.
>> I THINK IT'S CLEAR WHAT THEY
ARE AGAINST.
THEY ARE AGAINST TRUMP, THEY ARE
AGAINST WALL STREET.
WHAT I LIKED ABOUT KAMALA HARRIS
AND PETE BUTTIGIEG, THEY WERE
FOR SOMETHING.
KAMALA HARRIS WANTED TO GIVE A
CREDIT TO PEOPLE MAKING UNDER
$100,000 A YEAR.
THAT WAS IMPRESSIVE.
IT MADE HER A STAND OUT AS
WORKING FOR THE MIDDLE CLASS.
THAT'S WHAT I WANTED TO SEE.
>> DID YOU GET CLARITY FROM
TONIGHT OR BOTH NIGHTS IN TERMS
OF WHO WILL GET YOUR SUPPORT AND
ABLE TO LAST IN THE RACE?
>> I THINK IT'S FUNNY HOW
TONIGHT WAS SUPPOSED TO BE THE
NIGHT WHERE INDIVIDUALS WERE
MORE EXCITED BECAUSE OF THE BIG
NAME CANDIDATES THAT WERE
GATHERED TOGETHER.
UNFORTUNATELY, I PERSONALLY
BELIEVE THAT YESTERDAY'S DEBATE
WAS A LOT MORE BASED ON ACTUAL
POLICY THAT THE CANDIDATES
WANTED TO FOCUS ON.
ESPECIALLY THE CONVERSATIONS
THAT WE WERE ALL HAVING BEFORE.
AND ESPECIALLY WHAT SHE SAID,
UNFORTUNATELY TONIGHT IT WAS ALL
ABOUT TRUMP.
TRUMP, TRUMP, TRUMP.
AND AGAIN, IT'S LIKE, YES.
WE ARE ALREADY KNOW WHAT TRUMP
IS, WHAT HE STANDS FOR.
WE GET IT, WHAT ARE YOU GOING TO
DO AS AN INDIVIDUAL TO --
INDIVIDUAL TO HELP US.
WE ARE NOT GOING TO JUST ACCEPT
WHAT YOU SAY TO US.
IF YOU GET IN OFFICE, WE WANT
YOU TO STAND BY.
>> NIGHT ONE, ACTUALLY, SEEMS
LIKE IT WON WITH YOU GUYS.
THAT, THAT TOOK THE CAKE.
SO, WHO WON FROM BOTH NIGHTS?
LET'S START WITH YOU.
>> NO ONE.
>> TONIGHT, NO ONE WON.
YESTERDAY WAS --
>> I THINK -- WON FOR BOTH
NIGHTS.
HIS PERSONALITY AND POLICIES.
>> KAMALA HARRIS TONIGHT, BUT I
WOULD SAY OVERALL PROBABLY --
PREVAILED.
>> I THINK SECRETARY --
>> I THOUGHT CASTRO DID STAND
OUT DURING THE LAST DEBATE, I
THOUGHT ELIZABETH WARREN DID A
PRETTY GOOD JOB.
>> WHICH ONE BETWEEN BOTH
NIGHTS?
>> I LIKED CASTRO, BECAUSE I WAS
NOT EXPECTING ANYTHING OUT OF
HIM AND HE STOOD OUT DURING THE
DEBATE.
AND PETE BUTTIGIEG DID A GOOD
JOB.
AND ANDREW YANG DID A GOOD JOB.
>> I THINK KAMALA HARRIS DID
WELL IN BOTH NIGHTS OF THE
DEBATE.
I LIKE THAT SHE STOOD FOR
SOMETHING CLEARLY AND I LIKE
THAT SHE WAS A STRONG SPEAKER.
SHE ASSERTED HERSELFER AND THAT
IS SOMETHING THAT I WANT TO SEE
IN A PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE.
ESPECIALLY WHEN THEY TAKE ON
TRUMP.
>> WOW.
SO, STILL A PRETTY HEAVY VOTE
FOR CASTRO.
BUT KAMALA GOT THE SPOTLIGHT
TONIGHT.
SO, THREW HAVE IT.
THE DEBATE IS DONE AND WE WILL
SEE HOW THE REST GO.
THANK YOU SO MUCH AND THANK YOU
AGAIN FOR YOUR PANEL OF
STUDENTS.
>> SOMETHING THAT JOY REALLY
STRUCK ME.
I WANT TO BRING IN OUR GUEST
AGAIN.
JOY, WAS A YOUNG WOMAN IN THE
FRONT THAT SAID, KAMALA DID NOT
ACTUALLY WIN BECAUSE KAMALA DID
NOT GET A DOSE OF HER OWN
MEDICINE.
NO ONE DID THAT TO HER ON OUR
PROSECUTION RECORD IN CRIMINAL
JUSTICE.
IS THAT TRUE OR FALSE?
DID SHE WIN BECAUSE SHE DID NOT
TAKE THE HEAT HERSELF?
>> THAT MAY BE TRUE.
I THOUGHT SHE STOLE THE SHOW.
I THINK SHE CAME OFF ASSERTIVE.
CONFIDENT, SHE ANSWERED EVERY
QUESTION WITH A, YOU KNOW, A
DIRECT WAY.
I THINK THEY CAME OUT ON TOP.
I WALKED AWAY PERSONALLY HAVING
A BETTER IDEA WHERE SHE STOOD ON
ISSUES.
>> WHAT ABOUT, JACKIE, HER
CRIMINAL JUSTICE RECORD.
>> SHE HAS RECEIVED A LOT OF
SCRUTINY FOR NOT BEING
PROGRESSIVE ENOUGH.
SHE WAS ABLE TO EXPLOIT A FEW
OPPORTUNITIES IN ORDER TO TOUT
HER RECORD AS ATTORNEY GENERAL
WHEN SHE CALLED OUT BIDEN ON THE
OBAMA ADMINISTRATION'S TRACK
RECORD WITH INTRODUCING -- WHICH
WAS ONE POLICY OF HER FORMER
PRESIDENT THAT SHE WAS NOT IN
FAVOR OF.
BUT, THAT WAS THE BENEFIT OF
PREPARATION.
I MEAN, SHE, WHEN HAD YOU ARE ON
THE OFFENSIVE, YOU DO NOT HAVE
TO ANSWER FOR THE THINGS THAT
PEOPLE ARE NOT ATTACKING YOU
FOR.
AND IT WAS CLEAR, THAT THIS WAS
SOMETHING, ATTACKING BIDEN ON
THE OPPOSITION, WAS SOMETHING
THAT SHE HAD TEE'ED UP AND SHE
WENT FOR IT AND DID NOT LET UP
ON BIDEN.
THAT WAS A DEFINING MOMENT OF
THE WEEK.
THAT WILL BE THE DEFINING MOMENT
OF THE ELECTION SO FAR.
>> AND SHE MADE IT PERSONAL.
>> SHE DID.
>> AND WHAT ABOUT BUTTIGIEG,
NANCY, WHEN HE WAS ASKED ABOUT
WHY THE POLICE FORCE BACK IN
SOUTH BEND WAS NOT DIVERSE, HE
SAID PLAINLY, I COULD NOT GET IT
DONE.
WAS THAT REFRESHINGLY HONEST?
OR WAS THAT ENOUGH?
>> IT WAS HONEST, BUT IT WAS NOT
ENOUGH.
HE FELL SHORT.
I MEAN, YOU GAVE ME IN ALL OF
THE REASONS WHY IT DID NOT GET
DONE FT.
BUT YOU DID NOT GIVE ME, WHAT
WILL YOU DO DIFFERENTLY?
RIGHT?
YOU ARE GOING TO HAVE TO BREAK
THIS OPEN.
YOU CANNOT WALK IN TO THIS NEXT
STAGE OF OUR PRESIDENCY, WITHOUT
BEING ABLE TO ANSWER THAT
QUESTION IN A VERY CONCRETE A
WAY.
WHAT IS YOUR PLAN TO DO IT
DIFFERENTLY?
I DID NOT HEAR THAT AT ALL.
>> JACKIE, WHAT DID YOU THINK
WHEN CONGRESSMAN SWALWELL LOOKED
AT HIM ANDSAID, WELL, FIRE YOUR
POLICE CHIEF AND HE DID NOT SAY
ANYTHING.
>> RIGHT, AND I THINK THAT WAS
INDICATIVE OF MAYOR PETE'S
APPROACH TO POLITICS IN GENERAL.
LET'S SEE THE PROCESS PLAY OUT.
WE ARE CONDUCTING AN
INVESTIGATION AND NOT COMING TO
RASH DECISIONS.
BUT, I'M NOT NECESSARILY FOR THE
BEST OF ANSWERS THAT THE PUBLIC
WANTS TO SEE RIGHT NOW,
ESPECIALLY IN AFTER ERA OF THE
POLITICS WHERE THINGS ARE
PRETTY, ARE NOT RULES BASED.
AT LEAST IN TRUMP'S WORLD.
I THINK COMPARING HIM TO
SOMEBODY LIKE CASTRO, WHO
YESTERDAY, REALLY GOT AT HIS
CRIMINAL JUSTICE REFORM AND HIS
PLEASING REFORM AND WAS ABLE TO
TOUT ALL OF THE POLICIES, MAYOR
PETE WAS NOT ABLE TO SHOW THE
SAME, AND SO, TO ME, THE
ACCOUNTABILITY IS A STEP
FORWARDER AND A BIG CONTRAST TO
BIDEN.
WHEN YOU -- WHEN YOU TEE HIM UP
NEXT TO CASTRO, YOU KNOW, THAT
WAS SOMETHING WHEN THEY ARE
SITTING NEXT TO EACH OTHER, IT
WILL SHOW.
>> ONE THING WE HAD SPECKS ON.
HE HAD VERY STRONG WORDS.
HE SAID, CHINA IS USING
TECHNOLOGY FOR THE PERFECTION OF
DICTATOR SHIP.
DID HE REALLY LAYOUT A
DEMOCRATIC ALTERNATIVE TO
DEALING WITH CHINA?
>> NO, NOT REALLY.
YOU HEARD OTHERS MENTIONING THE
PUSH BACK AGAINST CHINA TO
CONFRONT THEIR BEHAVIOR.
CERTAINLY YOU HEARD THE MENTION
OF INTELLECTUAL PROPERTY, THE
ISSUE THAT THEY CAN RALLY
AROUND.
I DID NOT HEAR MUCH SPECIFICS
WITH ANY FOREIGN POLICY.
>> WHAT ABOUT WHEN HE TALKED
ABOUT THE PATHWAY TO
CITIZENSHIP.
HE SAID THERE'S 11 MILLION
PEOPLE, BUT THE WHITE HOUSE HAS
DIVIDED US ON THE COMMON GROUND
ISSUE.
WHAT DO YOU THINK?
>> IT'S A COMMON GROUND ISSUE,
WITH A KMOND BIG END GOAL.
WE DISAGREE IN THE DETAILS.
WE HAVE BEEN DIVIDED ON THE
ISSUE FOR A LONG TIME.
SO, I THINK ONE OF THE THINGS
THAT CAME UP, WAS THE OBAMA
RECORD, THEY CALL IT THE
DEPORTATION CHIEF.
THE DEPORTER IN CHIEF.
WAS NOT FAMILY SEPARATION, IT'S
DEPORTATION.
IT'S A DIFFERENCE THERE AND WHAT
IS NOW, IS VIOLENTLY AGGRESSIVE
WITH CHILDREN BEING TAKEN FROM
FAMILIES AND CHILDREN DYING.
WHAT IS NOT BEING CALLED OUT IN
ALL OF THE THINGS FROM THE
CRIMINAL JUSTICES REFORM TO THE
BUSSING SITUATION AND THE
IMMIGRATION, THE BIG ISSUE ON
THE TABLE IS AROUND RACIAL
EQUITY AND NOBODY IS CALLING IT
OUT.
NOBODY WANTS TO TALK ABOUT IT
FOR WHAT IT IS.
IT'S THE ISSUE OF RACIAL EQUITY.
AND UNTIL, WE GET COMFORTABLE,
ABOUT TALKING ABOUT IT, WE ARE
GOING TO CONTINUE GOING AROUND
IN CIRCLES AND IT WILL SURFACE
IN DIFFERENT WAYS AND IN
DIFFERENT POLICY ISSUES BUT THE
UNKMRT WE SAW FOR BIDEN NOT
KNOWING HOW TO RESPOND TO THAT
WAS HURTFUL CONVERSATION TO
BUTTIGIEG NOT BEING ABLE TO TALK
ABOUT, I DIDN'T GET IT DONE, IT
WAS PULLING BACK AND NOT WANTING
TO COME BACK OUT.
MARIANNE WILLIAMSON CAME OUT AND
SAID, LOOK, I DON'T THINK THAT
AMERICA IS RACIST, BUT I THINK
THEY ARE WOEFULLY UNDER EDUCATED
ON THE ISSUE OF RACE.
AND KAMALA SAID, NO, I ARE WILL
FINISH ANSWERING THAT QUESTION.
BECAUSE, OH, BY THE WAY WITH,
I'M THE ONLY PERSON OF COLOR
STANDING ON THE STAGE.
DO YOU THINK THEY WERE MORE
AGGRESSIVE ON ADDRESSING THE
ISSUE?
>> MARIANNE WILLIAMSON WAS
BRINGING UP REPARATIONS.
SHE SAID THAT IT WOULD BE A WAY
TO ADDRESS THE SYSTEMATIC
INEQUALITY THAT EXISTS IN
AMERICA RIGHT NOW.
WHAT I THINK WAS SO EFFECTIVE,
KAMALA SAYING, HAVING SO MANY
PERSONALER ANECDOTES THE VISION
AND TWEETS OF BEING A YOUNG GIRL
AND DEALING WITH BUSSING.
TO ME, IT WAS SOMETHING THAT
REALLY, REALLY RESONATED.
>> BECAUSE ON THE SAME ISSUE OF
REPARATION.
YOU MENTION THE BREAKFAST CLUB,
EVERYONE HAS BEEN ASKED AND THE
HOST OF THE SHOW WILL SAY, THEY
HAVE NOT HEARD ANY SPECIFICS.
YOU SAY IT'S IMPORTANT, IN
THEORY, WHAT -- WHAT DOES IT
LOOK LIKE?
IS IT A ISSUE ADDRESSING OR A
CHECK?
STAY WITH US HERE ON NBC NEWS
>>> LAST NIGHT, DECK DEMOCRATIC
CANDIDATES HELD BACK MORE WHEN
THEY WERE REFERENCING PRESIDENT
TRUMP, BUT TONIGHT WAS A VERY
DIFFERENT STORY.
>> LET ME TELL YOU SOMETHING, I
HEAR THAT QUESTION, WHERE WAS
THAT QUESTION WHEN THE
REPUBLICANS AND DONALD TRUMP
PASSED THE TAX BILL THAT
BENEFITTED THE TOP 1%.
>> THE AMERICAN PEOPLE
UNDERSTAND THAT TRUMP IS A
PHONY, THAT TRUMP IS A
PATHOLOGICAL LIAR AND A RACIST
AND HE LIED TO THE AMERICAN
PEOPLE DURING HIS CAMPAIGN.
HE SAID THAT HE WAS GOING TO
STAND UP FOR WORKING FAMILIES.
WELL, PRESIDENT TRUMP, YOU ARE
NOT STANDING FOR WORKING
FAMILIES WHEN YOU ARE TRYING TO
THROW 32 MILLION PEOPLE OFF THE
HEALTH CARE THAT THEY HAVE AND
THAT 83% OF YOUR TAX BENEFITS GO
TO THE TOP 1%.
THAT IS HOW WE BEAT TRUMP.
WE EXPOSE HIM FOR THE FRAUD THAT
HE IS.
>> WHAT DOES DONALD TRUMP DO?
HE SAYS GO BACK TO WHERE YOU
CAME FROM, THAT IS NOT
REFLECTIVE OF OUR AMERICA AND
OUR VALUES AND IT HAS TO END.
>> WHAT PRESIDENT TRUMP HAS
DONE, IS NOT ONLY ATTACK THE
CHILDREN AND DEMONIZE THE
IMMIGRANTS HE IS ATTACKING A
BASIC PRINCIPAL OF AMERICA'S
MORALE CORE.
WE OPEN OUR HEARTS TO THE
STRANGER.
THE WORST THING HE HAS DONE, HE
HAS DIVERTED THE FUNDS AWAY FROM
CROSS BORDER TERRORISM AND HE
HAS GIVEN THAT MONEY TO THE
FOUR -- IN PRESIDENT OBAMA DID A
HECK OF A JOB.
COMPARE HIM TO WHAT THIS GUY IS
DOING IS IMMORALE.
THIS PRESIDENT THOUGH, FOR
IMMIGRANTS, THERE'S NOTHING HE
WILL NOT DO TO SEPARATE A
FAMILY, CAGE A CHILD, OR ERASE
THEIR EXISTENCE.
>> OH, ONE OF THOR WORST THINGS
ABOUT PRESIDENT TRUMP THAT HE
HAS DONE TO THE COUNTRY, IS HE
HAS TORN APART THE MORALE FABRIC
OF WHO WE ARE.
WHEN HE STARTED TO SEPARATE
CHILDREN AT THE BORDER FROM
THEIR PARENTS.
THE FACT THAT SEVEN CHILDREN
HAVE DIED IN HIS CUSTODY.
THE FACT HAD THAT DOZENS OF
CHILDREN HAVE BEEN SEPARATED
FROM THEIR PARENTS AND THEY HAVE
NO PLAN TO REUNITE THEM.
>> ON DAY ONE, WE TAKE OUT OUR
EXECUTIVE ORDER PEN AND RESCIND
EVERYTHING ON THIS ISSUE THAT
TRUMP HAS DONE.
>> WHAT IS THE GREATEST NATIONAL
SECURITY THREAT TO THE UNITED
STATES?
IT'S DONALD TRUMP.
AND I WILL IT WILL YOU WHY.
AND I WILL TELL YOU WHY.
I AGREE, CLIMBED CHANGE IS A
THREAT.
HE DENIES THE SCIENCE.
YOU WANT TO TALK ABOUT NORTH
KOREA, REAL THREAT IN TERMS OF
NUCLEAR ARSENAL, HE EMBRACES KIM
JONG-UN.
>> MR. PRESIDENT, IF YOU ARE
LISTENING, YOU HAVE HARNESSED
FEAR FOR POLITICAL PURPOSES AND
ONLY LOVE CAN CAST THAT OUT.
I, I HAVE A FEELING YOU KNOW
WHAT YOU ARE DOING, I WILL
HARNESS LOVE FOR POLITICAL
PURPOSES AND I WILL MEET YOU ON
THE FIELD AND SIR, LOVE WILL
WIN.
>> SO, FOR FINAL THOUGHTS.
LET GET BACK TO THE PANEL.
WAS IT STRATEGIC AND WAS IT
SMART TO MAKE TRUMP MORE OF THE
FOCUS TONIGHT?
>> WELL TRUMP ENJOYED IT.
HE WAS LIVE TWEETING.
HE DID NOT SAY IT WAS BORING
THIS TIME.
AND YOU SAW HIM GO AFTER THE
DEMOCRATS FOR THEIR POSITIONS ON
PROVIDING HEALTH CARE TO
UNDOCUMENTED IMMIGRANTS AND
CROSSING THE BORDER.
>> WHAT DID YOU THINK?
I THINK THEY NEED TO TALK ABOUT
TRUMP TONIGHT.
I THINK THAT WAS MISSING FROM
LAST NIGHT AND YOU NEED TO TALK
ABOUT DONALD TRUMP BECAUSE
NOTHING ABOUT THE MOMENT IS
NORMAL.
>> WHAT DID YOU THINK, DID YOU
FEEL LIKE THIS TONIGHT, GAVE
DONALD TRUMP MORE FODER BECAUSE
OF THE DIVISION?
>> I THINK WHEN YOU THINK ABOUT
THE THING.
IF I'M A DEMOCRAT, I'M CONCERNED
ABOUT A COUPLE OF THINGS.
WHO CAN BEAT DONALD TRUMP IN THE
STATES WHERE IT MATTERS.
IF YOU LOOK AT PENNSYLVANIA,
TRUMP BEAT HILARY CLINTON BY
44,000 VOTES AND IN FLORIDA BY
100,000 VOTES.
THAT IS NOT A WIDE MARGIN THAT
IS NOT BEATABLE.
IF I'M GOING TO MAKE THE CASE
THAT I CAN BEAT THIS GUY, HOW DO
I MAKE UP THE MARGINS?
THAT HAS TO BE THE QUESTION WHEN
WHEN YOU ARE THINKING ABOUT
POLITICS.
>> IT WAS NOT JUST ABOUT
FOCUSING ON DONALD TRUM.
IT WAS ABOUT FOCUSING ON EACH
OTHER.
AND THEN, WE SAW A SIMILAR
TACTIC TONIGHT AS LAST NIGHT,
THESE GUYS WERE POLLING IN THE
SINGLE DIGITS ON THE END OF THE
STAGE, THEY WERE COMING FOR THE
GUYS IN THE CENTER OF THE STAGE.
WE SAW -- GO
FOR BIDEN, OR BENNETT GOING FOR
BERNIE.
DID THAT WORK?
>> I THINK IT IS HARD TO KEEP
TRACK WHERE PEOPLE STAND ON THE
ISSUE.
TO STAND OUT, YOU HAVE TO GO
AFTER THE GUY IN CHARGE.
YOU ARE RUNNING FOR PRESIDENT,
YOU ARE NOT RUNNING TO JUST BE
THERE.
ONE OFFICE.
AND YOU KNOW, I THINK GOING BACK
TO THE THING I SAID EARLIER WITH
ABOUT KA PAULA HARRIS MUCH.
IT'S IMPORTANT TO SHOW UP AND
ACT LIKE YOU ARE THERE TO BE
PRESIDENT.
YOU ARE NOT THERE TO BE VICE
PRESIDENT, YOU ARE NOT RUNNING
JUST TO UP YOUR NAME
RECOGNITION.
YOU ARE RUNNING TO DO THE JOB
AND I THINK GOING AFTER BIDEN
DIRECTLY SHOWS YOU ARE WILLING
TO TAKE ON SOMEBODY WHO WAS A
VICE PRESIDENT.
>>BUT WAS IT AFFECTIVE?
>> I DON'T THINK THAT ANYBODY
STOOD OUT AS MUCH AS SECRETARY
CASTRO DID LAST NIGHT.
YOU SAW BENNETT AND HICKENLOOPER
AND THEY WENT AFTER MAYOR PETE.
>> I CONSIDER HER IN A DIFFERENT
TIER, GOING AFTER THE BIG
CANDIDATES.
KAMALA IS IN A LEAGUE OF HER
OWN.
BUT, YOU KNOW, MICHAEL BENNETT
AND THE LOWER TIER CANDIDATES
DID NOT DO ANYTHING TO HELP
THEIR THIRD AND FOURTH ROUND
DEBATE.
>> PEOPLE ARE TUNED IN AND
CURIOUS.
WAS THERE ANYTHING THAT YOU
HEARD TONIGHT THAT WOULD REALLY
JAZZ UP THE PEOPLE WHO STAY HOME
BACK IN 2016?
>> I'M GOING TO BE HONEST, NOT
YET, BUT IT'S EARLY.
RIGHT?
THERE'S SO MANY DEBATES TO COME.
CANDIDATES HAVE TO CONTINUE TO
BUILD OUT THE OPERATIONAL
INFRASTRUCTURES.
WE DO NOT PAY A LOT OF ATTENTION
TO THIS.
DEBATE PERFORMANCES ARE GREAT,
BUT ARE YOU LAYING THE
FOUNDATION, WHICH IS HOW YOU
TARGET, HOW YOU MOBILIZE A
CONSTITUENTSY THAT PROPELS YOU
TO VICTORY.
AND IT'S TOO EARLY TO PREDICT
THIS YET.
>> YEAH, THEY ARE FOCUSED ON THE
PROGRESSIVE VOTERS AND THE
QUESTION IS, BY TAKING THAT
STANCE, WILL IT BE HARDER TO
APPEAL TO VOTERS IN THE GENERAL.
>> AND THE QUESTION IS, WILL IT
WORK WE HAVE A HARD BREAK IN A
MOMENT.
I WANT TO THANK EACH OF YOU FOR
COMING IN TONIGHT.
AND ALL THOSE THAT ARE NOT ON
THE COUCH.
AND ALL OF THE STUDENTS AND OF
COURSE, ALL OF YOU AT HOME.
THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR WATCHING,
THE FIRST DEMOCRATIC
PRESIDENTIAL DEBATE.
DON'T GO ANYWHERE, WE WILL
REPLAY NIGHT TWO OF THE FIRST
DEMOCRATIC DEBATE, JUST COMING
UP NEXT.
OTHERWISE, TUNE IN TOMORROW AT
3:00 P.M. EASTERN FOR MORE ON
NBC NEWS NOW.
THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR SPENDING
YOUR EVENING WITH US.